<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Constantinus redivivus, or, A full account of the wonderful providences, and unparallell'd successes that have all along attended the glorious enterprises of the heroical prince, William the 3d, now King of Great Britain, &amp;c. wherein are many curious passages relating to the intrigues of Lewis the 14th, &amp;c. carried on here, and elsewhere, never printed before, &amp;c. / by Mr. John Whittel ...</title>
            <author>Whittel, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 249 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 113 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65948</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2040</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8794</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11983627</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11983627</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51909</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65948)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51909)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 523:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Constantinus redivivus, or, A full account of the wonderful providences, and unparallell'd successes that have all along attended the glorious enterprises of the heroical prince, William the 3d, now King of Great Britain, &amp;c. wherein are many curious passages relating to the intrigues of Lewis the 14th, &amp;c. carried on here, and elsewhere, never printed before, &amp;c. / by Mr. John Whittel ...</title>
                  <author>Whittel, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[27], 199 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Tho. Harbin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [27].</note>
                  <note>First edition.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:51909:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 16. 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Char. Heron.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51909:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſtantinus Redivivus:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR, A FULL ACCOUNT OF THE Wonderful Providences, AND Unparallell'd Succeſſes</p>
            <p>That have all along Attended the Glorious Enterpriſes of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical Prince, <hi>William</hi> the 3d, Now KING of <hi>Great Britain, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein are Many Curious Paſſages, Relating to the INTRIGUES of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Carried on Here, and Elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; Never Printed before, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>JOHN WHITTEL,</hi> Sometime the onely <hi>Engliſh</hi> Chaplain to the Army.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and ſold by <hi>Tho. Harbin,</hi> at the <hi>Wheat-Sheafe,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Golden-Tun-Tavern</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51909:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51909:2"/>
            <head>TO THE QUEEN'S <hi>Moſt Excellent Majeſty.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Auguſt Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT being now about IX Years ſince I was firſt Converſant with Military Perſons, and heard the Sound of <hi>Drums</hi> and <hi>Trumpets,</hi> as well in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Netherlands,</hi> as Here, and in <hi>Ireland.</hi> And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:51909:3"/>the Honour to Bear in my Body the Marks of Fervent Zeal, and Unſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Loyalty to Your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty's; Which is, I confeſs, the <hi>Principal Thing</hi> in this World I rejoyce in, and value my ſelf upon. It hath ſo far encourag'd me, as to caſt theſe Unpoliſht Papers at Your Majeſty's Feet; Containing, an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Miraculous Providences,</hi> and <hi>Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Succeſſes,</hi> That have all along attended the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Enterpriſes of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb facs="tcp:51909:3"/>King <hi>William,</hi> for the Publick Good of <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> But eſpecially of the <hi>Britiſh Empire,</hi> together with the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Netherlands,</hi> and of the <hi>Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> as in the Reſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſo particularly in <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> it's moſt Secure and Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Seat: And hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to beg Your Majeſty's Moſt Gracious Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance thereof. I cannot ſay of this <hi>Enchiridium,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> ſometime ſaid to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of the <hi>Centurion,</hi> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:51909:4"/>it Treats of ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a Subject,) <hi>Dignum eſt,</hi> It is worthy that Your Majeſty ſhould accept it: But, I may truly ſpeak in the <hi>Centurion</hi>'s own Words, <hi>Non Sum dignus,</hi> I am not worthy to be Grac'd with Your Majeſty's Favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Acceptance; As be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Conſcious of my ſmall Abilities. Neither are theſe Fragments deſerving, for Excellency of Style, or Elegancy of Phraſe, which is not my Ambition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: Since the true Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant
<pb facs="tcp:51909:4"/>is beſt poliſht with its own Duſt, and Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick Deeds are their own proper Encomium.</p>
            <p>I have not for my own part, whereof I can boaſt, but the Honour of being ſometime, the only <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Caplain to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Army, in the late bleſſed and memorable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition; and of reading and diſperſing then ſome hundreds of His Gracious DECLARATIONS, between <hi>Tor-Bay</hi> and <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:51909:5"/>to the Joy of all true Proteſtants, and Dejecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>To make no mention of my Service and Wounds received in <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. There is no Man that hath endeavour'd to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance Your Majeſty's moſt juſt Deſigns, more than my ſelf, according to the ſmall Sphere of my Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as is not unknown to ſeveral Noble Lords, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51909:5"/>
            <p>May then the covering of the Almighty Wings, be ever ſpread over your Excellent Majeſties, and underneath the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Arms; may your Royal Perſons be ſtill moſt precious in the Eyes of all your Subjects, and your Forces proſper by Sea and Land. May you be bleſſed with an Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, Religious and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al People throughout all your DOMINIONS, and with a long and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Reign over them, in
<pb facs="tcp:51909:6"/>Health, Wealth, Peace and Godlineſs; and after this Life, may Your Majeſties be Crown'd with Glory and Immortality, is the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Majeſty's moſt Loyal, moſt Dutiful, moſt Obedient, Subject and Servant,</hi> John Whittell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:51909:6"/>
            <head>THE Preface.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Author</hi>'s Principal Deſign is not here to Form a <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of our Preſent Gracious Soveraign, who is the Main Subject of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſe: Nor to give the World any Exact, or Minute Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of His Glorious Actions; Knowing well enough, that Task has been, and is, perform'd daily by many Abler and Acute Pens,
<pb facs="tcp:51909:7"/>who have already Engraven them, with ſuch Fair and Laſting Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, in the Adamantine Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, laid up in Honours Temple for the uſe of Poſterity: That doubtleſs they will be found there Brightly Legible, when Old-Time ſhall have Eaten out, and Effac'd thoſe of <hi>Alexander,</hi> and the <hi>Caeſars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, that for the People of this Preſent Age, and of this Part of the World, there are few or none of them, but have either ſeen His Heroical Exploits, heard the Fame of them; or felt, at leaſt, their Comfortable Influence, which, indeed, has proved Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to all, but the Noxious part of Mankind; and ſuch as, like
<pb facs="tcp:51909:7"/>Fiſhes and Monſters, Prey upon the Reſt.</p>
            <p>And therefore knows well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, that 'twould be Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for him to pretend to Write a Hiſtory, in which, it would be altogether impoſſible, to ſay any New Matter, or any thing, but what has been already much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter expreſt by others.</p>
            <p>No; his Aims in this Eſſay, are quite different from theirs; for, though he hath been him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf an Eye-witneſs of ſome of His Majeſties Greateſt Archievements, having been with him in two Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Expeditions; and has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready given the World an Account of ſome of the Chief Paſſages in
<pb facs="tcp:51909:8"/>them; Of which, be bears about him continually ſome very <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>neaſie, though Honourable Marks: Yet, duly remembring, that he ſerv'd Him, More in Quality of a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> than a Souldier in His Army; And that the Preſent Age Swarms with a <hi>Race of Men,</hi> that Attribute ſo much to Second-Cauſes, that they ſcarce ever look up to God, who is <hi>Cauſa Cauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> of All; and ſo much Idolaters of Fortune, that they will hardly allow any <hi>Room to Providence,</hi> or an <hi>Over-ruling-Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, the <hi>Author,</hi> upon this Conſideration, has endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, ſo to Compile this <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> of <hi>His Majeſties Actions,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:51909:8"/>as it may be more a <hi>HISTORY</hi> of God's Providence, and Over-ruling-Power, than of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties <hi>GLORIOUS ATCHIEVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTS:</hi> inſiſting properly upon the Firſt, as his <hi>Text;</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on His Majeſties Happy Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and His Enemies Motions, as only a good Comment upon it; Needing (indeed) nothing elſe, but a Full and True Application: Being very ſenſible, that herein, He is ſo far from detracting from, that he much adds to that Glory, which His Majeſty (without flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery) moſt Affects and Glories in; Which is, to give all the Glory of his Actions to God alone; And being throughly convinc'd, That His Majeſty in that Point, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much unlike to the Vain-glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:51909:9"/>Monarch of <hi>France (Lewis</hi> the XIVth) who Arrogantly Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes all the Honour of his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, ſoly and wholly to himſelf; as very properly he may (all things well conſider'd) becauſe, whereas, King <hi>WILLIAM'S</hi> Great <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, are, All Men who love the Truth muſt own, really found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon moſt Juſt Motives, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected purely, to Noble, Religious, and Generous Ends, yea, even to the Common Good.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> King's on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, are Grounded upon ſo Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Perſidious a Bottom, and tend ſo very much to the General Deſtruction of Mankind; that for all his Innate Confidence, being aſhamed to Attribute them to the
<pb facs="tcp:51909:9"/>All-righteous God, who knows his inward thoughts; he, with an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent Mind, Arrogates them very fairly to himſelf, for fear other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of being obliged to Father them upon a Worſe <hi>Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to come to the Matter in hand, the <hi>Deſign</hi> of this <hi>Eſſay,</hi> in ſhort, is, to ſhew the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs</hi> of <hi>Providence</hi> over all Humane Prudence, in the late Revolutions of <hi>Holland,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of theſe <hi>Britiſh</hi> Kingdoms; and how very viſibly the finger of God, has appeared in the Chief Tranſactions of His Majeſties Life, and of our Great Deliverance by Him; by making ſo many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Cauſes to Concur, to the producing that Mighty Effect; and
<pb facs="tcp:51909:10"/>directing the Counſels of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, to ſteer their Veſſels upon thoſe very Rocks, which they had uſed all poſſible Endeavours to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void; And thereby, to move all Good Proteſtants, of theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons eſpecially, Earneſtly to Wreſtle with Allmighty God in Prayer, for a Long Preſervation to them, of their Bleſſed Deliverer; by Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging Him, to be the Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Inſtrument of the moſt High Lord, more than of any mere Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Cauſes, or pretended Influence of the Stars.</p>
            <p>For, though the <hi>Author</hi> be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely perſwaded, that <hi>Miracles</hi> properly ſo called, are, at preſent, ceaſed; yet, he cannot but Believe, with all Reaſonable Men, That,
<pb facs="tcp:51909:10"/>God Almighty by his Extraordinary Providence, doth ſtill oftentimes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe, between both his Friends and Enemies, and bare natural Cauſes; in order, to bring about his just de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, of puniſhing or favouring them, and eſpecially unuſual Revolutions in Kingdoms and States.</p>
            <p>And that theſe laſt Revolutions in the united <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. if well conſidered, in all their precedent, Concomitant, and ſubſequent Circumſtances, are ſuch very evident and infallible proofs of that undeniable Truth, that it cannot poſſibly but be acknowledged by all modeſt Men, who will give themſelves free leave but to think.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51909:11"/>
            <p>This he verily believes any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial and unprejudic'd <hi>Reader,</hi> will be fully convinc'd, when they ſhall make due Reflection upon ſome Paſſages, particularly, thoſe which he has collected out of ſome very choice Memoires, lent him by ſome Friends, who had more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opportunity, to enter behind the Scenes, and view the ſecret Springs, that ſet ſome of the chief Machines of thoſe great Artificers on Work: So that, though they may perhaps have read the Story of the ſame Tranſactions, elſewhere; yet, they will however be obliged to confeſs, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw them before in the ſame Light, manag'd with the ſame Method, nor applied with the ſame Reflections and Obſervations.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51909:11"/>
            <p>One thing he will only add, That if any well affected Perſon who is an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> indeed, in whom there is no guile, ſhall think himſelf, or his Party reflected upon, when men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd herein, as intended to be made. Tools of, by ſome of the late <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Jacobite</hi> Intrigues; that they would rectifie that mistake in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by conſidering well, it is not any where here aſſerted; that they conſented to thoſe Motions, nor yet, that they were actually put in Execution, though it muſt be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by all, that it was partly done in <hi>CORPORATIONS;</hi> but only that they were intended to be made Tools of, as well as ſome biaſs'd Church of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> Men, and to be plaied both of them, one against another, in order to
<pb facs="tcp:51909:12"/>make way for their mutual Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, for the eſtabliſhing of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and Arbitrary Power.</p>
            <p>And why, the affirming or prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this ſhould appear offenſive to any ſober Man, that really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves, there was a moſt true, fair and juſtifiable cauſe for this bleſſed <hi>REVOLUTION,</hi> the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor cannot well imagine.</p>
            <p>And therefore hopes, all ſober and unbiaſs'd Men of what perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſoever, that are Friends not only in <hi>Tongue,</hi> but in <hi>Deed</hi> and in <hi>Truth,</hi> to this preſent GO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERNMENT, will lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide all prejudice and partiality, and candidly accept his honest and well deſigned Endeavours; which tend
<pb facs="tcp:51909:12"/>only to the laying open the Enemies INTRIGUES, the caution<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men of all ſorts, from being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more drawn in by them.</p>
            <p>To alienate, their hearts, even from all thoughts of accommodation with the <hi>French</hi> Harpies, till their <hi>Claws</hi> be cut cloſe.</p>
            <p>To ſhew, the Moderate and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Carriage of our <hi>Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> in re-ſetling the ſhaken <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> the very Juſt and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Grounds, and indiſpenſable Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations their preſent Majestys mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon; in all the whole courſe of their Proceedings, their Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards the perſon of the late King; and their exceeding great Moderation, and Matchleſs Clemency
<pb facs="tcp:51909:13"/>to all their diſſatisfied Subjects.</p>
            <p>To ſet forth His <hi>MAJE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIES</hi> indefatigable Care, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Conduct, eminent Courage, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reſolution and Constancy, and happy Succeſs; in all theſe wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Occurances; and to do juſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to all other Inſtruments of our preſent <hi>LIBERTY</hi> and <hi>HAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PINESS;</hi> and yet, reſerve and attribute to almighty GOD, the due Praiſe and Glory of all.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe few Male-contents that are blinded, by the God of this World, and are Enemies to this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Government, if any Expreſſions in this <hi>TREATISE</hi> diſpleaſe them; he is not at all concern'd at it, let them look off it, and withall
<pb facs="tcp:51909:13"/>know, it was not calculated for their ſqueamiſh Palates; the Author being very conſident, there are honeſt <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamites</hi> enough in the Nation, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace heartily the whole Impreſſion, at leaſt, if 'twere three times the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. And being no leſs aſſured, they are with all ſo generous and kind, that they will read this <hi>Eſſay,</hi> for the ſake only of the Authors good, and honeſt intention, how mean a conceit ſoever they may have of his performances.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:51909:14"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 15. l. 2. <hi>Artificis,</hi> for <hi>Artifices.</hi> p. 49. l. 25. <hi>and fare,</hi> r. <hi>of fare and.</hi> p. 91. l. 22. <hi>is for, if to.</hi> p. 99. l. 2. <hi>five</hi> r. <hi>fire.</hi> p. 148. l. 15. <hi>Convent</hi> r. <hi>Convant.</hi> p. 151. l. 6. <hi>Bavillon</hi> r. <hi>Barillon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51909:14"/>
            <head>Conſtantinus Redivivus: OR, <hi>An account of the wonderfull providential Succeſſes that have all along attended the Heroical Enterpriſes of his preſent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, King</hi> WILLIAM the III. <hi>Through the grand Revolution of</hi> Holland, England <hi>and</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</head>
            <p>THE Auguſt and Glorious He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roe, who is the principal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of all our following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and alſo of the Love, Veneration and Admiration, of even the better part of the <hi>Chriſtian World</hi> at this very Day, as well thoſe of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Communion,</hi> as of the reform'd <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51909:15"/>Religion;</hi> is lineally deſcended from the moſt Ancient, and Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Houſe of <hi>Naſſaw;</hi> a Houſe, ſignal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honoured and adorn'd, with moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and ſplendid Alliances throughout <hi>Europe;</hi> and whoſe truly noble Branches have ſpread themſelves in ſeveral parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> that was graced about four hundred Years ago, with the imperial Dignity, in the perſon of <hi>Adolphus,</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of <hi>Germany,</hi> and Succeſſor to that famous <hi>Rodolphus</hi> of <hi>Habsburg;</hi> who, when a certain Man came to Him, to ask what he would give him to kill <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carus</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> with whom he waged War, anſwered, <hi>Et ſi noſter hoſtes Octocarus, non tamen efficiet, ut praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grediar fines Juſtitiae atque Moderationis.</hi> In fine, whoſe illuſtrious Family has flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh'd, in very remarkable and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhable Grandeur, for above a thouſand Years, as is Chronicl'd of it. How Prince <hi>Mauricius</hi> took the ſtrong Caſtle of <hi>Zutphen,</hi> and alſo the excellently well Fortified City of <hi>Breda, March</hi> the 3d. Anno 1590. How his great Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father Prince <hi>William</hi> of ever glorious Memory, after having furmounted num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51909:15"/>of ſundry Obſtacles, thought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to be inſurmountable, and with a prodigious and undaunted Reſolution, Conduct, Prudence, and Conſtancy, laid the Foundations of a flouriſhing Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, that now ſends forth Ambaſſadors daily upon equal terms to the moſt puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Kings in the habitable part of the Earth, and even to the King of <hi>Spain</hi> himſelf, who accepts the alliance and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of thoſe his <hi>quondam</hi> Subjects, <hi>whom not content to rule as ſuch, his haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and impolitick Progenitors, ſometime treated as Slaves and Abjects.</hi> And how his Warlike, Great and Famous Uncles and Grand-fathers, by the continued courſe of their Victories fixt and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, the dear-bought liberty and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Country; by the hazard of their Lives and Fortunes, and the vaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of their Treaſures, is amply ſet forth by many florid and learned Pens. Nor have even the Writers of their very Enemies ſide, been able to be ſilent of their Praiſes, and noble Acts, ſo manifeſt to the whole World: And therefore, we judge it altogether ſuperfluous to ſay any more here, on this Subject. <hi>Nam Genus
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51909:16"/>&amp; proavos &amp; quae non fecimus ipſi, Vix ea noſtra voco.</hi> Our main and chief deſign, in this ſmall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, being only to ſhow how our preſent illuſtrious Prince, after that he had no leſs miraculouſly retrieved, not only the very Being, but even the proſperity and greatneſs of the ſame State; when through the Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſottiſh negligence of its then Governours, it ſeem'd (as t'were to the World's eye) to be tumbled down to the very Foundations, and laid all in Rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh by the thundring and ſurpaſſing fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of a more powerful Monarch, than the former <hi>Roboam</hi> of <hi>Spain;</hi> has ſtill providentially advanced, by moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſucceſsfull ſteps, againſt that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable, and too much prevailing <hi>Nero</hi> of the <hi>Weſt,</hi> and alone given life to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt (if not) all, the efforts that have been made againſt his uncontrollable power, which elſe would like an irreſiſtible Tyde, or Sea, where the Banks are broken down, have deluged even all <hi>Europe.</hi> And how at length in recompence of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hard Toils, and Perils of his preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Life for the Publick Good, the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Lord of Battels, particularly for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51909:16"/>the glory of his holy Name, and the well-fare of his ſuffering Church, hath by a ſeries of Providences, more won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull than all the reſt exalted Him, to a ſtation that's above many of his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Anceſtors, and placed Him on the Sovereign Throne of the moſt Military and Formidable Kingdoms of the <hi>Weſt;</hi> and beſtowed upon him yearly, ſtill new and freſh earneſts, or ſpecimens of his having really elected Him, to compleat like the great <hi>Conſtantine</hi> (whoſe So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign power likewiſe had its firſt riſe in the warlike <hi>Britiſh</hi> Iſles) the full de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of his oppreſſed Children, and the Re-erection of his Church in a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant State, both of Purity and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirity, by (at leaſt the cruſhing under, if not) the utter ſubverſion of that <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biloniſh</hi> Power and Authority, which has been ſo long the Bar, which letteth the growth of the Truth of the Goſpel, and the right underſtanding of the great Myſteries of Godlineſs, as well as the Plague and Terrour of all quiet and peaceable Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>This glorious Prince, I ſay, as if in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed God of his great Mercy and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51909:17"/>had removed all humane Tutelage and Protection on mere purpoſe, that he might ſhew us and all the World, that he himſelf took Him under his own immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and peculiar care and Guardianſhip, as a mighty Heroe; by whom he graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly intended to work or bring to paſs, ſome Signal and Extraordinary Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances to his own <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily deprived of his Father (a Prince of a truth of moſt hopeful and ſurpaſſing Courage, Prudence, Piety, and all other very noble Endowments) even before he was brought forth into the World. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken off by that common Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, the <hi>Small Pox,</hi> in the very Spring of his Days, or flower of his Age; being but twenty four years Old when he died. And our bleſſed <hi>Prince,</hi> coming into the World not till ſome few days after his renowned Father's deceaſe, <hi>viz.</hi> on the fourth of <hi>November,</hi> Anno 1650.</p>
            <p>He was verily obſerved in his tender Years, or youthful Days, to diſcover a Diſcretion, Moderation, ſweetneſs of Temper, and a Reſervedneſs, much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond or above his Age. And his Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Valour, and other Princely Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51909:17"/>increaſing daily with his Stature; He gave his Relatives and Friends, as well as thoſe about him, all the Appearances of an extraordinary ſhare of Courage, Conduct, and all other Diſpoſitions that could poſſibly be deſired in a <hi>Prince,</hi> in order to qualifie him: As for an affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Father, ſo alſo, for a moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Defender of his Rights and Country. And it is moſt peculiarly obſervable, that though God hath permitted ſundry mighty endeavours, to have been made by <hi>Domeſtick Factions,</hi> even from his very Cradle, in order to have oppreſt his growing Greatneſs, and ſeveral horrid and execrable Plots and Devices, to have been carried on with great Secreſie, both by them and the Intrigues of <hi>Foreign Princes,</hi> to defeat his grand Deſigns, and to bereave him of his moſt Juſt, Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Hereditary Rights and Honours, or of his precious Life it ſelf. Yet ſtill (thanks be to God for it, and adored be his holy Name) the many oppoſitions and helliſh Machinations of his implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and undeſerv'd Enemies, have been by good Providence made to ſerve even againſt their original intention, only to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51909:18"/>his far greater Glory and Exaltation; cauſing his noble Virtues to be more ſeen in the World, as the Stars ſhine brighteſt in the darkeſt night.</p>
            <p>For though the Faction of <hi>Barnevelt,</hi> continued and upheld afterwards by the <hi>De-wits,</hi> prevail'd upon the States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral in thoſe daies moſt ungratefully and ungenerouſly, to deprive our accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht young Prince of all his Hereditary Dignities and Employments; yet at the ſame time, they thus took care to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Prince, they were ſo infatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and blinded with inveterate malice againſt him, that they minded not at all to what Dangers they then expoſed their State or Country. To which end, they committed the greateſt Blunders imaginable in Politicks; for after the Peace of <hi>Munſter,</hi> fooliſhly believing they had no more Enemies to fear, but the Ancient and Warlike Houſe of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> whoſe greatneſs they conjectured, if not timely depreſs'd, would be a perpetual Obſtacle to their unjuſt and ambitious deſigns, of graſping the Government entirely into their own hands; they therefore raſhly and without any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51909:18"/>disbanded all their hardy Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran Forces, and well experienced Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, by whoſe valour and hard toil, their Country had been raiſed to that flouriſhing condition it was then in; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for that very reaſon, becauſe they looked upon them as too much affected to his Highneſs, the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> and this was done too, without the leaſt care to procure, or provide any other old experienc'd Troops in their Room. Moreover, they gave the chiefeſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments in their Armies and Garriſons at that time, to the Sons of <hi>Burgher-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> or Deputies of Cities that were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry raw, and not well experienced in <hi>Martial Diſcipline,</hi> being moſt of them ſuch, as had never ſeen the face of an Enemy in the Field, and ſo as unfit to Command as to Obey. By which means it ſhortly came to paſs, that when they were afterwards contrary to their vain hopes, invaded by a very ſubtil and powerfull Enemy, even whole Cities and Towns, though (of a truth) ſome of them were both Naturally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally well Fortified, Stored <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with numerous Garriſons, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:51909:19"/>or five thouſand Men a piece, beſides Horſe proportionable; yet yielded up even without the leaſt oppoſition, upon the firſt appearance, or ſummons of the Enemy, not ſo much as ſtriking a ſtroak, or firing one Gun againſt them. And thus <hi>Faction</hi> and curſed <hi>Self-intereſt,</hi> with private <hi>Ambition,</hi> having reduced that, but very lately, flouriſhing Republick to the very brink of ruin and deſtruction: It gave the ſore affrighted People of that Country a fair opportunity, for to ſee plainly into what dreadful Dangers or Quick-ſands, their new Hair-brain'd Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours (which were but of Yeſterday and knew nothing) out of mere Spight, and Malice to an Ancient and very illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Family, were now driving them and their late happy Common-wealth, and ſo inſpired them with Boldneſs as well as Fore-ſight at this time to apply a ſeaſonable and fit remedy, by the quick deſtruction of thoſe notorious <hi>Domeſtick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> who had been the real occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof; and intruſting Him again with the recovery of their very much ſhattered and loſt State, who was the true genuine Iſſue of its firſt glorious and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51909:19"/>fortunate Founders, and by ſacrificing his moſt ungrateful Enemies, to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry angry and inraged genius, of the poor injured Country.</p>
            <p>Neither can it be fairly denied, but that the <hi>French</hi> King, even <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th. himſelf, as great and mortal Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my as he is to our renown'd King <hi>William;</hi> yet notwithſtanding by Gods over ruling Providence, (as he hath done ſince, to that in <hi>England</hi>) did, though the World knows, moſt contrary to his own Inclination and Intention, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute as much or more to that firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution in the united Provinces, and the ſubſequent Exaltation, Grandeur and Glory of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> than all other concurrent Cauſes put together; for having by mere ſubtilty, far over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reach'd thoſe ſelf deſigning States-men, that then ſwayed ſo much in <hi>Holland,</hi> and induced them by his moſt ſpecious promiſes, and alluring pretences, to ſtand firmly by them upon all occaſions, as well as in their late Uſurpations; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally to neglect (as we have ſaid) their old, expert, and harden'd Soldiers, and their frontier Garriſons; to turn all their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51909:20"/>Counſels and Attempts wholly towards the famous <hi>Orangian Family,</hi> and the brisk Trade and power of <hi>England,</hi> upon the vain confidence of effecting which, the crafty Monſieur had already made them to build themſelves a fools <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe;</hi> for he, all of a ſuddain leaguing on the contrary with <hi>England,</hi> attacks them moſt ſharply on their blind and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenceleſs ſide, and meeting with very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no reſiſtance, from ſuch raw Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and totty headed Commanders, as he then knew to have the main Guards of their Garriſons and places, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-run their Country with ſo rapid and ſurprizing a ſwiftneſs, that he then forc'd the People of neceſſity to have recourſe to their laſt, but ſureſt refuge under God; to wit, the valiant Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and to reſtore Him whom their wicked and treacherous Guides blinded with Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, had before ſo ungratefully and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politickly rejected. And ſo by half ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a flouriſhing Republick, they gave a meet opportunity to his Illuſtrious High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to ſhew in the open ſight of the admiring World, the wonders of his <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Policy</hi> and <hi>Magnanimity,</hi> in reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51909:20"/>it to its former Power and Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour. And withal, to let his ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and uncivil Country-men know and ſee, that the great Triumphs of their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Enemies, were cauſed for the moſt part by the wild attempts that had been made upon Him and his Rights, and that the doing juſtice to the ancient and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Progeny of the real Founders of their State, was the true and only way unto its Reſtauration. But the laſt lift that was given towards the advancing and ſecuring his Authority and Power, ſtill more and more in the united <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi> was, the diſcovery of the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid <hi>Plot</hi> laid againſt him by the two <hi>De-wits,</hi> viz. <hi>Cornelius</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> who finding well that there was no poſſibility for them of ſtemming the ſtrong and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent tide of the Peoples great Affection, tending wholly to the advancement of the Prince, which was to them an inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable Mortification; they thereupon endeavoured to corrupt a certain <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion,</hi> with the promiſed Reward of no leſs than 3000000 Franks, or 25000 pound Sterling to take away his moſt valuable Life; which matter being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51909:21"/>or providentially coming to light, and firmly atteſted, made out and ratified by the ſaid <hi>Chyrurgion;</hi> the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd <hi>De-wits,</hi> were, by the great fury of the vulgar People (not content with the milder and ſlower Proceedings of the Magiſtrate) torn preſently all to pieces, and miſerably put to Death after ſuch a manner, as now all the World knows. <hi>Namely, That they were hung up by the Heels in the Market-place, and being cut to pieces, their Joints and Fleſh ſold by piece-meal at great rates, which were carried away by the Buyers in a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of Revenge.</hi> And the Prince him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, not long after, moſt firmly fixt in the Hereditary State-holder-ſhip of all the united Provinces, and Captain Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of all their Forces by Sea and Land, with much more advantage, than any of his famous Predeceſſors enjoyed it before.</p>
            <p>Thus the Almighty and moſt wiſe Diſpoſer of the World, return'd the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and Wickedneſs of the Princes <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick</hi> Foes upon their own Heads, for they fell by the Snare which they had laid for Him, according to the tenour of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51909:21"/>holy Oracles. <hi>Nec lex eſt juſtior ulla Quam necis artificis arte perire ſua.</hi> And thus the juſt Judge of all Men, and avenger of all wrongs, puniſh'd the perfidious and ungrateful; and at the ſame time, deliver'd the <hi>Innocent:</hi> Yea, mortified all the Foreign Enemies by his own <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Arm,</hi> and rewarded at laſt, even far beyond all his hopes or deſires, his unſhaken Patience, and unparallell'd Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity, in having born ſo long a time, with a forbearance beyond <hi>Humane Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,</hi> the many baſe affronts, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries daily offer'd him by the envious and ſelf deſigning <hi>De-wits,</hi> and their up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart party. Nor were the people (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they choſe him in a great heat, and ſudden fright, to conduct the ſhattered and wheather beaten Bark, of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent forelorn, and diſtreſs'd State, into a ſafe Harbour or Port) in the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, in their expectations of him. The falſe and miſguided ſteps of their late unhappy Governours, had now by the rule of Contraries, inſtructed them in a few moments ſpace, in the very beſt and right meaſures that could poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be taken. And the furious alarms
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51909:22"/>of the <hi>French</hi> Armies, had cooled them from the wrong <hi>De-wits,</hi> into their right Wits again, and into their perfect Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, out of which they had fooliſhly by deluſive, but more ſpecious appearances been decoyed ſo lately. For our young accompliſht Prince, though made a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral at two and twenty Years of Age, as his great Grand-father had been before Him, in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth; quickly gave them ſuch fair and Signal Proofs and Specimens of his Prudence, Conduct and Courage, as ſufficiently Entituled Him to four of the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Accompliſhments, that qualifie and conſummate a ſupream Commander, <hi>viz.</hi> military Knowledge, undaunted Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, awfull Authority, and proſperous Succeſs; ſo that like the youthful <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> or <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> Nephew to <hi>Julius Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> he was no ſooner in the Field, than ripe and fit for Action, and the moſt daring Attempts and Execution. Which he ſo fortunately managed, that He not only ſtopt a puiſſant, and inſulting E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, who till then, like a moſt ſtrong or violent Torrent, carried all before them: Nevertheleſs in a ſhort time, our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51909:22"/>young Prince changed the Fortune of the War, and forc'd the pride of Elder, and longer experienced Captains, fluſht and buoy'd up with continual Victories, to ſubmit to the more powerful and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Aſcendant of his no leſs wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guided Valour, and proſperous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct.</p>
            <p>And what was ſaid of <hi>Alexander,</hi> and <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> may not improperly be ſpoken of him, concerning his Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and Conduct, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. <hi>Nihil procraſtinans.</hi> He ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver delayed or let ſlip any occaſion, as will moſt plainly appear, if we will but take the pains, juſtly and impartially to examine the ſeveral ſteps he has made, ſince he firſt ſet out on his <hi>Glorious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs;</hi> we ſhall then in large Characters, <hi>as bright as the Sun-beams, or in Capital Letters, more beautiful to our ſight, than Apples of Gold, in Pictures of Silver.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, ingraven in every <hi>Field,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every <hi>City, Garriſon</hi> or <hi>Town,</hi> where he has appeared, his matchleſs <hi>Courage,</hi> and providential <hi>Succeſs,</hi> ſince he firſt undertook to fight the Battels of his Countrey.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:51909:23"/>
            <p>For no ſooner was he inveſted in the Office of <hi>Captain,</hi> and <hi>Admiral General</hi> of all the Forces of the <hi>united Provinces,</hi> and was arrived in the <hi>Army,</hi> then ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near <hi>Nienkop;</hi> but, He put a ſtop immediately to the whole power of <hi>France,</hi> though commanded by <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th. himſelf; and notwithſtanding all their Numbers of veterane and well diſciplin'd Soldiers, and expert Officers, He not only kept them from gaining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Advantage, but even repuls'd them ſhamefully with loſs, to quit the attack they had made upon his Poſt of <hi>Nien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kop;</hi> and compell'd them to retire to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their own Country, with ſuch great Precipitation, as to leave behind them their <hi>Spades, Shovels, Mattocks</hi> and other neceſſary <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenſils,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements of the <hi>Pioneers</hi> belonging to War.</p>
            <p>And ſoon after this, as if the very Reſtauration of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> the true repairer of their Breaches, had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready put new life and vigour into all ſorts of People again. A numerous party, of about 5000 <hi>French,</hi> were twice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puls'd from the Walls of <hi>Aerdenburg;</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51909:23"/>and beſides their ſlain, forc'd to leave behind them, 500 Priſoners, among whom were, ſeveral Commanders, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Perſons of Quality. And all this effected by the extraordinary Valour, of no more than 200 <hi>Burghers,</hi> and 100 Garriſon Soldiers, together with the ſmall or feeble Aſſiſtance of a few Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; for while their Wives fill'd their Bandileers with Powder, the Children themſelves carried the Balls or Bullets, to their active and valorous Parents; nor did the Citizens of <hi>Groning,</hi> with leſs <hi>courage</hi> and good <hi>ſucceſs,</hi> defend their Walls againſt the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Munſter,</hi> forc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him after having lain there a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable while before it, with an Army of between 20 and 30000 Men to raiſe his Siege, after the loſs of near half his Men, and a vaſt expence of warlike A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, and other Inſtruments of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. To which, they were chiefly incouraged, by the confidence they put in his illuſtrious Highneſſes good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and wiſe Conduct, and by the care and vigilancy he always took to ſupply them in time, with all manner of neceſſaries for their Defence and Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:51909:24"/>
            <p>Upon the Promotion of our renown'd <hi>Heroe,</hi> or more properly upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhing of him in his <hi>Hereditary Rights, Dignity</hi> and <hi>Employment,</hi> that Great and powerfull Prince, and wiſe General, the late Elector of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> wrote a Letter to the <hi>States-General;</hi> wherein he Congratulates them upon the Reſtauration of his Heroical Kinſman, the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> to the Power, Grandeur, and Glory, of his Anceſtors; adding withall, that he made no doubt, but that ſuch wholeſome and juſt deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, would be in the concluſion proſpered from Heaven for the <hi>Common Good;</hi> more eſpecially, as knowing his illuſtrious Highneſs, to be a Perſon that truly inherited all the Vertues of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Predeceſſors;</hi> and aſſuring them with all, that he found himſelf obliged by his Couſin's Exaltation (or more truly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration) to contribute his very ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt towards the Recovery and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of what his renown'd Anceſtors had acquired, with ſo much Blood and Jeopardy of their own Lives. About the ſame time, our young Prince fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to remove the out-guards of his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51909:24"/>moſt troubleſome <hi>French</hi> Neighbours, gave them ſo ſuddain and fierce an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm, with a party of Horſe and Foot, that without diſmounting off his Horſe all the whole Night, he never left them till he had driven them back again to their Trenches before <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht;</hi> and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried off with him ſeveral <hi>French</hi> Lords Priſoners, who were Hunting at his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival in the Woods of <hi>Amerong,</hi> whom he ſent away to <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> and ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry courteouſly were they uſed on the way, that not the leaſt offer was made by any to rifle them.</p>
            <p>Much about the ſame time, he made ſundry neceſſary and wholeſom alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Magiſtrates of many Cities, to the great and general ſatisfaction of the Inhabitants, who now ſaw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by that means, in a very fair way of recovering their former Peace, Glory, and Proſperity. And alſo among the military Men, ſeveral faint hearted Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, received the due reward of their <hi>Puſillanimity</hi> and <hi>Treachery;</hi> His Highneſs being fully reſolv'd to endure no longer that corruption of martial Diſcipline, which had brought his Country ſo very near its final ruine.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:51909:25"/>
            <p>His next Action was, his vigorous at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack of <hi>Woerden,</hi> then poſſeſt by the <hi>French,</hi> where he ſo very roughly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the haughty Duke of <hi>Luxemburg</hi> and his Army, that attempted twice to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it; that he kill'd two thouſand of their common Soldiers, even on the ſpot, maim'd many of the reſt, and ſlew or wounded moſt of the Officers; in a manner, quite ruining five Regiments of their beſt Infantry; which Heroical A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſtruck ſuch a terrour of him, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in the minds of the <hi>French</hi> Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> that they would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly draw Lots, who ſhould be ſent againſt any Parties, where the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was engaged.</p>
            <p>Thence after deliberate Conſultations, and due meaſures taken in a Counſel of War, held for that very purpoſe, he marched with an Army of about 24000 ſtrong, towards the Country of <hi>Leige,</hi> in order to fight, or at leaſt to remove the <hi>French</hi> Army there, under the <hi>Count de Duras,</hi> from the Quarters about the <hi>Meuſe;</hi> in which expedition, he had ſuch remarkable Succeſs, that though his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my was compoſed of ſeveral Nations,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51909:25"/>and that his March was in the very depth of Winter, into an Enemies Country, and along very bad ways; yet he effectually removed that older, and more experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc'd General, <hi>Duras,</hi> out of his Poſt, or rather ſtrong hold, and hunted him up and down as a Partridge, till he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired to <hi>Staſſemburgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Terrified two ſtrong Garriſons to the purpoſe, and then return'd with the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners and Booty, of two fortified places; and all this was acted in the ſpace of nine daies, with very inconſiderable or no loſs of his own Men; beſides the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour he at the ſame time ſtruck, in the Biſhop-Elector of <hi>Cologne,</hi> who thought himſelf ſecure neither at <hi>Bonne,</hi> nor any other part of his Dominions, ſo long as ſo very active and vigilant a Chieftain as our Prince, was quarter'd with his whole Army thus near to him.</p>
            <p>After this, having repuls'd the Duke of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> who at that time by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the <hi>Ice</hi> and <hi>Froſt,</hi> had made an incurſion into <hi>Holland,</hi> towards the City and Univerſity of <hi>Leyden;</hi> in which Parts, and the adjacent Villages, he had made no ſmall Havock, nor committed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51909:26"/>little Spoil and Barbarity, (theſe devaſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a Country, being the peculiar pleaſures of his Diſpoſition, which is no leſs crooked than his deform'd <hi>Aeſopian Body,</hi>) and forc'd him to retire in all haſt, with the loſs of above ſix hundred Men, and no ſmall hazard of his own Life.</p>
            <p>Moreover he moſt happily, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all very expeditiouſly, recover'd from the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter,</hi> then leagued with the <hi>French,</hi> the ſtrong and well fortified City of <hi>Coevorden,</hi> accounted by thoſe who pretend skill therein, one of the nobleſt pieces of Portification, in all the Low Countries; which place had fallen into the hands of that Biſhop, not long before by Treachery: But now was regain'd with <hi>ſuch aſtoniſhing Valour</hi> and ſurprizing <hi>Gallantry,</hi> together with moſt ſignal Concurrence of the Divine Providence, that though it formerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puls'd <hi>Verdugo,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> General, after a fruitleſs Siege of one and thirty weeks; and was now at this time, well furniſht and ſtored by the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter,</hi> with an exceeding great Magazin, of all ſorts of Proviſions for <hi>the Mouth,</hi> as well as Ammunition and Artillery for Defence.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51909:26"/>Nay, he had in it even then, a Garriſon of nine hundred effective Soldiers; yet was it in one hours time Storm'd, and retaken by a party only of nine hundred and ſixty, with the loſs only of ſixty of the Aſſailants; as the Hiſtory of thoſe Wars moſt plainly demonſtrates.</p>
            <p>Whereas quite contrary to what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, almoſt in all other Seiges, there was ſlain one hundred and fifty of the Defendants, beſides Officers, and four hundred and thirty taken Priſoners, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom, alſo were many Officers, the reſt eſcaping out of the Town, when they perceived that it was abſolutely loſt.</p>
            <p>The conſequence of the regaining this important Place, was ſo exceeding great, as to caſt the Enemies then very much down, and put them into ſuch a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Conſternation, that preſently after that, they deſerted ſeveral of their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, even upon the firſt news of it, and diſpers'd themſelves here and there, every man being glad to ſhift for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>Whereas on the contrary, it redound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo very much unto the Reputation of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51909:27"/>our illuſtrious Prince, and ſo exceedingly enhans'd his Eſtimation and Honour, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all ſorts of People in <hi>Holland,</hi> and the united Provinces, that finding ſuch a continued and unexpected Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſuch a happy chain of good Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, and withall ſo very proſperous an Alteration to happen upon his illuſtrious Highneſſes being advanced, to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Management of their Affairs, they could not but attribute them to the viſible Benediction of the moſt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Jehovah,</hi> upon the juſtice they had ſo lately done to the moſt ancient and warlike <hi>Progeny</hi> of their firſt and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Founders (and without any Flattery, greateſt Benefactors) and upon the moſt diligent, and vigorous Efforts of that Courageous and <hi>prudent Prince,</hi> whoſe Noble and Divine Talent, they had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time deſpiſed and ſet at <hi>nought;</hi> nay, they themſelves cannot deny, but that they were moſt groſly ignorant of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable worth, (like the Cock in the Fable, of his precious Gemm) till an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and provoked Heaven, by very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing Judgments, rouz'd them up to diſtinguiſh and employ his <hi>Royal Virtues,</hi> and moſt <hi>noble Accompliſhments.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:51909:27"/>
            <p>Neither was he leſs happy in conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Domeſtick Jarrs and Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, than foreign Foes; but gave the World a moſt important proof of the <hi>mighty Effects</hi> of that ſparkling golden Authority that is gain'd over the very hearts of Men by Sweetneſs and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and of that grand Awe, Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and Reverence, that is ſo deeply im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd and inculcated by an unfeigned Affection, or undiſſembled Love. For when the mortal <hi>Feuds</hi> and <hi>Diſſentions,</hi> between the old and new Magiſtrates of <hi>Friezland</hi> were grown to that prodigious height and degree, that repreſenting the Sovereignty of that Province, they held then ſeparate, diſtinct Aſſemblies, and gave contrary Orders each to other, to the very imminent danger of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick at the ſame time; and would in no wiſe ſuffer themſelves to be reduced into any good Order, neither by the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Friezland,</hi> nor his Mother: yet upon the very arrival of the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners diſpatcht to them, by the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> thoſe heats were ſuddenly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipated, and the Breaches made up again, and the whole Province ſoon reſtored to its former <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> and <hi>Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:51909:28"/>
            <p>And afterwards going himſelf in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to pacifie the growing differences in <hi>Zealand,</hi> He no ſooner appeared in the Aſſembly of their States at <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> but their <hi>Diſſentions</hi> aſſoon vaniſht away, like a ſmoaky vapour in the Air, and all things thereupon were ſuddenly reſettled, for the defence and ſafety of the <hi>Country</hi> to the full; and general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and ſatisfaction of all Perſons, and his illuſtrious Highneſs's very great <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By theſe Beginnings, having now gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the World ſufficient Proofs of his great <hi>Capacity,</hi> in the Art of <hi>Civil,</hi> as well as of <hi>Military Conduct</hi> and <hi>Policy;</hi> He was called daily to greater and more glorious <hi>Actions</hi> and <hi>Atchievements:</hi> For not only his own <hi>Country-men,</hi> but even <hi>Foreign Princes,</hi> after this being ſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied of his moſt incomparable <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities,</hi> that they ſcrupled not in the leaſt to intruſt Him, with the ſole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of their Armies, and to adventure them and their Fortunes at Stake, in his moſt victorious and ſucceſsful hands.</p>
            <p>Neither can it be poſſibly inſtanc'd, that ever he deceived their Hopes, or
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51909:28"/>that kind <hi>Providence</hi> ever failed his Roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky and firm expectations in any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, were a full confidence was wholly repos'd in Him, and that he was well ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by his Allies.</p>
            <p>We ſhall only touch briefly upon ſome of the moſt important of the reſt of his glorious <hi>Atchievements,</hi> paſſing by all leſſer Occurrences and other Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, but ſuch only as ſhall be purely neceſſary to ſet forth in <hi>Chryſtal Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters,</hi> how wonderful careful the good Providence of the Almighty has been all his whole life long, to preſent him with fair Occaſions in order to Signalize his moſt illuſtrious and incomparable <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities.</hi> How very induſtrious he hath been alwaies to cultivate thoſe <hi>Divine Favours,</hi> not at all for his own private Ends, but meerly for the <hi>Publick Good;</hi> and how he hath been commonly attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Succeſſes, much beyond the Hopes of his greateſt <hi>Friends,</hi> or <hi>Fears</hi> of his grandeſt <hi>Enemies,</hi> and the opinion of indeed the whole World. <hi>Quid gaudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um fando,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To proceed then, though (by the watchfulneſs he was obliged to have up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51909:29"/>the Motions, not only of the Armies of the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> but likewiſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> themſelves; who at that Juncture, threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten'd a Deſcent) he was hindred from affording any relief to <hi>Maeſtricht,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieg'd the next Spring by a very power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Army, headed by the <hi>French</hi> King himſelf in Perſon; yet upon <hi>Lewis</hi> the fourteenth's retreat, after the taking of that place, and upon the returning home of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet, after the laſt Engagement on the Coaſt of <hi>Holland,</hi> he ſoon repaired that loſs by the retaking of <hi>Naerden;</hi> which although it had in it a Garriſon of two thouſand nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and thirty Men, and was very well Fortified and abundantly ſtored with all manner of Neceſſaries, yet he took it in the ſpace of four daies, maugre all <hi>Luxemburg</hi>'s oppoſition, and that again even contrary to the uſual fortune of Sieges, with much leſs loſs to his own Men, than to the beſieged.</p>
            <p>And not long after that, carried the great ſtroke in the no leſs ſpeedy and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Reduction of the ſtrong and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous City of <hi>Bonne,</hi> the Seat of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51909:29"/>of <hi>Cologne,</hi> then in the <hi>French</hi> confederacy, which was no ſooner taken, but that famous old General <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> who was a proper Judge of <hi>Martial Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct,</hi> having left with him the command of the <hi>Imperial Army</hi> to join with his own; He with them both made ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable an Expedition towards the main Poſts, poſſeſſed then by the <hi>French</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the <hi>Meuſe,</hi> and the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle,</hi> that the <hi>French</hi> who wanted Men to re-implace thoſe multitudes of good Soldiers they had too profuſely ſquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd away in their late raſh and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate Enterprizes, not being able to maintain Garriſons and Armies in both Frontiers, as the State of Affairs then required, rather than venture the loſs of the places, that compoſed the main Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier of their Country, towards the <hi>Rhine</hi> in this juncture of Diſtreſs, and Conſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, abandon'd immediately <hi>Woerden, Herderwick, Crevecoeur, Bommel,</hi> the City and Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> and moſt of all the reſt of the places they had then taken, in the united <hi>Netherlands;</hi> whoſe Example was ſoon followed by their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, the <hi>Munſterians.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:51909:30"/>
            <p>And thus his Highneſs in ſome ſence, out-did <hi>Coeſar</hi> himſelf, vanquiſhing his Enemies even at a diſtance, where he neither came nor ſaw; and forcing them willingly to ſubmit, by the onely ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of his <hi>Auguſt</hi> Name, and made them with a very mortifying reverſe of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, behold the period of their <hi>Victories,</hi> in his bright and riſing Glory; which the moſt florid copious Pen can never ſufficiently delineate to the Life.</p>
            <p>In conſideration of which, moſt great and unexpected turn of Affairs, from the very brink of irrecoverable Ruin, and Deſtruction to a formidable State of Power, Grandeur, and Proſperity, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected (next and immediately under God) chiefly by the Policies and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary valour of the Prince: The States General as in Gratitude ſtrongly bound, not only confirm'd the Charge, of State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder of the Provinces of <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friezland,</hi> in the perſon of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown'd Highneſs during Life; but ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it likewiſe in the Heirs-male of his Body, begotten in lawfull Marriage by a publick Decree, Dated the 2d. of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi> 1674. The tenour of which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51909:30"/>being ſo ſignal, and glorious a Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, of his high, and Unparallell'd Merits; we thought, it would be a piece of Injuſtice not to inſert, and no ſmall ſatisfaction to the Candid and Impartial Reader to Peruſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Friday, February</hi> 2d, 1674.</head>
               <p>HAving taken into Deliberation, by way of Reſumption, what the Lords Deputies of the City of <hi>Haerlem</hi> Propoſed to the Aſſembly, the 23d of <hi>January</hi> laſt paſt; Whether it would not be expedient, that the Charge of State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, and Captain-Admiral, of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friezland;</hi> and Captain and Admiral-General of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> ſhould deſcend upon the Heirs-Males of his Highneſs the P. of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> begotten in lawful Marriage, as by the Rolls of the ſame Date more amply may appear; We, the Body of the Nobility,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51909:31"/>and the Deputies of the Cities, in the Name, and in the Behalf of the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghers, and Commonalty of the ſaid Cities, have Declared, and do Declare by theſe Preſents, that having delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately Conſidered the State and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Government of theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, as it was in former times, by the bleſſing of God, under the Moſt Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Princes of <hi>Orange,</hi> of Glorious Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, his Highneſſes Predeceſſors; and particularly, what has befallen this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick for theſe 23, or 24 years, laſt paſt, till now; we have obſerv'd, that this Republick has been afflicted with ſeveral Calamities and Diſaſters, as well Domeſtick, as Foreign, ever ſince the ſad and unfortunate year 1650. That as to our Foreign Calamities, we have never been without Wars, or the Fears of Wars. More particularly, One moſt dreadful War, between the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and theſe <hi>States;</hi> which ſhook the very Foundations of the Government of theſe Countreys; So that it hardly has reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered Breath, ever ſince the ſaid War; and another againſt the Crown of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal,</hi> in the years 1656, 1658, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51909:31"/>1659; and another occaſion'd by the Intereſt of the Northern Wars. That in the year 1664, they had another New War with the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and now this preſent War, more ſad and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal than all the reſt. And that during the whole Courſe of the ſaid War, this Republick has been forc'd to ſuffer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Affronts from her Neighbours, to whom ſhe was before a Terror. That as to our Domeſtick Affairs, we have been overwhelm'd with Inteſtine Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Factions. That from the year 1650, to the year 1660, ſeveral Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this Republick have had a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Averſion to the Perſon of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> the only Son of that Illuſtrious Family; and that Others, on the contrary, have zealouſly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, that the ſaid Prince ought not to be ſo ungratefully abandoned. That the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> being recall'd to the Government of his Dominions, and paſſing through theſe Countreys, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his Embarking for <hi>England,</hi> this Republick teſtified, as well to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, as to the Princeſſes Royal, and Dowager, that they would take particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51909:32"/>care of the Intereſt, and Education of his Highneſs; and to Reſtore him to the Dignities which his Illuſtrious Anceſtors of Glorious Memory had enjoyed. But that after the Death of the ſaid Princeſs-Royal, all Good will and Affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Highneſs, was loſt, and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notice taken of him; till of late, that ſome Care was taken of his Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and that, at length, towards the end of 1671, or 1672, Great Conteſts aroſe, about the Election of His Highneſs to be Captain-General of the Militia of this Countrey. That we have found, by ſad Experience, that the ſaid Inteſtine Diviſions and Factions, have given an Occaſion to the Enemies of this Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, to Affront us every moment, as knowing well, that they render us unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to mind our Own Defence, by the Violation of that Union, which laid the Foundation of this Republick; and which God hath ſo Miraculouſly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And that the Differences which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe every day, about the Election of Captain General of the Militia, and theſe Diſcords, which happen'd among the Principal Members of this Republick,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:51909:32"/>were the Occaſions, that Retarded and Hindred theſe Deliberations and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; Which of neceſſity ought to have been taken, to Repel Foreign Force, and made us ſpend in Idle Diſputes, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Time, that ought to have been better husbanded. That the ſaid Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were the Reaſon, that towards the year 1671, when the King of <hi>France</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly declared, That he would make a War againſt this Countrey; we conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med whole Months together, in Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berating about the Election of a Captain-General; and whether to pitch upon his Highneſs; which time ought to have been ſpent, in providing for the Defence of the State. And that for the ſame Reaſon it was, that the King of <hi>France</hi> invaded this Countrey, by Force of Arms, in the Year 1672, and reduced us to the laſt Extremities, and hazard of Total Ruine. That therefore the Lords and States of <hi>Holland</hi> have deemed it neceſſary, as the only Expedient that they can imagin, or hope for, utterly to pluck up by the Roots the Occaſions of the ſaid Factions and Diviſions; to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their falling any more into thoſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51909:33"/>Misfortunes and Miſeries, to which they have been hitherto expoſed; And, on the other ſide, to acknowledge the Great and Glorious Services, which the moſt Illuſtrious Houſe of <hi>Orange,</hi> has from time to time perform'd, for the Preſervation and Eſtabliſhment of this Republick. For theſe Reaſons, the Lords of the Body of the Nobility, as alſo the Deputies of the Cities, have Unanimous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Conferr'd, and by theſe Preſents do Confer, in the Name, and on the behalf of the Burghers and Commonalty of the ſaid Cities, upon His Renown'd High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and his Heirs male, begotten in law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Matrimony; the Charge of Stadhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Captain, and Admiral General of the Provinces of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friezland,</hi> with all the Dignities, Preeminences, Prerogatives, Rights and Privileges thereto belonging, without any excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or reſervation, in as ample, and in the ſame manner, as the ſame Charge is at preſent executed by His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> And conſequently, that after the deceaſe of his ſaid High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, (to whom, nevertheleſs, the States of <hi>Holland</hi> wiſh a long and happy Life,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:51909:33"/>in all health and proſperity) the ſaid Charge of State-holder, Captain, and Admiral-General of the Provinces of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friezland,</hi> with the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, Preeminences, Prerogatives, Rights and Privileges thereunto belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without any exception or reſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall devolve and deſcend upon his Heirs-males, begotten in lawful Wedlock. In purſuance of which reſolution, the ſaid Lords of the Body of the Nobility, have ordered Letters-Patents to be drawn up, and Sealed with the Great Seal of the Provinces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the ſame day likewiſe, the States of <hi>Zealand</hi> conferred the ſame Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties upon him, and made him Hereditary Noble of their Province; upon which enſued the recovery of all the reſt of the Places and Countreys yet remaining in the Enemies hands; which our Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Heroe ſhewed as much Prudence and Policy, in clearing from Abuſes, and Remodelling to their Antient Form and Order, as he had before ſhewn Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and Conduct in their Recovery.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:51909:34"/>
               <p>Thus, did both the <hi>French,</hi> and the <hi>De-Wits,</hi> and their Upſtart-party, by thoſe very Deſigns, that ſtruck at the Ruine both of Him and his Countrey, by a ſtrange over-ruling turn of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, advance him to ſudden Greatneſs, of a much higher pitch, than that they attempted to diſmount him from; And his unjuſt Deprivation of all his Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Honours and Dignities, became the occaſion of his being afterwards inveſted with more abundant Honour: Which he always ſtudied to make redound to the advantage and proſperity, and not (like his <hi>French</hi> Tyrannical Neighbour) to the Miſery and Oppreſſion of his Countrey. After this, the King of <hi>France,</hi> to repair his late Loſs in the United <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi> by regaining freſh Ground in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Provinces, falling down with his Power into <hi>La Franche Comté,</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering that whole Province, before any ſufficient Force could poſſibly advance to hinder him; and being returned for <hi>Paris,</hi> leaving that experienced, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned General, the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> in the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi> with a Powerful Army of his Choiceſt Forces, to watch the Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:51909:34"/>and thwart, if po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>le, the Deſigns of the Confederate Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which now conſiſted of the United Forces, of the <hi>Imperialiſts, Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Hollanders,</hi> amounting in all to 60000 Men, under the Command of Three great Chiefs, <hi>viz.</hi> General <hi>Souches,</hi> His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the Count <hi>de Monterey,</hi> whereof, the Prince Commanded the main Battel, and the other Two Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, the Van and the Rear. There happen'd ſoon after, between thoſe Two Potent Armies, the moſt fierce and furious fight of <hi>Seneffe;</hi> wherein the Great Prince of <hi>Conde's</hi> Valour and Courage was every way Matcht, and his Conduct, and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in ſeveral reſpects, out-done, by a General, who was yet but a Young Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginner in War. By which means he put a check upon that Fury, which guided, as it was, with ſo much skill in a General, equally fiery and experienced; and back'd with a numerous Army of veterane Soldiers, fluſh't, and bouyed up with continual Victories: Had it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſucceſsful, as but for the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prudence, Courage and Diligence of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> it moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:51909:35"/>had, would have overwhelmed <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and all the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi> with a Second Inundation of <hi>French</hi> Violences, much more dangerous and remedileſs (as all Relapſes commonly are) than the Firſt. For, not to inſert here all the particulars of that Dreadful Battel, of which there are ſo many well-penn'd Relations extant, it is certain, on all hands, That the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> tho he before were averſe to a Fight, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very loath to expoſe the Glory and Honour he had won in ſo many Battels, by encountring an undaunted and vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous young Prince, of Twenty three years of age, and knowing his Eagerneſs even in that early beginning of his Mighty Career, by making his firſt Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of a pitcht-Battel, againſt ſo famous a Chieftain as the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> and by Victory over him, to open himſelf a ſecure and eaſie paſſage into the very Bowels of <hi>France,</hi> in order to revenge the Grand Injuries, both his Native Countrey, and his own Hereditary Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality, and other Patrimonial Lands, had received ſo lately from that Inſolent and Unquiet Nation; and reflecting on
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:51909:35"/>himſelf, upon the account of the Civil and Foreign Wars he had been engaged in, not many years before, againſt <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th, what ſevere Cenſures he would be obnoxious to, more than any other Commander, upon any Conſiderable Misfortune to his Army, which would have laid <hi>France</hi> open and Defenceleſs on that ſide, and would have been thought in him, a wilfull Miſcarriage.</p>
               <p>Though (I ſay) for theſe Reaſons, that Great <hi>French</hi> Prince moderated his Natural Impatience to Fight; And, with Deſign to avoid a Battel, poſted his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſo, that he could not be any ways forced to it; yet, when he heard of the daily Claſhings of the General-Officers of the Confederate Army; and how much the Well-adviſed Meaſures of our Couragious Prince, were disjointed and broken thereby; and found, that upon their Deſpairing to bring him to a Battel, they were Marching to lay Siege to ſome important place, within their New Conqueſts; and that in their March by him, they were forc'd to file through ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry narrow and moſt difficult paſſages; Letting the Van-guards Politickly paſs,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:51909:36"/>and ſome of the Main-Body too, quietly, without any diſturbance, ſome Leagues before; he thought he had then a very ſure proſpect, of cutting off ſecurely and eaſily, at leaſt, their whole Reare; and accordingly fell upon them, with ſo much vigour and fury, and with ſuch ſucceſs, that in a few Moments, he routed, and broke in pieces, all the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Cavalry, and the Foot ſent to their Relief; who being ſo broken, fell upon the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and put them into ſuch a terrible diſorder, that could no ways poſſible be remedied by our brave young Prince; though it muſt be granted by all, that he uſed all imaginable means to do it, that Induſtry, Prudence, or Courage could ſuggeſt: And moſt certain it is, that had the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the ſucceſs of that firſt Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Victory was his, and the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates could no ways, at that time, as their Armies were poſted, have Retalia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the loſs to the <hi>French.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the fiery General, of theſe laſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing encouraged by the hopes of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Victory, as thinking the <hi>Dutch,</hi> whom he looked upon, to be very deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:51909:36"/>Soldiers, would never ſtand after the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were wholly Defeated, would needs make his whole Army ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, and endeavour to force the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> out of ſome advantageous Poſts he had Seized, to ſtop the torrent of his Succeſſes and Fury, and make a general Battel of it; whereby he gave occaſion to our illuſtrious Prince, to catch his Lawrels from him, and by main Force and Courage, to wreſt the Victory from one who before had it in his hands, and oblige him to retire with the loſs of all the flower of his Army, under the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the darkſome Night; and to wellcome its approach for ſaving him from the diſgrace of a total Defeat, tho 'tis moſt aſſured, he had not at all miſs'd of his aim, but had ruined that day with an irreparable Slaughter, the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Army, had he had to do with a Prince with the leaſt degree of leſs Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, Obſtinacy, Activity and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, than himſelf.</p>
               <p>And moſt certain it is, the Glory and Renown our Heroical Prince gain'd that day, is very great indeed; when ſo great a Maſter of War, as the Prince of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:51909:37"/>
                  <hi>Conde</hi> was, thought it a glory not to be overcome by him.</p>
               <p>And indeed the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Conduct and Example, muſt needs be confeſs'd by all unbiaſs'd Writers, to have produced the mightier Effects of the two on that occaſion, ſince if the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi>'s Behaviour and Example, kept up the Courage to admiration in an old Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, compoſed all (as 'twere) of Captains, as much uſed to Victory, as to Fight: That of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> reſtored it to a Miracle, in men altogether diſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and defeated; and in a few Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, made able Captains of thoſe, who till that very Day, were hardly Soldiers, and knew not what 'twas to be in a hot Engagement; and animated them with ſuch freſh Vigour, as to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh away a glorious Victory, from an Army of old beaten and long experienced Soldiers.</p>
               <p>All the while this Action laſted, our undaunted Prince gave all neceſſary Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, with admirable Prudence, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Skill; He neglected no means nor advantage, he could poſſibly improve, oppoſed a fit and ſpeedy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:51909:37"/>where ever there was occaſion, and charged the <hi>French</hi> ſeveral times at the head of his Squadrons, with match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Bravery and indefatigable Deligence; he ſtopt even his own Fugitives, that fell upon him, as well as his Enemies; and rallying them again, charged with them ſeveral times a freſh; he expoſed himſelf as well as the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> more than the meaneſt Soldier, and Count <hi>Souches</hi> rightly ſaid of him, <hi>That he fought with the Conduct of an old General, and the Courage of a</hi> Caeſar.</p>
               <p>His very Enemies ſaid of Him, that if their Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> had multiplied him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he had met the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very were; and the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> himſelf ſpeaking of him, with admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaid, <hi>That he had behaved himſelf in every thing like an old Captain, excepting his expoſing himſelf unto too many Dangers, wherein he ſaid, he had Acted like a young Man; though as old, as himſelf was, he was as guilty of the ſame fault, as he, and had committed more Blunders in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In fine, the <hi>French</hi> Prince was glad to leave him the Field of Battel, and Retire,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:51909:38"/>and was ſo very cautious after that, of venturing another Engagement with him, though after both Armies were well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſht and recruited, that he declin'd it by all the waies and means he could poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and contented himſelf thence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with obſerving only his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries motions, and covering the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts and Frontiers of <hi>France,</hi> againſt him, which was the main deſign of our redoubted Prince, could he have found ſo ready a Compliance, from the other confederate Generals, as was abſolutely neceſſary for ſo great an Enterpriſe; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever finding he could not draw the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> to any more Battels, he laid a Siege to <hi>Oudenard,</hi> with intent to draw the <hi>French</hi> out of their Re-trench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to its Relief. Accordingly the Stratagem took ſo far, that the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> having ſtrengthened himſelf with ſome Detachments of freſh Forces, brought him by the Marſhal <hi>D' Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> marching to attempt its Succour, the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> preſently ſummoning a Council of War, adviſed the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates to march with him immediately out of the Lines, and attack the <hi>French,</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:51909:38"/>while they were now weary with their long and hard March; which, had they done in all probability and appearance, he had obtain'd a glorious Victory over them; and the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> was ſo ſenſible of the certainty of the meaſures his Enemy had adviſed, that when upon the news they were broken, by the ill tim'd oppoſition of Count <hi>Souches,</hi> and the Imperaliſts, and a <hi>French</hi> Officer took occaſion thereupon to tell the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> that our Heroical Prince was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, he is reported to have uttered this prophetical Speech of him. 'Tis true, anſwered he, he is as unhappy as brave; but yet for all that, he would in time prove a General as formidable to <hi>France,</hi> as his Fore-Fathers had been to <hi>Spain;</hi> ſuch was the judgment of this great and knowing Enemy, of his grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Honour, and blooming Glory. And what <hi>Alexander</hi> King of <hi>Macedonia</hi> ſaid to a certain Queen, that ſent him moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious and Fare, Junkets curiouſly prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, may at this time be truly applied to our illuſtrious Prince. <hi>Reſpondit ſeip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum habere meliores obſoniorum artifices, ad prandium quidem</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> i. e. <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturnum
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:51909:39"/>Iter, ad Caenam vero</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> i. e. <hi>tenue prandium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Finding himſelf then balkt in his He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical Deſigns, and main Ends and Scope, againſt the <hi>French</hi> Army, by the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the <hi>Imperial Officers,</hi> ſuſpected ſtrongly to be cauſed by <hi>French</hi> Intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues and Inſinuations; His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> moves towards <hi>Grave,</hi> the laſt remaining and ſtrongeſt recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the <hi>Gallicans</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> and the moſt reſolutely defended by a ſtout Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of between 4 and 5000 Men, and took it in the ſpace of about 16 days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Arrival, where he found 450 pieces of Cannon, whereof 100 were mounted, beſides an infinite quantity of Corn and other Proviſions; and of Powder, Ball, Granado's, and all war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Ammunition, the <hi>French</hi> having hoarded up in that place, almoſt all they had brought away from their deſerted <hi>Conqueſts;</hi> and thus he happily and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ended that Campagne.</p>
               <p>After this, he faced more than once the main Power of <hi>France,</hi> led by the King himſelf, who tamely ſuffer'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be by him, even with advantage
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:51909:39"/>provoked to Battle, without daring to accept the Challenge; and (it cannot be denyed) had moſt certainly been attack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him, in deſpight of all his precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions before <hi>Bouchain,</hi> had not the Town, contrary to Expectation, with too much inconſiderateneſs and precipitation fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred, before he could poſſibly exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his great and noble Deſign; and indeed it muſt be acknowledged, that he all along made much more vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and reſolute Efforts, to relieve the beſieged <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Towns, than the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> themſelves did in defending them; whoſe Officers were too often either cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by <hi>French</hi> Gold, or not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently provided for by the fault and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of their General Governours, or elſe through the grand negligence and dilatory proceedings of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Court it ſelf, whoſe Motto may well be <hi>Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na lente.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What he did afterwards in the Seige of <hi>Maeſtricht,</hi> is ſufficiently demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the World, that had the promiſed Re-inforcements arrived to him, from the Dukes of <hi>Lunenburg</hi> and Biſhop of <hi>Munſter,</hi> upon which he depended, he
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:51909:40"/>had not failed through God's bleſſing reducing it: Yet ſo formidable was his Courage and Conduct, more than the number of his Forces, or the quality of his Army, to the wary <hi>French</hi> General <hi>Schomberg</hi> then ſent againſt him, that he was contented only to relieve the Town without accepting Battel, though offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, as much fatigued and diminiſh'd, as were his Enemies Troops at that time.</p>
               <p>The next Year, the <hi>French</hi> King ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe of the great advantage, his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Command over a formidable Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of experienced, well-diſciplin'd and hardened Soldiers; and over the Purſes of all manner of Perſons, in his Realms and Dominions, had above thoſe who acting in the Confederacy, met with a thouſand delays, cauſed by different Counſels and Intereſts; and the Poverty and want of Power, in ſome of their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, falls in the very depth of Winter, with numerous and prodigious Forces in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Netherlands, and taking the ſtrong Town of <hi>Valenciennes</hi> with an aſtoniſhing Celerity, ſits down before <hi>Cambray,</hi> takes the Town, diſtreſſes the Caſtle, and at the ſame time, ſends his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:51909:40"/>Brother the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther potent Army to beſiege St. <hi>Omers,</hi> which were all three Towns of mighty Importance, that formerly extreamly gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Frontiers of <hi>France;</hi> and this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any of the Confederate Forces, could be got together, but ſuch as might be drawn out of <hi>Holland,</hi> and ſome Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Garriſons. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe grand Diſadvantages at this time our gracious and truly publick Spirited Prince, not willing the Intereſt of his Allies, and of his Country, ſhould ſo deeply ſuffer without ſome attempt, to repell the dreadful Storm; he aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles ſuch an Army, as he could poſſibly in ſo ſhort a time, and in ſuch haſte, draw together, as we have ſaid, of <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Forces; and though he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> leaving only ſome Regiments to guard his Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and keep the Town blockt up, had poſted the reſt of his Army, in and about all the Avenues and Paſſages to the place, which were difficult to force, and were beſides that ſtrongly guarded with two Rivers, one behind the other; yet he paſſed the firſt River, with ſuch ſpeed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:51909:41"/>and ſilence, that all his Army were got over before the Enemy perceived them; and afterwards, though the <hi>French</hi> were all drawn up in Battalia, not far from the very Banks of the ſecond River, yet he moſt ſucceſsfully made himſelf Maſter of the Abby of <hi>Pienes</hi> on the other ſide, and lodged his own Regiment of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons in it, which provoking the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to march out from an advantageous poſt to diſlodge them, brought the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies at length to a Battel, wherein the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> found himſelf ſo hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſs'd by the Prince, that his beſt Troops about his Perſon gave at one time ſo much way, that (as I have been credibly informed) ſome perſons of Note, that were of his own party in that Battel, reported, that when Prayers and Menaces would not avail or do, he had once Recourſe to Sighs and Tears, to make them return to the charge againſt the Enemy. For which he could not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the Raillery even of the King his Brother at his coming back, who could not forbear ſmiling at his Conduct, tho perhaps <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th. would have been as much frighted at the Danger, had he himſelf been there as the other.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:51909:41"/>
               <p>Certain it is, the <hi>French</hi> much exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Number and Quality of Troops, having received the very night before a Re-inforcement of 15000 choice Men, from the Kings own Army; ſo that by the impartial report of the <hi>French</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> withſtood that day, no leſs than 39 Battalions of Foot, and an 100 Squadron of Horſe: And though the loſs on the Confederate ſide was very conſiderable, yet ſeveral Squadrons of the Enemy were moſt roughly handled, in ſo much that the Adverſaries themſelves ſcrupled not to ſay and own, That if the Prince's left Wing had fought, with equal courage to the right, he might in all probability, have relieved the Town, and obliged the Enemy at that time to have quitted the Siege, if he had not entirely routed them; but a Regiment of new raiſed Soldiers, planted or poſted in that Wing, were the real cauſe that his Highneſs had not all the Succeſs in that Battel, which indeed his wiſe Conduct undaunted Courage, and indefatigable Induſtry de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. However, all relations agree in this, That he performed all that was
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:51909:42"/>poſſible to be done, with ſuch a ſmall Army, and in ſuch a place and juncture, againſt ſuch a puiſſant Enemy, by the moſt Prudent, Courageous and daring Leader in the whole World. And that in the main Battel, were he himſelf com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in Perſon, he did Wonders, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on his Men at the very head of his Troops to the Charge, and hazarding himſelf to that degree, that he received two Musket Shots in his Armour. After the end of this Campagne, Heaven de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminating to lay the Foundation of his preſent Grandeur and Glory, by giving a very precious Gage and Pledge of the Poſſeſſion of thoſe Crowns it intended, as the due reward of his truly Royal Vertues, and indefatigable pains for the weal of Chriſtianity; ſo influenced the heart of our late King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond of <hi>England,</hi> that in ſpight of the <hi>French</hi> Intrigues, and the ſecret Inclinations of the then Duke of <hi>York,</hi> her Father, to the Contrary, and to the ſurpriſal and mortification of the <hi>French</hi> King, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon Him in ſacred Marriage, the no leſs Virtuous and Accompliſhed, than the beauteous Princeſs his Niece,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:51909:42"/>the <hi>Preſumptive Heireſs</hi> of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Monarchy, an alliance of a much more dreadful proſpect to the Aſpiring Monſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur, than the loſs of all his late Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts in <hi>Holland, Flanders, Brabant</hi> and elſewhere, and which threatn'd <hi>France</hi> it ſelf, with an unpleaſant Retaliation (in due time) for all her notorious Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olences.</p>
               <p>This illuſtrious Alliance was ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz'd on the 4th. day of <hi>November,</hi> 1677. being the joyful Birth-day of his illuſtrious Highneſs, at eleven at Night; but ſo privately, that the People not knowing till the (Morrow, or) next Day, being the Anniverſary of the <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder Treaſon,</hi> made it a double Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day. (And ſince that, he hath made it a threefold Holy-day, or day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying, by his moſt happy Landing at <hi>Tor-Bay,</hi> &amp;c.) as well upon the uſual occaſion, as to teſtifie their Joy, for ſo Bleſſed and Glorious a Match, from which even then, the whole Proteſtant Church throughout <hi>Europe,</hi> began cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to hope for the cruſhing of the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Power; as if the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants had known by ſome Prophetick
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:51909:43"/>Inſtinct, that Heroick Prince, unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly eſpouſing their Intereſt, as well as their religious Princeſs, would one day become their moſt wellcome and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Deliverer and Defender, and make the memorial of the famous 5th. of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> once more ſacred and dear to them, by publick Benefits; no leſs ſignal than thoſe by which it was firſt ennobled, above the common days.</p>
               <p>After which the Prince well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring how very neceſſary his preſence would be in <hi>Holland,</hi> return'd thither with all the haſte he could, with his moſt rich and gracious Acqueſt, that ſince has produced ſo much good to the common Cauſe, and the benefit of the Confederates, as well as of the two moſt potent Sea-Nations of <hi>Europe;</hi> where both He, and his Royal Bride were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with a Magnificence ſuitable to their High and auguſt Quality; and with all the expreſſions and Demonſtrations of Joy that could be expected from a People, ſenſible of their great Happineſs in ſo illuſtrious and powerful Alliance. Upon their firſt publick entrance into the <hi>Hague,</hi> the Bridge was crowned
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:51909:43"/>with Garlands of Triumph, and an Arch was builded through which they paſſed, and on it was written.
<q>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xori &amp; Batavis vivat Naſſovius Hector,</l>
                     <l>Auriaco &amp; Patriae vivat Britannica Princes.</l>
                  </q> And another Arch with another Motto.
<q>Auriaci his Thalamis Batavis dos Regia pax eſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Soon after his return, the <hi>French</hi> King being alarm'd at this Alliance, and the conſequent preparations made by the King and Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> to oblige him to a juſt and reaſonable Peace with his Neighbours, he himſelf with all ſpeed diſpatcht away a project of Peace to <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meguen,</hi> and getting it after ſome Demur, conſented to by the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> by the influence of a Party that ſtill co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertly oppoſed the Prince, and by the diſcouragement the then poſture of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in <hi>England</hi> really gave the States, occaſion'd by the Diſturbances raiſed and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:51909:44"/>fomented there, by the ſame <hi>French</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues to prevent the dreaded effects of the late Marriage; a Treaty was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded ſoon after, that gave ſome reſpite to our renown'd Prince for ſeveral years, from his military Fatigues and weariſome Nights. And now to ſignalize himſelf, no leſs by the Prudent and advantageous reformation of abuſes, and regulation of things relating to the Civil State of his Countrey, than he had been vigorous, and ſucceſsful in the maintenance and defence of its Territories; but however, before that work was perfectly finiſht, the delays and new difficulties made by the <hi>French</hi> King, to ſign the Treaty, though according to his own propoſals, cauſed a new League to be made between the States and King of great <hi>Britain;</hi> and gave the Prince opportunity once more to ſhew his wiſe Conduct, and match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Proweſs againſt that inſolent and powerful Enemy, in a more glorious and ſucceſsful manner than ever before; and well near to have made the <hi>French</hi> King pay dearly for his over refined and ill timed Politicks, with the loſs of his now darling General <hi>Luxemburg</hi>'s whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:51909:44"/>for the ſtrong City of <hi>Mons</hi> having been long blockt, and very much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs'd by the <hi>French,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> having taken his march that way, to hinder all Succours from it; his Highneſs made haſte to the Army, then near the Canal of <hi>Bruſſells,</hi> where the reſt of the Confederate Forces, had newly join'd the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Troops, and purſuant to a reſolution taken for that Effect, in a council of War, march with an intention to attack and diſlodge <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emburg,</hi> after he was joined a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Bruſſels</hi> with a re-inforcement of 6000 <hi>Brandenburghers,</hi> and <hi>Munſterians;</hi> but upon Advice of the Princes March, <hi>Luxemburg</hi> quitting his Camp, took up his head Quarters in the Abby of St. <hi>Denys,</hi> which was a Poſt he thought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceſſible, there being no coming at him but through Woods and Defiles, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with Precipices; yet for all this, our redoubted Prince advanced to that Abby with his left Wing, and with his Right, faced <hi>Caſteau,</hi> which the <hi>French</hi> likewiſe were poſted in, and which was as difficult to force as the other; and as ſoon as ever he had ranged his Army, he firſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:51909:45"/>of all drove the Enemy from a certain Hillock, and then with ſome Canon, played upon another Party of them briskly, that endeavoured to maintain themſelves on one ſide of a Cloiſter near St. <hi>Denys,</hi> who not being able to reſiſt the vigour of the Confederate Dragoons, who drove them from their holds, and maſtered the Cloiſter; whilſt Adjutant General <hi>Collyers,</hi> back'd by General <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vick,</hi> filed his men ſilently and ſpeedily through the narrow Paſſages, and ſliding with an undaunted Courage down the Precipices, repulſed the Enemy in ſpight of all the reſiſtance, within their own lines. In the very midſt of which, our renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Prince with eager warmth and ſpirits enflamed, cryed out aloud, <hi>to me, to me,</hi> to encourage the coming up of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments that were to back the foremoſt; this fight on the left Wing continued till night with a great vigour, beſides which Count <hi>Horn</hi> drew near, and played with his Canon upon ſome <hi>French</hi> Batallions in the Valley, with no ſmall Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:51909:45"/>
               <p>From thence the Prince advanced to <hi>Caſteau,</hi> which was Aſſaulted by the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> in the Right Wing; where his Highneſſes Foot Regiment of Guards, and a Body of <hi>Engliſh,</hi> through Fire and Smoak, after an obſtinate Fight of Five hours, Chaſed the Enemy, at laſt, from a Poſt they thought altogether impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and purſued them a Quarter of a League, through a Field, and down a Precipice, where the River <hi>Haines</hi> runs, toward the farther ſide of <hi>Caſteau.</hi> And our brave Lord of <hi>Oſſory</hi> did ſurpriſing things, with his <hi>Engliſh,</hi> at a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the Guards; where the <hi>French</hi> are ſaid to have loſt more Men than any where elſe; Nor were there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other of the Generals that acted not like Heroes; But more eſpecially the undaunted Prince, who, through whole ſhowers of Bullets, thick as Hail, and Clouds of Fire and Smoak, adventured ſo very far, and preſs'd on with ſo much vigour in the Crowds, that he had been, in all appearance, ſlain, had not the brave Lord <hi>Overkirk</hi> interpoſed between him and a daring Captain, that was running full tilt at his Highneſs, and laid the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:51909:46"/>bold Champion in the ſilent Duſt, for his attempt.</p>
               <p>The Cavalry, in this Fight, had no convenience to be ſerviceable, becauſe of the Narrowneſs of the Paſſages, and ſteep Deſcents of the Ground; but all was acted by the Foot, and Dragoons. The Night alone put a period to the Bloody Fray, and parted the Furious Aſſaults of each Valiant Captain, under the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert of which, the poor Surpriſed and Aſtoniſhed <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> retreated with ſilence, and extream Confuſion, nearer to <hi>Mons,</hi> to ſecure himſelf, between a Wood on one ſide, and a River on the other, leaving to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> the Marks of Victory, as the Field of Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, and moſt part of his wounded Men, and part of his Tents, Baggage, and Match, Powder and Ammunition.</p>
               <p>The <hi>States-General,</hi> on the News of this Fortunate Blow, to ſuch a proud and fierce Enemy, ſent Commiſſioners to his Illuſtrious Highneſs, to Congratulate his happy Victory, which he had won with ſo much Renown, and to thank him for his moſt Careful and Prudent Conduct, in ſuch a long, Bloody and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:51909:46"/>Action; and alſo to Conjure him, in tender Conſideration, to the Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Tranquility of his Country, <hi>and Wellfare of the Reform'd Religion, which ſeem'd, as 'twere, to be tied to the thread of his precious Life, that he would be more careful of his own moſt dear Perſon;</hi> And accordingly to ſhew the World, how great a value they ſet upon his Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; they preſented the Lord <hi>Overkirk,</hi> who had ſo Valiantly Defended him, and ſaved his highly eſteemed Life, with a Rich Sword, hilted with Maſſie-Gold, a pair of Piſtols, Richly and Curiouſly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay'd with Gold, and a pair of Horſe-Buckles of the very ſame.</p>
               <p>Nor had our brave Prince contented himſelf only to have obliged <hi>Luxemburg</hi> to retire, without further purſuing his Advantages; had not he, whilſt he was conſulting what to do, Received Advice, That the Peace was really made and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, between the <hi>French</hi> King, and the <hi>States</hi> ſome days ſince, which made the <hi>French</hi> draw off to the <hi>Sambre,</hi> and the Prince towards <hi>Nivelle;</hi> from whence he returned to the <hi>Hague,</hi> applying his Care thence forward, ſolely to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:51909:47"/>of the Civil Government; till the breaking out of this laſt Perfidious War, upon Occaſion of the Manifeſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of both the ſaid Peace, and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Truce, by the moſt Unjuſt Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences of the <hi>French,</hi> and their Grand Barbarities; Renewed in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and the Dioceſs of <hi>Cologne;</hi> and by the Siege and Surpriſal of <hi>Phillipsburg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that which advances the Mighty and Glorious Atchievements of this, now moſt excellent Monarch, to a pitch of Glory and Greatneſs, above thoſe of any other Heroe of this preſent Age, or perhaps of any former; is, that he has given ſuch Convincing Proofs, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyable Teſtimonies, to the whole World, of their flowing merely from a pure, and untainted Principle of zeal to his Countrey, to true Religion, Virtue, and the Publick Good. That he has left neither Friends nor Enemies, any room to doubt of it, or call it in Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; ſince in the very loweſt Ebb of his Fortune, neither the multiplyed and inſulting Injuries, and repeated Affronts, of an Ungrateful Countrey; Nor, the ſmall proſpect he had of ſaving even his
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:51909:47"/>Patrimonial Eſtate, any other way; nor, all the fair ample and magnificent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of two Mighty Kings, could make him accept of Grandeur, at the Expence of the Liberty and Privileges, though of a very unthankful People, that had ſometime ſtript him of his Ancient Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Rights and Dignities; and ſince, no Motives at all could poſſibly prevail with him, to accept of Soveraignty, in a Free-State, that his Glorious and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Anceſtors made, and himſelf found ſo; Neither from the full Grant of a Conquering Invader; Nor yet, from the Free Donation of the People themſelves; And though the <hi>French</hi> Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, even ſince the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> and the following Truce; and before the breaking out, or eruption of this laſt War, moſt contrary to the expreſs Treaty, very Notoriouſly oppreſs'd, ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ravaged; not only his Soveraign Principality of <hi>Orange,</hi> but all his other Lands and Lordſhips, Dominions and Privileges in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; yet ſuch was his Princely Mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and Patience, that he did never move the <hi>States</hi> into any New quarrel,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:51909:48"/>to redreſs his own wrongs; Nor ſo much as put them upon propoſing any New Articles, in his particular Cauſe, or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; Even at the very making of the Peace, though all the Tranſactions of it were managed in his Preſence, and his Advice ſtill asked about them. Yet, I ſay, ſuch was his goodneſs, never did he inſiſt upon any peculiar Articles, to be inſerted for himſelf, That might be thought, peradventure, to retard the Concluſion of a Treaty; but with a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity without, and beyond all Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; while others preferr'd points of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and private Intereſt, before the Common Peace and Good; He even Quitted his own Pretenſions, and Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon'd the moſt Juſt Demands of Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, for the Devaſtation of his own proper Demeans and Territories, to the Neceſſities of his Countrey; like another <hi>Codrus,</hi> in ſome ſenſe laying down his Prerogatives and Privileges for their Benefit, and Jeoparding his own Life for their Good: And what is ſaid of that Noble Conſul <hi>Publius Decius,</hi> may well be applyed to him; who, when he ſaw his Army greatly diſcomfited, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:51909:48"/>almoſt Overcome, redoubled his Valour, Courage, and was moſt ready and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to hazard his own precious Life, to ſave his Countrey from danger and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
               <p>How exceeding happy were it for their People, if all Princes; and how wonderful happy for all Princes, if all private Perſons, were but half ſo publick-ſpirited, and ſo wholly and perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to the Exigence of the Common Good; as was this Great and Incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Prince, even from his very Cradle? Whoſe Right-Noble, and Unparallell'd ſteps, having traced through the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſtrange Revolutions of <hi>Holland; Let us now</hi> further purſue, in his more Glorious Advances, in the <hi>moſt Memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Revolution</hi> of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> where his Gratuitous, and truly Heroical Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and not his Ambition, have raiſed Him to a Throne He never ſought for, but in Vindication of theſe Nations Rights, more than His own private Ends.</p>
               <p>Thus our <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had hitherto been chiefly on the Defenſive part, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:51909:49"/>at the Heads of Armies, He was not the abſolute Sovereign of; yet, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the many Intrigues and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, devis'd and form'd againſt him, Maugre all the Malice of his open, and ſecret Adverſaries; He reſtored a Torn, and tottering State, or Republick, to its former Peace and Proſperity; and forc'd his own, and his Countreys grandeſt, and moſt Politick Enemy, in the very midſt of his Triumphant Career, to give back, and even quit all his Encroachments in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Netherlands;</hi> with far more Precipitation, than he had at firſt ſeized them with Celerity. Though it was ſuch, as had at that time, ſurpriz'd the whole World. But (bleſſed, and for ever bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God) now a more glorious, and delightful Scene opens it ſelf; And to put him, in a fair, or ſuitable condition, to attack that proud and inſulting Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary in his turn; as well as tamely to ward off his furious and cunning paſſes; Kind Providence leads him on, with a much more wonderful Career and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, even ſwifter than Fame it ſelf, to ſeize the Enemies ſtrongeſt Bulworks, (As was <hi>Great Britain</hi> to the <hi>French</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:51909:49"/>Monarch at that time; If I may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence call it ſo) by the General Conſent, and Invitation of his Nobles, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and Friends, made privy to it; And there drops two Crowns (with a glorious and happy Reverſe of things, and an unexpected Liberty to all his Subjects) upon his Heroical Head, ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be further Graced, and Guarded by the addition of a Third, to make him the fitter Match, both to Grapple <hi>with the Tripple Crown of Rome,</hi> and the Iron Scepter of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in order to bring about this great and aſtoniſhing Deſign, which Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſeem'd to have promiſed him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time before, by thoſe no leſs than Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Phoenomena's, or Apparitions of Glorious Crowns in the Air, over the City of <hi>Orange,</hi> in two different years; As is related in two Narratives, of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Credit; to which, as well known to the Curious, I referr. The Great and Almighty Diſpoſer of Kingdoms, and Juſt Governour of the whole World, ſeems to have employed a Chain of Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, all compoſed of Miracles, from one end to the other; or, at leaſt, of Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:51909:50"/>and Events, as much beyond the Comprehenſion, as the Expectation, both of Friends and Enemies; For as when the Tyrant <hi>Maxentius,</hi> and other <hi>Pagan</hi> Perſecutors, had filled up the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their Cruelties, God (in his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Goodneſs and Mercy) was pleaſed to make, not only part of the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Authority to devolve upon <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> the Revenger of all his Churches wrongs, and Reſtorer of her Liberties, by the death of his Father, and unanimous Election of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Legions. But to order and diſpoſe of all things ſo, as moſt ſtrangely to concur to the elevating him to ſuch a further power, (although he was but the leaſt, amongſt the Seven Sharers of the <hi>Roman</hi> Greatneſs) as to trample upon the reſt, and even throw them all down, and ſet himſelf up, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivall'd in the Throne. Where, fearleſs of the Attempts of any future Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, he might moſt effectually protect, and propagate the true Religion, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his pleaſure.</p>
               <p>So the moſt Barbarous <hi>Maxentius</hi> of our preſent Age, or Common Enemy of Truth, and Oppreſſor of Peace and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:51909:50"/>in <hi>Europe,</hi> viz. the Gallick Tyrant having now carried on his Fury to the greateſt Extremities, that either his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Hounds, or blood thirſty Dragoons could Act, or humane Nature poſſibly ſuffer, both againſt his own innocent Proteſtant Subjects, and againſt thoſe of all his Neighbour Princes and States, of what Religion ſoever, that durſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to diſpute his moſt imperious Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. And having like the Dragon in the Apocalypſe, already beaten down with his Maſſy Tail, ſome of the ſupream Powers next him, which are the leſſer Stars, of <hi>Europe</hi>'s bright Heaven, and being in a fair way to ſweep down all the reſt, ſometime ago, and bring them at leaſt under Subjection; it pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Almighty God in his due time, for to raiſe up another <hi>Michael,</hi> or another <hi>Conſtantine</hi> (many learned Expoſitors thinking that by <hi>Michael,</hi> in that place of the Revelation of St. <hi>John</hi> 12. is meant <hi>Conſtantine</hi>) to ſtop the rage and fury of this <hi>French</hi> Dragon; who with his long Train of bloody Miſcreants, hath ſo very much infeſted Chriſtendom of late Years, and totally to rout this new
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:51909:51"/>
                  <hi>Maxentius</hi> and reſtore Peace, Juſtice and Liberty to the Church and People of God; even out of that moſt ancient, as well as illuſtrious Houſe of <hi>Naſſaw.</hi> A Houſe that once before had ſtopt the dangerous Torrent of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Power, and redeem'd the Captive Netherlands from its Yoak and Thraldom.</p>
               <p>And to let the World know, that the All-wiſe Governour, and moſt righteous Judge of the whole Earth, intended to make uſe of him, not only to retard the Progreſs of the <hi>French</hi> Tyranny for a while, but (we hope) even totally to deſtroy it; and that as the Tyrant him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had begun his own ruine, ſo like the Champion of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> he ſhould go on, and continue to compleat it; and make every Man's Sword in his Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Army to be againſt his Fellow, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that our happy <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s men may with Triumph trample upon their Necks. The Almighty Avenger of the Injuries of his Elect, which cry day and night to him in compaſſion to his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Saints, was not content to uſe the Valour and Conduct of our warlike Prince, only to reſcue the united Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:51909:51"/>but even the whole Proteſtant Religion, and the civil State of all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> from the ſame Bondage and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. And therefore that he might no longer at ſo great a diſadvantage, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate with ſuch an over-grown Monſter, he reſolves to exalt him to the ſublime and ſacred Station of <hi>Royalty,</hi> and that too, in thoſe Ancient and Warlike King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, which he was moſt rightfully inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled to (not only by Conſanguinity, but Affinity) and which had before been happily inſtrumental to lower the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh pride,</hi> on the one hand, and ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to chaſtiſe the inſolency of the more formidable and crafty <hi>French</hi> on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>And if this work was great enough to amaze all beholders, and to put the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical Faith of all ſucceeding Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to the very uttermoſt proof; the manner by which it was effected, muſt of neceſſity appear much more wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſince towards his mighty and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious effect, even the moſt contrary Intereſts, Inclinations, Accidents and Events; and in a word, all the moſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Cauſes imginable, were made to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:51909:52"/>conſpire and concur with as much Union and Harmony, as if they had been all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one and the ſelf-ſame Soul or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (who is <hi>Ens Entium,</hi> as well as <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Cauſarum</hi>) for even Enemies, Friends, Papiſts, Proteſtants, Winds and Seas, all acted towards, and promoted proportionably, this grand and glorious deſign of Providence, even while they contended moſt againſt it.</p>
               <p>Becauſe therefore it will not be a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle edifying and inſtructive to us of theſe Kingdoms, not only in our Religious, but alſo in our Politick and civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, to underſtand rightly and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template (in ſome meaſure) the moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous method uſed by the Divine and over-ruling Power, in producing this <hi>happy and never</hi> to be forgotten <hi>Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> Before we proceed to give you any account of that, we ſhall (as far as we, in a private Station could, or think fit, for particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Perſons to prie into) give you a ſhort view of the ſeveral ſteps that were made on all ſides towards it, till at the laſt, they were all deceived; ſome very hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily as being carried on far beyond their
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:51909:52"/>firſt propoſed ends, and the utmoſt of their hopes; and the others with a more Melancholick Surprize, finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves defeated of their Giant-like expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations, and driven upon ſuch Rocks, as they thought they had ſteered the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt courſe to avoid.</p>
               <p>And firſt, we will begin with the <hi>French</hi> King, his illuſtrious Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s moſt inveterate and irreconcilable Enemy, ever ſince the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal of his Overtures for betraying his Native Countrey, and ſhew what ſteps he himſelf, though a <hi>great Maſter of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks,</hi> made to this great and bleſſed Revolution; which may (by God's bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) prove in due time a means to bring him to Subjection to this ancient and imperial Crown of <hi>England</hi> again.</p>
               <p>In order to ſecure the ſucceſs of the mighty Project, which has been ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly purſued, and carried on by <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th. for ſome Years paſt, of attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the univerſal Monarchy of the <hi>Weſt;</hi> it is not at all doubted by any well ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Politicks, but of all other things, it was moſt highly neceſſary, that his ſureſt Alley, the late King <hi>James,</hi> ſhould
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:51909:53"/>be fully and abſolutely Maſter of his Kingdoms, and till that were effected and put out of all danger of being Travers'd; that it was no leſs needful for him (namely, the <hi>French</hi> King) to treat his Proteſtant Subjects at home well, nay, rather better than ordinary; to keep up a good correſpondence likewiſe with the <hi>Pope,</hi> and other <hi>Roman Catholick Princes;</hi> to have religiouſly obſerved the Truce with the <hi>Empire;</hi> to have diſſembled for ſome time at leaſt, his reſentments againſt the renown'd <hi>Prince of Orange;</hi> to have reſtored him the <hi>Principality</hi> of that Name, which he moſt unjuſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted from his noble Anceſtors; to have perſwaded his Uncle to have careſs'd him; to have kept fair with the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> to have terrified no body with Arms of Cruelties, but only to have ſupply'd his faithful Ally of <hi>great Britain,</hi> conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and privately with ſufficient Moneys, and carried on all his Intrigues elſewere, only with the underhand and potent charms of Gold; to have perſwaded King <hi>James</hi> to have let alone the Intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue of the pretended <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales;</hi> to have abſtain'd from multiplying <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:51909:53"/>Chapels,</hi> and publick toleration of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Prieſts;</hi> to have forborn the planting a Jeſuitical Crew in <hi>Magdalene College;</hi> to have abſtain'd from ſending <hi>Mandamus</hi> after <hi>Mandamus,</hi> to violate the ancient Privileges of that Loyal and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Univerſity of <hi>Oxford;</hi> to have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born the ſending of the moſt Reverend and right Reverend, the Biſhops (<hi>thoſe Pillars of our true Reformed Church of</hi> England) <hi>into the</hi> Tower: In a word, to have contented himſelf only with new modelling Corporations, and inſenſibly new regulating his Army and Court, till all had been ſure. Had he been duly cautious, and circumſpect in theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, it had been ſhrewdly probable, if not an aſſured thing, that a great part of the Clergy, Nobility and Gentry of <hi>England,</hi> would not have ſeen through the late king <hi>James</hi>'s Deſigns, nor at leaſt have believed them, till perhaps they had felt the Chains about their Necks; that his Army would have ſtood by him till at laſt, when things had been full ripe for it; they had ſeen the greateſt part of themſelves ſhip'd off, upon ſome ſuddain Foreign Quarrel, and their places ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:51909:54"/>at home, by Soldiers in <hi>French</hi> pay. And this might have been peradventure, ſo politickly managed, as not to have alarm'd the illuſtrious Ancient and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> the <hi>Hollanders</hi> perchance would have unconcernedly lookt upon it, being ſo exceedingly bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied about the <hi>Indian</hi> Gold and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; and the Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> might perhaps have been lull'd faſt aſleep, by their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Peace, vaſt Trading and Plenty: And this ſtep once gain'd, the ſubtil Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur could have ſecurely oppreſs'd the Spaniſh <hi>Netherlands,</hi> once again, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run <hi>Holland,</hi> and have invaded the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi> when the imperial Forces ſhould have been perhaps (as dreaming of no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from the <hi>Rhine</hi>) employed as far as <hi>Bulgaria</hi> or <hi>Romania</hi> in chaſing the <hi>Turks;</hi> and theſe were the Counſels of his wiſeſt <hi>Ahitophel,</hi> the late famous <hi>Louvois.</hi> But he that taketh the wiſe in his own craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs, and maketh Diviners mad, and brings good out of Evil, cauſed that vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Proverb here to prove an Oracle, That <hi>Quos perdere vult deus, prius de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentat,</hi> God firſt blinds or renders fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:51909:54"/>thoſe whom he hath reſolv'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy; for the deep and moſt ſurely laid Counſels of that great States-man, were providentially over-rul'd by the fawning influence of Jeſuited Heads, whereof ſome were on Mens, and ſome more advantageouſly placed on the necks of the charming and ſeldom fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sex; who working upon the <hi>French King's</hi> unmeaſurable Vanity, and unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Ambition, very eaſily perſwaded him, that his Power was now grown ſo Formidable, and all his Forces for Sea and Land ſo well diſciplin'd, that he needed not to be ſo much inſlaved to thoſe cautious Meaſures, propoſed by his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of State, as he had been hitherto; but leaving thoſe flow paces, <hi>to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Houſe of</hi> Auſtria, <hi>who placed moſt of their Majeſty in deliberate Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and more ſlow Executions;</hi> he might now reſume his natural briskneſs, and advance ſecurely the neareſt way to <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> eſpecially ſince <hi>England</hi> was then under a <hi>Roman Catholick Prince,</hi> entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at his Devotion upon all occaſions. And with all, ſeeing things at that time were in ſuch a poſture, that the imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:51909:55"/>Force was ſo wholly taken up in a War, in the remoteſt Frontiers of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Europe,</hi> there was no other Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that either durſt, or could timely and effectually oppoſe his Attempts, either in Religious or civil Matters; and that the moſt active Spirits, that were beſt able, or moſt diſpoſed to obſtruct the courſe of his proſperous advance, were many of them (as well Princes, as their Miniſters) now become wonderful docile and diſciplinable without word of Mouth, or beat of Drum, only by the bare Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre and Loadſtone of ſome choice gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>Lewis</hi>'s, Art fully brandiſht before their Eyes, by a <hi>French</hi> Emiſſary. And theſe plauſible advices, which ſo tickled him in his moſt ſenſible part, prevail'd on him to Act in all things juſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of what he had ſometime before been counſell'd by thoſe who beſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and had all along (when believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) moſt ſucceſsfully purſued and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the intereſt of that univerſal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty, which they would have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded him to court gently; but his hot Jeſuited Councellors, would needs have him attempt to raviſh; which impotent
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:51909:55"/>and ill tim'd Eſſay, has now ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm'd the Coy Lady <hi>(<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy)</hi> that if we miſtake not, having providentially untwiſted her ſelf out of his Arms, and got clearly out of the reach of his violence, ſhe will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit his cringing Addreſſes any more. For looking, not without cauſe, upon both the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and the <hi>Pope,</hi> though moſt oppoſite in Principles, to be moſt mighty obſtacles in his way to <hi>univerſal Sovereignty,</hi> the one as being perfectly inform'd, in the knowledge of the truth in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and zealouſly affected to the Defence both of their Natural, and civil liberty as Men and Subjects, and of their Spiritual privileges as <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and the other pretending not only a kind of Sovereignty over a great part of all Princes, Subject, of the <hi>Roman Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> (namely the Clergy, both Secular and Regular) and all religious Perſons; and by them a dangerous rivalling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence over all the reſt of their people. But alſo holding (as t'were) the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of power in his own hand, even in temporal matters, between all Popiſh Princes and States; and being no leſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs'd
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:51909:56"/>for maintenance of himſelf and ſucceſſors, in that Power and Figure, to hinder the growth of any one Prince to an exceſſive Grandeur, than the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant were for the preſervation, both of their <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> Liberties; and therefore having agreeably enough to the rules of Policy, reſolv'd equally upon the removal of both theſe dangerous adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, by totally deſtroying the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and caſting Popery it ſelf into a new Model, that might diſpoſe the whole body of Chriſtians, both Clergy and Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to ſuch a tame and ſupple temper, as might make them alike ſuſceptible of his intended univerſal Yoak.</p>
               <p>Thus it pleaſed the <hi>Almighty Being,</hi> to make him the very chiefeſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment himſelf, in breaking the neck of theſe his greateſt and ambitious Deſigns, by leaving him to the infatuating deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of new Jeſuited Adviſers, whereby he forſook the more ſure <hi>Maxims</hi> of his old ſagacious Counſellors, <hi>Richelieu, Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin,</hi> and the <hi>Le Telliers;</hi> and to drive <hi>Jehu</hi>-like and raſhly to attempt to do all at once, what ſhould have been enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd at very different Seaſons, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:51909:56"/>thoſe wiſely tim'd one after the other. For at the ſame time, the poor <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> were ſo hotly perſecuted, and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly handled, the <hi>Pope's Authority</hi> was then as briskly attack'd, not only in the buſineſs of the <hi>Ragalia,</hi> but in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other more fundamental points, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting no leſs than the utter ruin of the whole Machine of that Eccleſiaſtical Monarchy; inſomuch that this great haughty Monſieur thought himſelf doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſome prodigious Giant, that could reach both poles at once, with each arm one, <hi>viz.</hi> That of the <hi>Northern Hereſie</hi> (as they term it) and the <hi>Southern Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,</hi> and ſnapping them off ſhort, to make the World turn thence forward up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſole Axle tree of his Arbitrary and imperious will, as ſufficiently appeared, not only by the proceedings of the <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonne,</hi> of the Aſſembly of the Clergy of <hi>Paris,</hi> and of the <hi>French</hi> Kings chief Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate, Mr. <hi>Talon,</hi> and by the ſtrange acting of Mr. <hi>Lavardin</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, and the writings of Mr. <hi>Maimburg:</hi> The Writings and Actings of all which, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Authority of the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> were hardly ever out-done by thoſe they
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:51909:57"/>vainly call'd, and at the ſame time per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted as Hereticks; but alſo by many odd Theſes and Poſitions, then main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in ſeveral places up and down that Kingdom, whereof theſe were ſome, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. That as Princes had the Power of nominating other Biſhops to the Sees vacant in their Dominions; ſo the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Prince in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> had a right of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>inating the greateſt Biſhop, namely, the Pope.</p>
               <p n="2">II. That the Election of a Pope, by the private College of Cardinals, was an Innovation.</p>
               <p n="3">III. That the Kings of <hi>France</hi> having ſome time delivered the Popes from the oppreſſion of the <hi>Lombards,</hi> and founded the new Empire of the <hi>Weſt,</hi> acquired thereby not only a right to chuſe future Popes, but that they are thereby ſtill the only <hi>Rightful Emperours,</hi> the eldeſt Sons of the Church, and the greateſt of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:51909:57"/>
               <p>Which by the way, would be a ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Argument, to prove both the Empire, Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> and the Election of the Pope, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to belong to the young Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> than to <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th. that young Prince, being Lineally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from <hi>Charles</hi> the great, whoſe race that of the preſent <hi>French</hi> King ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. That the reſidence of the Pope, is not fixed any more to <hi>Rome</hi> than it was formerly to <hi>Antioch;</hi> but that it ought to be in the capital City of the greateſt <hi>Chriſtian Prince, pro tempore,</hi> or in ſuch other place as he ſhall approve of.</p>
               <p n="5">V. That the <hi>French</hi> King in his Right, may if he pleaſe diveſt the Cardinals of <hi>Rome</hi> of the right of Election of Popes, or diſown ſuch as they ſhall chooſe, and make an Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> or any other prelate <hi>Pope;</hi> that ſuch Pope ſo nominated, would be a true Succeſſor of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> though he ſhould dwell at <hi>Paris,</hi> or elſewhere, and have no tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Dominions; and that he ought to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:51909:58"/>be own'd as ſuch, by all other <hi>Roman Catholick Princes,</hi> becauſe nominated by the Succeſſor of <hi>Charles</hi> the great, and a Prince no leſs great in Power, than he who was the reſtorer of the Papal Authority.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. That as the Temporal Dominions of the Pope, were at firſt given him by <hi>French</hi> Kings, they may be forfeited, and taken back again; and that for the peaceable enjoyment of them, the Pope ought to grant freedom of Quarters to the <hi>French</hi> Kings Ambaſſador at <hi>Rome,</hi> as an acknowledgment of the Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of him of whom he holds them, and that he ought not to grant the like pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege to any other Ambaſſador.</p>
               <p>Theſe and many other ſuch like <hi>Theſes</hi> there were, about the Pope's Power and Authority in Spirituals as well as Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals, whereby they allow'd him little more than what is granted by ſome <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> and what any other Patriarchs do enjoy, as is deducible from their own Writings; in this you may ſee an Image of the new Popery, intended by
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:51909:58"/>the <hi>French</hi> King, who by this appears to be only ſo far for Popery, as will ſerve his own turn, to make both Pope and Papiſts his Vaſſals or Slaves; (what other meaning had he, when he treated the Nuns of the Society ſo ſeverely, called the Nuns of the <hi>Infancy of Jeſus,</hi> and threw Madam <hi>Mondeuville</hi> into Priſon for mediating, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) Such is the favour he deſigns to afford them, if ever in his power, and a great favour too; they that will be Proteſtants, or will not be Papiſts, thus, <hi>Alamode de France,</hi> being both equally deſtituted to utter Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And to convince you further, that theſe were the real and unfeigned <hi>Deſigns</hi> of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th. King of <hi>France;</hi> a Friend of mine that intimately knew the Perſon, aſſured me that when the <hi>French</hi> Clergy were aſſembled in the year 1682. he ſent a skillful Antiquary into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to ſearch diligently and moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curately our Records in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> to ſee and learn what ſteps King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. had made in his Rupture with <hi>Rome,</hi> and which of them might moſt effectually be put in practice by him, in order to accompliſh his foreſaid ends.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:51909:59"/>
               <p>But what followed from this Conduct, of driving on ſo very furiouſly at one and the ſame time, two ſuch <hi>contrary deſigns</hi> as theſe were one towards the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to bring about the ſame ſelf purpoſe? Why, the ſame that's reported to have happen'd to the famous Wreſtler <hi>Milo,</hi> who in oſtentation of his great ſtrength, endeavour'd to rive a ſunder with his Arms, the main Limbs of adouble bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Tree. He made a ſhift indeed, to ſplit them in part, but not being able to go through perfectly with the Work, was, by their recoiling Force, catch'd ſo faſt himſelf between them, as to be made a defenceleſs prey to the wild Beaſts. Thus <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th. by firſt perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and attacking the Pope's <hi>Authority,</hi> has reduced himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Labyrinth, and brought a general War upon his Dominions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By his moſt ſevere Perſecution, and endeavour abſolutely to exterminate the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> he bereſt himſelf wholly of ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of thouſands of his wealthieſt and moſt uſeful Subjects, conſiſting of many of the moſt trading Merchants, beſt Officers, and expert Mariners and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:51909:59"/>Seamen, to the ſtrengthening of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies round about, in the adjacent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and the utter ruin of many <hi>Roman Catholick Families,</hi> their Creditors, or that were of their Dependance; and fill'd his Kingdom with Hypocrites, and Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, who required as many Troops, to watch over their Conduct (which gave and will give continual Jealouſies and Alarms) as would have ſerved him, to compoſe a good Army, to defend the largeſt of his Frontiers, and that which was more fatal to him, than all the reſt; theſe cruel and moſt barbarous proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of his, exaſperated the Spirits of the warlike and valorous <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by made it altogether impracticable; for his great Ally King <hi>James,</hi> to make himſelf Maſter enough of his People, to be ſo ſerviceable to him, in his Attempts towards univerſal <hi>Monarchy,</hi> as he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps might have been, is to ſweeten the minds of the undaunted Britiſh <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants;</hi> Monſieur <hi>Lewis</hi> had politickly (at the late King <hi>James</hi>'s firſt acceſſion to the Crown) and voluntarily reſtored the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants their old Liberties and Privileges, which he ſolemnly ſwore
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:51909:60"/>to maintain at his Coronation. (For it muſt be acknowledged on all hands, that they, namely the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> were his faithfulleſt Subjects, who put the Crown on his head) out of a feigned, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended difference to the late King <hi>James</hi>'s intreaties, and reſpect to the interceſſion of the <hi>Engliſh Church and Nation.</hi> To have been thus before hand with us in Civility, what ſavours would it not have extorted from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, towards the Papiſts here? And what Jealouſies would it not have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd? And how much more eaſily, might we have been catcht by tickling, than by ſcratching; eſpecially, had he at the ſame time kept Quiet, and juſtly obſerved the laſt concluded Truce with the <hi>Confederates.</hi> But acting the quite contrary, it made the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Conduct, by far the more narrowly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into, and rendred all people both Jealous and Affraid, even of his favours, and made them juſtly ſuſpect the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of ſuch a Prince (though at the ſame time declaring himſelf for liberty of Conſcience) whom they ſaw ſo viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and amicably to correſpond with a
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:51909:60"/>notorious Tyrant of the ſame Religion, ſo very eager upon Perſecution, as daily to fill his greateſt and beſt Friends Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, at ſo unſeaſonable a nick of time with whole Shoals, or multitudes of Exiles, in ſuch a miſerable plight, as he knew could not but ſtir up the reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the hardy <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants, againſt both Princes; and thereby (as we have ſaid) diſabled his Ally from getting that power into his hands, which was ſo neceſſary for his aſſiſtance, in the accompliſhment of thoſe Ambitious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, he ſince unproſperouſly purſues. And on the other hand, by acting as we have inſtanc'd againſt the Pope, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering ſo plainly at a <hi>new Model of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> yea, and making ſuch brisk attempts upon the temporal Dominions and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories of the Pope himſelf, and that in his own <hi>Capital City</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> as he did by his Ambaſſador, the Marqueſs of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verdine;</hi> who, not only exaſperated the then Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 11th. a perſon not of a temper, either to be hectored, or to be wheedled out of the Rights and Reſpects he thought due to him, from a Prince pretending to the Titles of Moſt
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:51909:61"/>Chriſtian, and of Eldeſt Son of the Church; one who not only very well underſtood his own Intereſt, and the whole drift of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th. But like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe firſt of all, gave the alarm to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes of the <hi>Roman Communion,</hi> who thereby plainly ſeeing, that not only their Territories, but their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo, was in no ſmall danger from ſuch deſigns; and that the <hi>French</hi> Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan intended, <hi>Mahomet</hi>-like, to have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminated Popery, properly ſo called, as well as <hi>Proteſtantiſm,</hi> and to have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced by the Sword, a third Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hateful to both; which was to have been <hi>Franco-Catholick,</hi> more than <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> and to have been new Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened by that Name, aſſoon as <hi>Paris,</hi> by the prevailing Arms, or more availing pieces of Gold of <hi>Lewis Le Grand,</hi> ſhould have been made the Metropolis Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of all <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> Hence he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits his Statue to be erected and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his Subjects in the poſture of Proſternation; he permits Holy-days to be Dedicated to them, and Harangues to be made to them, as if they were really ſo many Deities, ſo that upon the Baſis
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:51909:61"/>of theſe baſe Idols, you may ſee theſe Inſcriptions in Capital Letters, <hi>TO THE IMMORTAL MAN.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this Alarm of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the XIth, all <hi>Europe</hi> began to look with a Suſpicious Eye upon the Proceedings of the <hi>French</hi> Monarch, and his Ally of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and minded more ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly every paſſage between them: And though <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth endeavoured extreamly to throw duſt in their eyes, by extirpating and deſtroying the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> in his own Dominions, out of a zeal, as he feigned, or profeſs'd, to the Holy See; yet they could not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend how that could poſſibly conſiſt with his continual abetting, and corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borating the <hi>Turks,</hi> and ſupporting Count <hi>Teckely,</hi> and his Proteſtant fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers in <hi>Hungary;</hi> and much leſs with his moſt Undutiful and Inſolent Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to the Pope, and with ſuch formal Deciſions, as ſtruck at the very Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Authority, and of the whole Fabrick of the <hi>Roman Catholick Religion,</hi> as diſtinguiſhed from the Proteſtant. No, they now ſcann'd every Period, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of <hi>Maimburgh</hi>'s Works, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:51909:62"/>ſmelt out whoſe Senſe, and in what view he ſpoke; And that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd the Monarchy of the <hi>Roman Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,</hi> only to erect upon its Ruines an Univerſal Empire, for his Maſter <hi>Lewis;</hi> They thoroughly examined the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> and of all the <hi>French</hi> Clergy: Took good notice of the many odd <hi>Theſes</hi> put up, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd daily in that Kingdom; And, in a word, let nothing paſs of that nature, without the ſtricteſt Obſervation; nor without preparing under-hand, an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition ready to be exerted, in fit time and place. The Pope, though indeed for his part, he could heartily have wiſh'd that the <hi>Proteſtant Name</hi> were ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly aboliſh'd, and all Chriſtian States as firmly ſubjected to his See, as ſome Ages before; and particularly, would have unfeignedly rejoyc'd to have ſeen the Return of ſo important a Member of his pretended ancient Empire, to his Communion, as were the <hi>Brittiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions:</hi> Yet he could not well brook to ſee them, or the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants either, made but as Steps to raiſe the Throne of the <hi>French</hi> Monarch high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:51909:62"/>to over-look his; And, of an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Pope, to make him, but as a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cairous <hi>Mufti,</hi> under a New Weſtern <hi>Sultan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He thought with himſelf, that it would ſignifie very little for him to gain ground upon the Quickſands of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> where he could promiſe himſelf no ſure footing: Whilſt he ſhould loſe his firmer Poſſeſſions in <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf: And took but little pleaſure, whatever outward countenance he ſhew'd, in the hopes that were given him by the <hi>French</hi> Tyrant, of the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of a Mock-Popery there, whilſt the true one ſhould be ruin'd, and totally blown up by the Crafty Engi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers of <hi>France.</hi> And the Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a Prevailing <hi>French</hi> Popery, were indeed to him far more dreadful of the two, than that of the Triumphing of (what they fooliſhly call'd) the <hi>Northern Hereſie.</hi> And the Religious old Father thought (as well he might) that there was much leſs danger, from an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and profeſs'd Enemy, than a ſecret Traytor; And that, according to the Proverb, <hi>Ira quae tegitur nocet,</hi> There
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:51909:63"/>was leſs harm from an openly aſſailing Lion, than a private Boſom Viper. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was he ignorant of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth's ſtrict Confederacy with the Male contents in <hi>Hungary,</hi> who are all <hi>Lutherans,</hi> or <hi>Calviniſts;</hi> At the very ſame time he Perſecuted his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects at home, and aboliſh'd the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and ordered the <hi>Nuns of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy,</hi> becauſe they ſided with the <hi>Pope,</hi> to go home to their Parents, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever elſe they pleaſed: Commanded that their Altars ſhould be pull'd down, the Ornaments and Holy Utenſils car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away, and thoſe Conſecrated Places to be moſt vilely prophan'd. And yet, at this very time, he ſuffer'd himſelf in Publick Theams, to be advanc'd above the Glorious <hi>Angels of God,</hi> and to be look'd upon as a Proof of the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime <hi>Myſteries:</hi> And thoſe ſame words, which were once ſpoken of the <hi>Holy Jeſus, the Son of God,</hi> he allow'd to be apply'd to himſelf, Yea, (in ſome ſort) Commanded it; <hi>My Works are for the King;</hi> Who is the King? <hi>'Tis Lewis the Great, the King of Glory.</hi> Nay, which is much more, he ſuffer'd himſelf to be Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp'd
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:51909:63"/>like a Deity. You might have ſeen this in the Five Works upon the <hi>Greeve,</hi> under the Title of the Temple of Honour, which was made to Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the Erecting the New Statue, that was ſet up in the Court of the <hi>Common-Hall</hi> of the City. The Inſcriptiono which was upon the Frize, and upon the Four Fronts of the Temple, was after the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitical manner, and no leſs Impious;</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The City of</hi> Paris, <hi>Pious, Loyal,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Obedient, Devoted by Publick Vows</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To the Divinity and Majeſty of—</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lewis <hi>the Great, the Father of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As a Monument of their Duty, Dedicate</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Conſecrate a Temple.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>The <hi>Pope,</hi> who was not half ſo timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, as ſome of the other Temporal Princes of his <hi>Communion,</hi> could not, nor did not look tamely on theſe Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; but oppoſed them with all his Might, and with a Vigour, that ſhewed a <hi>Magnanimous Spirit;</hi> and that waked all the reſt of the Roman Catholick Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, out of the Lethargy they ſeem'd to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:51909:64"/>have been laid into by the Charms of <hi>French</hi> Sorcery. For he Wrote vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly againſt the Severities uſed againſt the Proteſtants, cauſing his Beloved Daughter, the late Queen <hi>Chriſtina of Sweden,</hi> to Write to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; He diſapproved the <hi>French</hi> King's Dragoon Converſions; loudly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd againſt his Violences, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious Uſurpations, Cloaked un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Name of <hi>Regalia;</hi> Cited Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>La Chaieſe,</hi> and Father <hi>Maimbourg</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> to Anſwer their Diſobedience; and cauſed the latter to be actually thruſt out of the Jeſuits Society. Takes away the Liberty of Quarters from the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſadors at <hi>Rome,</hi> which, with all their Hectoring, they could never yet regain; Cauſed the Proceedings of the <hi>French</hi> Clergy to be Cenſured; Denies to <hi>Preconize,</hi> or Confirm any <hi>French</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; ſtirs up the <hi>Illuſtrious Houſe</hi> of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria</hi> to act vigorouſly againſt the <hi>French</hi> King. Fiercely oppoſes the Election of the Cardinal of <hi>Furſtemburg</hi> to the <hi>Arch-Biſhoprick</hi> and <hi>Electorate</hi> of <hi>Cologne,</hi> and lets all the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> as well as the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> ſee their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:51909:64"/>therein; and even doth all he can, by his Nuncio at <hi>London,</hi> and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Imperial Ambaſſadours</hi> there, to draw off King <hi>James</hi> from the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt, and from taking <hi>French</hi> Meaſures, either in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Politicks; And to perſwade him to forbear making uſe of <hi>Frenchified</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, or Prieſts, of what Nation ſoever; and uſe only thoſe of the <hi>Auſtrian Party;</hi> And to pleaſe his own People, by mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> and holding the Balance of <hi>Europe</hi> ſtiff a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>France;</hi> and for that end, whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Private Submiſſions he had made to His Holineſs, yet to have let matters in Religion throughout the <hi>Britiſh Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, be in Statu quo prius,</hi> at leaſt, till the preſent Great War, with both the <hi>We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern</hi> and <hi>Eaſtern Turk</hi> had been over: when by the Favour of a profound Peace, Reigning among all Catholick Princes, he might have made uſe of their Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and Concurring Aſſiſtance, to have ſecurely Re-eſtabliſh'd, not the <hi>French,</hi> but true and Genuine Popery, in <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> without hazarding the Diminution of the Majeſty of his
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:51909:65"/>Crown, or of the Greatneſs and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency of his Power; or rendring himſelf to be but a Deputy, or Tributa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry King, as he muſt do, if he went on to augment the already too formidable, and inſolent Power of <hi>France;</hi> and to take <hi>French</hi> Meaſures, and neglecting to uſe his own Eyes, and the Advices of his own Agents, Spies and Intelligencers, to make uſe only of <hi>French</hi> Spectacles, <hi>French</hi> Intelligences, and the Dictates of <hi>French</hi> Miniſters of State, and <hi>Frenchifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Jeſuits, or Monks, to ſteer by; which would, at length, but make him Split a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Fatal Rock: a Ship fraught with the faireſt hopes, that ever ſet out in Great <hi>Britain,</hi> under St. <hi>Peter's Banners,</hi> ſince Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> days.</p>
               <p>Theſe were the Actions of <hi>Pope Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent the XIth.</hi> againſt <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth, and ſuch were the Remonſtrances and Advices both of his Nuncio, and the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> and <hi>Imperial</hi> Ambaſſadours in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to the late King <hi>James;</hi> Which His <hi>Imperial Majeſty</hi> afterwards, in his Letter to the Late King, in Anſwer to one from him, relating the Doleful Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Abdication, hints at; and tells
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:51909:65"/>him, Had they been followed, he might ſtill have been upon the Throne, with all the Advantages of a <hi>Great Engliſh Monarch.</hi> The obſtinate neglect of which Councils, the moſt ſafe and prudent that could be given to a Popiſh King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> at that time of the day, together with the formidable growth, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Inſolent Proceedings of the <hi>French</hi> King, cauſed both the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the Ancient and Potent Houſes of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> not onely to League themſelves together, but alſo for their Common Defence, both againſt <hi>French</hi> Popery, and <hi>French</hi> Power, which were advancing hand in hand to attack them; And which, if ſuffer'd to fix footing in <hi>England,</hi> would ſhortly become altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther irreſiſtible to Confederate. Nay, even with the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Princes and Powers; the one <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Princes of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately; and the other, namely, the <hi>Pope,</hi> Mediately, and Covertly; by abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and underhand promoting the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues and Attempts of the others, for the carrying on ſuch Deſigns as ſhould divide <hi>England</hi> from the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:51909:66"/>though it were by the Diſmounting a Prince of their own Religion, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> upon the Throne. They being very well ſatisfied it was much ſafer for Popery in General, as well as for their particular Temporal Intereſts, to ſee a <hi>Proteſtant wear the Crown of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> though to the ſeeming diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Popiſh Religion in that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Kingdom; that would help them to balance the exceſſive Power of <hi>France,</hi> than to ſuffer a Popiſh <hi>King of Great Britain,</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Stamp, to aſſiſt the <hi>French</hi> Monarch to enſlave all other, much more <hi>Catholick Princes;</hi> depreſs the Papal Power it ſelf, and impoſe a Popery worſe to them, than what their erroneous fancies teach them to call <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie.</hi> But that which clincht the Nail home, and which not only confirm'd them in thoſe Reſolutions, but haſtned them to a ſpeedy execution of them, were three very dangerous Attempts of the <hi>French</hi> King; the one was the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Intereſt the <hi>French</hi> had made, to get their Devoted Creature, that Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Traytor to his Countrey, the <hi>Quondam Prince William,</hi> but now Biſhop of <hi>Stras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:51909:66"/>and Cardinal of <hi>Furſtemberg,</hi> to be choſen Elector of <hi>Cologne,</hi> that he might be the more able to back his old Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th. in all his Encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the <hi>Empire,</hi> in awing the reſt of the Electors on the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and by them influencing the whole <hi>Electoral College,</hi> to deprive the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> of the Imperial <hi>Dignity,</hi> by chooſing <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Dauphin, for King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> or Succeſſor to the <hi>Emperor</hi> inſtead of the Arch-Duke <hi>Joſeph,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The ſecond was, his breaking ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſly the new made Truce, though ſworn to for twenty Years, and under the pretence of backing the Election of his dear Cardinal, and purſuing ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Demands, he was pleaſed to make in the name of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans,</hi> of the preſent Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> to beſiege and ſurpriſe <hi>Philipsburg,</hi> and committing a thouſand Outrages, and Hoſtilities elſewhere, at a time, when the Emperour truſting to the ſecurity of the twenty years Truce, was employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Arms to repell the Turks, the ſworn Enemies of Chriſtianity in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteſt borders of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:51909:67"/>
               <p>The third was, his declaring War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Holland,</hi> becauſe they ſeem'd to oppoſe his baſe illegal violences, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to force an Election, which ought to be free, and that in a Country, where the proud Tyrant had no right to meddle, and which was ſo near their Frontiers; and that too, being not content with that, as if he had had the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Head under his Girdle, he was pleaſed to threaten, that <hi>England</hi> ſhould do the like; and as a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of it, perſwaded King <hi>James,</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly, and without any reaſon gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to recall his Subjects out of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Service, at a time when he had no viſible occaſion for them.</p>
               <p>Theſe Reaſons all put together, made the <hi>Roman Catholick Princes to league with</hi> Holland, and the <hi>Proteſtant Princes</hi> of Germany; and to favour the Bleſſed and Glorious Deſign, of our preſent So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Lord, King <hi>William,</hi> &amp;c. to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to break the ſtrong Chains that were preparing for all <hi>Europe,</hi> by firſt breaking thoſe of <hi>England,</hi> and by ſeizing before hand of the Reins of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, over thoſe moſt willing Nations
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:51909:67"/>that were ſo exceeding glad of his ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable help in time of Need; the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of which ſhould he delay a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was viſibly going to be moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly alienated from him, by the means of a ſuppoſititious Child, brought upon the Stage only for a blind, and to be conſign'd unto the Tyrannical hands of the <hi>French</hi> Monarch.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, that which made an end of giving a through alarm to the <hi>Pope,</hi> was, the <hi>French</hi> King's inſulting and inſolent proceedings, by his Ambaſſador at <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf; his invading of <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>Piedmont,</hi> and carrying thereby the War into <hi>Italy;</hi> which by the bye, is now one of the moſt troubleſome Thorns, that he has in his foot, and which he would moſt fain be rid of, it having proved notwithſtanding his Succeſſes, the moſt chargeable and incommodious War to him, next that of <hi>England,</hi> of any of the reſt. Which conſiderations made the Pope, and the reſt of the <hi>Roman Princes,</hi> and particularly the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> employ ſundry Prieſts, devoted to their intereſts, but as ſo many Spies about the late King <hi>James,</hi> to fiſh out the ſecrets of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:51909:68"/>the <hi>Frenchified</hi> Cabal; and to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate the ſame, from time to time, to the late <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſadour, who fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to advertiſe the King his Maſter, the <hi>illuſtrious Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> and all the Allies, nor yet to communicate them to the Nobility, Gentry and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified Citizens of <hi>England;</hi> to whoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret advice, thus obtain'd (next to God Almighty) we owe all the ſatisfactory light we have had into the dark Intrigue of the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> which above all things, gave the laſt and moſt powerful Impulſe to thoſe Motions, that brought about the late Happy and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful <hi>Revolution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having thus ſeen how the <hi>French</hi> King, by catching too eagerly at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy,</hi> and his Ally the late King <hi>James,</hi> by adhering to the <hi>French</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel more than to his own <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, ſtirr'd up the moſt zealous Princes of the <hi>Roman Communion,</hi> and even the Pope himſelf, to ſide with the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Powers againſt them, and readily to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur with theſe laſt, even to the ſuppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all hopes of their own Religions, becoming predominant in <hi>England;</hi> and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:51909:68"/>rather than ſee it planted there by <hi>French</hi> hands. We cannot therefore at all won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that the <hi>Proteſtant Foreign Powers,</hi> and the people of <hi>Great Britain</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, who had much greater obligations to it, both from their Civil and Religious <hi>Intereſts,</hi> ſhould willingly unite to the ſame purpoſe, and take the opportunity of entring into ſo potent a Confederacy, to preſerve their Religion and ſecure their Poſterity, and all that was <hi>near and dear</hi> to them in reference to both Worlds; when they ſaw the very Popiſh Princes, and the head of that Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſo hotly take the Alarm, though nothing ſo nearly, nor ſo deeply con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the danger as themſelves; and by their diligence in being ſo ready to join with them, Tacitly to reproach their Dulneſs and awake them timely and vigorouſly, to <hi>ſecond</hi> the noble Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, of ſuch a Wiſe and valiant Prince; whoſe known injurious Treatment, by both Kings and very legal and rightful pretentions, to the ſucceſſion of the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Throne,</hi> as well as his Exemplary and Military virtues, had now gotten him ſo large a ſhare, or intereſt in the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:51909:69"/>hearts of all the oppreſs'd People of the three Kingdoms, and gave them and all their Foreign Friends, ſuch fair dawning hopes of a moſt happy and glorious Succeſs.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> they were mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to aſſiſt in this <hi>great Enterpriſe,</hi> not only by the conſideration of their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Intereſt, as one of the chief Parties in War with <hi>France;</hi> nor yet, wholly and ſolely out of gratitude to the coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous and illuſtrious Prince, who had ſo lately reſcued them from imminent ruin, and reſtored them to as great a Beauty of Order, and formidable Strength, as any other Republick; (though no doubt theſe Motives ſwayed them very much.) But being particularly prick'd forward, and provoked by daily menaces from <hi>France,</hi> and appearing and moſt convincing Mark from <hi>England,</hi> that the late King, did not they firſt prevent him, would certainly declare War againſt them, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for that purpoſe already recall'd all his Forces, and made ſeveral other ſteps that way by his Envoy Marqueſs <hi>D'Abbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville;</hi> they could not chuſe but think it great Prudence, as well as Gratitude, to cloſe with their renowned Prince, and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:51909:69"/>our mighty Deliverer, and anſwer the calls and intreaties of their ſore oppreſs'd Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Who in former Ages, had given them a lift, and partly delivered them from Bondage, and who being now once aſſiſted and freed by them, would in all probability, contribute moſt effectually of any of their Allies, to the repulſing of that ſubtil encroaching Foe, that threaten'd them with a ſecond Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; and in order to prevent the fatal Stroke intended againſt them, as the chief Obſtacles of erecting Deſpotick Power and Arbitrary Government in <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and from thence infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it upon all <hi>Europe,</hi> by lending a powerful, timely and hearty Aſſiſtance to his Highneſs.</p>
               <p>Add to this the <hi>Sympathy</hi> and feeling compaſſion, which the horrid ſufferings of the poor Proteſtants in <hi>France,</hi> many thouſands whereof wearing the cruel Marks and Badges of <hi>French</hi> Barbarity; were daily objects of their Eyes, moved their Chriſtian hearts, which laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, as well as that of their civil Intereſt, of which the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Netherlands, were the great <hi>Barrier</hi>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:51909:70"/>and <hi>Bulwark,</hi> as likewiſe the Deſign they had diſcovered to be Hatched by <hi>France</hi> to devour them all one after another, and to extirpate the Proteſtant Name, (ſcurrillouſly nick-nam'd by the ſcoffing Enemy, the <hi>Northern</hi> Hereſie) from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven, prevail'd likewiſe with the reſt of the <hi>German</hi> Proteſtant Princes, eſpecially the moſt wiſe and experienc'd Prince the then Elector of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> his Heroical Highneſs's illuſtrious Kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and the Princes of the Houſes of <hi>Saxony, Lunenburg</hi> and <hi>Heſſe,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute their beſt Helps as well as Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, to the accompliſhment of that great Heaven-inſpired Enterpriſe.</p>
               <p>Next the Cauſes that moved the illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> beſides all the former conſiderations and motives, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to him with all the reſt, were ſo viſibly ſenſible, and moſt juſt, and of ſo very cogent a nature, that to reſiſt them, had been to reſiſt both Senſe and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and God himſelf who now ſeem'd to give him a Commiſſion, to reſcue his Church and oppreſs'd People.</p>
               <p>He ſaw the State, in which he firſt drew his Breath, which his warlike An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:51909:70"/>founded, and which he no leſs gloriouſly and miraculouſly had newly raiſed again, into a ſtronger and more beautiful Structure than before, out of (in a manner) a confuſed heap of Rubbiſh, menaced afreſh by the ſame crafty and powerful Enemy, back'd with another potent Popiſh Ally, in a more formidable manner than ever; he heard from a far, the diſmal Groans of the miſerably af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and tormented <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> and eſpecially of thoſe of his own <hi>Hereditary Principality</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> moſt unjuſtly wreſted from him; and what infinitely more ſenſibly touch'd him, the Slavery and more than <hi>Aegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptian</hi> oppreſſion of his natural Subjects, crying to him for Juſtice, and ſaying, Help, O thou mighty Prince of Valour, and nurſing Father of God's true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Church; it is high time for to lay to thy powerfull and bleſſed hand, for popiſh Judges and Seminaries have made void our Laws, Rights and Privileges.</p>
               <p>He found the ruine of his Country le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd at, through his Auguſt ſides; and that the <hi>Gallick</hi> Tyrant would never par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don him, the unexpected raviſhment of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:51909:71"/>his ſtollen and perfidious Conqueſts; nor the truly generous and <hi>Princely</hi> refuſal of purchaſing a Sovereignty by the betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his own Country; nor the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, ſmarting and diſgracefull blow, he received from him before <hi>Mons;</hi> nor his obſtructing an uncomely peace at <hi>Nime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guen;</hi> nor finally his happy Match with a moſt accompliſht and amiable Princeſs of his own Blood, when the ſubtil Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur leaſt thought on't, and whom he had laid cloſe Intrigues and ſubtil Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems (had not they been Providentially prevented, by a ſpeedy concluſion of that bleſſed Marriage) to have ſpirited or ſtollen away, and made a Sacrifice to the black Intereſts, concerted between him and her Father, which was to have been the great Iſſue of that numerous and ſplendid Embaſſy of <hi>French</hi> Lords, not long before preceeding; had not God in his Mercy to our Nation prevented it, by making the late King <hi>Charles,</hi> as much inclin'd as he was otherwiſe, to favour them; to balk all their Projects by that ſudden and contrary jerk of Policie, which put them for the preſent, quite out of countenance; and which all their Jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles knew not how to prevent.</p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:51909:71"/>
               <p>He likewiſe ſaw plainly, that whereas beſides the unpardonable crimes againſt the greatneſs of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th. and the bigotted Inclinations of his Uncle and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-in-law, he was ſenſible he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a Third, which was greater than all the reſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Obſtinately refuſing to give his Aſſent, and Conſent, to take off the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> and give a new <hi>Magna Charta of Liberty</hi> to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts of <hi>England,</hi> to ſupplant and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Rights and Liberties of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; He was therefore by thoſe whoſe threatnings were never vain, when in full power to execute them, menaced, that he ſhould pay dearly for it; and he ſaw they were going in down-right ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to be as good as their Words, by popping up a Child all on a ſudden, to act the Prince of Wales, and put <hi>him</hi> and <hi>his Royal Princeſs,</hi> by the Succeſſion of theſe Crowns, of which they were the true undoubted <hi>preſumptive Heirs;</hi> no leſs unjuſtly than they had depriv'd him of his other poſſeſſions, and all this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to put him out of Power, and make him uncapable to vindicate his own and his poor Subjects former wrongs, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:51909:72"/>any longer with ſucceſs the Re-pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick he had hitherto ſo proſperouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended; to revenge the unſpeakable op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the people in <hi>France,</hi> or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port or retrieve the Proteſtant Religion, and civil Rights and Liberties of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and warlike people of Great <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain;</hi> whereof he appeared a kind and powerful Defender, and who were his undeniable <hi>Subjects in Reverſion,</hi> and whoſe Intereſts he ſeem'd reſolv'd zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly to eſpouſe, and as ſtiffly to defend as his own.</p>
               <p>And when he ſaw the people of all Ranks and Qualities, and of all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Intereſts, in the three Kingdoms, but one (to wit, the Papiſts) with one common and earneſt mind and voice, call to him as next undoubted Heir at Law, to take care no Damage might be done by the preſent Poſſeſſour, in the Lands of his Succeſſion; to reſiſt the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Uſurpation, or Alienation intended by a Suppoſititious Child, and the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Intrigues of a Jeſuited Step-Mother; and in a word, to redreſs all the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Wrongs and Oppreſſion of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; to ſave the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:51909:72"/>and the civil <hi>Liberties of all Europe,</hi> which depended chiefly in that dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Juncture, upon the Preſervation of Great <hi>Britain</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Confederacy from becoming a P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey to the overgrown Monſter of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the loſs of all which, and of the vaſt Detriment, that would have thence happen'd to ſo many millions of precious Souls, and to the publick <hi>Weal of all Chriſtendom,</hi> he would have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly thought highly guilty; had he neglected ſo many forcible Calls, and indiſpenſible Obligations, both of Nature, Duty, and Intereſt.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, when beſides all theſe ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtible Motives, he conſidered, that the danger was extreamly preſſing; that <hi>Ireland</hi> was already Haltered, and bound as a Sacrifice ready to be offered; <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſtrongly manacled, and the intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Chains juſt ready to be thrown o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>England</hi>'s Neck; and the terrible glittering Sword drawn out, and ready to be Brandiſh'd againſt himſelf and his Republick; and that unleſs he would reſolve to ſtrike the firſt Blow, it would be too late to ſtrike at all. And Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:51909:73"/>that unleſs he made an attempt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>England,</hi> while his Allys had Forces and time to ſpare for his aſſiſtance, and the Armies in <hi>England,</hi> as well as the people of all ſorts, were in a Condition as well as Diſpoſition, to ſecond his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and excellent Efforts; that the very next Spring perhaps, ſome of the Allys might find an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army upon their Frontiers, intermixt with <hi>French;</hi> and an Army of Frenchified <hi>Switzers,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh Tories,</hi> in poſſeſſion of <hi>England;</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Fleets, maſters of the Sea, aſſerting the Greatneſs of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th; and <hi>Holland</hi> and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, ſwallow'd up by a ſudden inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, breaking violently in upon them on all ſides, before they were aware; or that their neareſt, and moſt powerful Allys, could come up within ſight, much leſs within reach enough to give them any Aſſiſtance; I ſay, when our wiſe and preſaging Prince, now his moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty, ſaw, and duly weighed all this, how loath ſoever he were to do any thing, that might bear the leaſt Shadow, or Semblance of ill; or that might ſeem to violate, that Tenderneſs
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:51909:73"/>and Reſpect, he had naturally for an Uncle and a Father-in-law, of that great Quality: Yet now, when not only his private <hi>Intereſts</hi> lay at ſtake, but the publick Happineſs and Well-fare of ſo many <hi>Myriads</hi> of <hi>Souls;</hi> ſo many King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Territories, ſome of which, he had ſuch an indiſpenſible Obligation to take care of, were in ſuch extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary preſſing Danger, and Honour of Conſcience, even of King <hi>James</hi> himſelf, baſely beſlur'd and abuſed, by ſo groſs a Cheat put upon him, by the ſubtil Intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues of Jeſuits, and his Jeſuited Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort, in prejudice of his own <hi>Natural and undoubted Iſſue,</hi> in order to the inſlaving Him, as well as his Subjects, every whit as much to the Caprices of <hi>France,</hi> as he is now; and to the manifeſt greater pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril of his Life, than ſince has happen'd by the attempts his people would have made againſt the Intrigues of his Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; had not they found a far more regular, and legal Aſſiſtance otherwiſe. And conſidering that there was no other remedy, but breaking the neck of their miſchievous Proceedings, by ſome ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and ſurprizing Maſter-ſtroke of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:51909:74"/>and Policy; He now ſtood no longer, conſulting with Fleſh and Blood, and parling with the unſeaſonable reaſonings of the tenderneſs we have been ſpeaking of; but fully reſolve with all Expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to prepare for the prevention, and happy redreſs of ſo great a ſtorm of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils; as otherwiſe he foreſaw would moſt inevitably fall upon <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Holland:</hi> Yea, on all the greateſt part of <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But leave we our Gracious Prince a while, making his war like Preparations, and ſtuffing his ſtately Wooden Horſes, with fierce courageous Troops, not to Burn, but to ſave our otherwiſe loſt <hi>Troy;</hi> and make a ſtep back to <hi>England,</hi> to ſee how all things there concurr'd and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, to meet his moſt noble En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, and Crown his ſo glorious and heavenly Enterpriſes, with a bleſs'd Succeſs beyond all Expectation.</p>
               <p>If we come then to examine things there likewiſe, we ſhall ſtill find that our Royal <hi>Heroe</hi>'s Enemies, whilſt they were plotting his Deſtruction, and the enſlaving of theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> under a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Yoak of Popery, and Arbitrary pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:51909:74"/>which were both to Cent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Subjection to the Tyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nny of the <hi>French</hi> King; made Tools of themſelves, by an Over-ruling Providence not only to ſave, but to exalt them, whoſe utter ruine they really deſign'd; and even lift them up, to ſuch a Power, as to be able to throw down their New Erected <hi>Babel</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and to ſhake the very Foundations of their Old one, ſo long ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led (even) in <hi>France</hi> it ſelf. For the late King <hi>James,</hi> beſides the Miſtakes and Faults which he had all along fallen into, and daily perſiſted to commit; for want of diſcerning his own true Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts from thoſe of <hi>France;</hi> and, for lack of ſeeing the Bottom of the <hi>French</hi> King's Deſigns, made all other ſteps, that his Enemies could have wiſh'd him to take, towards the bringing upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Swift Deſtruction; and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of that Warlike-Prince to the Throne of <hi>Great Britain:</hi> which, againſt the ſtrong Obligations of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and without any ſenſe, or regard of his own highly injured honour thereby, his late Majeſty ſhamefully went about, by the ſubtle Stratagems of Jeſuits and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:51909:75"/>Prieſts, to bereave him and his Royal Conſort of.</p>
               <p>For beſides his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ing ſo openly with <hi>France,</hi> and moſt highly diſobliging thereby the reſt of the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Powers, as we have related; And beſides the Broad-Signs he had given, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king War upon <hi>Holland,</hi> on pretence of their having Aſſiſted the Duke of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> and <hi>Argile,</hi> and of ſome other New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarted Complaints of the <hi>Dutch</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt our Merchants at <hi>Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipatan,</hi> &amp;c. and in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> whilſt the Injuries done our People dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the <hi>French</hi> about <hi>Hudſon</hi>'s <hi>Bay,</hi> and elſewhere, and in the Inſults they daily received by the <hi>French</hi> Privateers, and Men of War, almoſt every where, were paſſed by unregarded, and without any redreſs; And beſides the particular threats he had made againſt the <hi>Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince of Orange;</hi> he had Diſſolv'd that <hi>Parliament</hi> that had ſo zealouſly ſtood by him againſt the late D of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth;</hi> not only becauſe they would not grant him a Fund of Money to maintain a Standing Army, above the Regulated number of Guards, and Garriſons, in
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:51909:75"/>time of Peace, Contrary to the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Government; But rather becauſe, forſooth, they would not let them be Mann'd, and Commanded by as many Popiſh and Foreign Officers and Commanders as he pleas'd to ſtuff them with.</p>
               <p>After this, he continued and put in as many Popiſh Commanders, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours into his Army, Ships and Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; And as many Popiſh Juſtices of Peace into all <hi>Towns, Burroughs</hi> and <hi>Cities,</hi> all over <hi>England,</hi> as he could: And, in favour of that proceeding, ſo contrary to Law and Juſtice, orders his Judges to Declare <hi>a Diſpenſing Power,</hi> to be one of his Royal <hi>Prerogatives,</hi> in prejudice to the Privileges of the Two Houſes, and even of his own Power in <hi>Parliament.</hi> And deals with all the Artifices imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, with all Qualified Perſons, both Clergy and Laity of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to induce them to Conſent to the Repealing of the <hi>Penal Laws and Teſt;</hi> to the Countenancing of his Diſpencing Power, and the keeping up of his Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Army, and putting down the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia; and when he ſaw them averſe to it;
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:51909:76"/>though he had but juſt before, moſt high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incens'd the Diſſenting party, by his MOST BLOODY, and Severe Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of ſo many Hundreds of them that had been engaged with <hi>Monmouth</hi> and <hi>Argile;</hi> and though he knew them all bred up in an Inveterate Averſion to <hi>Monarchy;</hi> Yet he, moſt Impolitickly, Quits his Beſt Friends, that had Set the Crown upon his Head, becauſe they would not humour him in things viſibly tending to his own overthrow, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, as well as theirs; And has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe by Fawning, and moſt Unkingly, Mean, and Abject Sollicitations, to thoſe very Diſſenters, whoſe BLOOD he was ſtill REAKING with; Thinking to do by them, his Sworn Enemies, what he could not get done by his Friends, and weaken both them and the other Party with Diviſions, till he could reduce them both, by his Third Growing party, of <hi>Engliſh, Scotch, Iriſh,</hi> and Foreign <hi>Papiſts,</hi> to be his Abſolute Slaves: To this end he New-models over again thoſe <hi>Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi> both he and his late Deceaſed <hi>Royal Brother,</hi> had but lately Modell'd before; and taking away all the Old
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:51909:76"/>
                  <hi>Charters,</hi> gives out New ones, by which, all true <hi>Church of England</hi> Men, who ſtood for the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſt,</hi> were ungratefully turn'd out; and Diſſenters, and ſuch as had been turn'd out before, were intruded in their places; Think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby to have ſuch a Packt <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as would take away thoſe Laws, and Deſtroy the <hi>Church of England,</hi> by laying it open, in Common, and Defence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; and make Room for the Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of <hi>Popery and Deſpotick Power,</hi> when it ſhould be leaſt apprehended. He Granted out Commiſſions, for the vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and calling to Account thoſe, that in the former Reign, though really ſet on by the Intrigues of himſelf, and his own Party; had vigorouſly executed the Laws then in force againſt Diſſenters; and that, not ſo much out of Righting the Diſſenters, for the Exactions that had been made upon them; Or Reim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſing them, or the Crown, for what was pretended to have been extorted from the one, and detain'd from the other; but meerly to raiſe New Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities between the two Parties, and make the Diſſenters, though but for their own
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:51909:77"/>Ends, willing to be his Tools, in the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Deſtruction which he intended to both.</p>
               <p>And to this end, of his own Single Authority, by virtue of the Diſpencing Power he procured to be inveſted in him, by Eleven Judges, though in ſpight of the Unanimous <hi>Senſe of Parliament,</hi> ſufficiently declared againſt it, in the time of his <hi>Late Royal Brother, King Charles the Second,</hi> he gratifies them, by a Declaration for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> which ſome of them, though they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted with ſeeming Joy, and Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and being no leſs skill'd in the Art of Diſſimulation, than his Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor F. <hi>Petres,</hi> and imagining it good po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy to flatter him, as he flattered them, according to that common ſaying, <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere fallentem non eſt fraus;</hi> thereby to find the eaſier Means to work their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, both upon him and the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and <hi>Eſtabliſhed Church;</hi> Yet, the Major part of them received it rather with Silence, than any apparent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or Applauſe; and ſeveral of them, like true <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and brave <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> expreſs'd plainly their diſlike of it,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:51909:77"/>and Renounc'd ſuch an Opportunity of expreſſing their Reſentments, againſt the Ancient and True <hi>Reformed Church of England,</hi> by any proceeding, that was like to prove ſuch a Tool for the Erecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Popery, Slavery,</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Power;</hi> and rather began then to have better thoughts of the Eſtabliſh'd Church here, than ever before: When they ſaw her Chief Members ſo ſtifly to ſtand up, and Defend the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> againſt the Mines, as well as the open Attacks of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Abſolute Power;</hi> and to refuſe all manner of Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> or any Complaiſance though to their then King; that might any way evacuate the <hi>Law,</hi> or put them under any Suſpicion of their being capable to give up their Common Intereſt; and ſaw well enough, that it was the real Effect of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues of a Court-party, influenc'd and biaſs'd by deſigning Popiſh Emiſſaries; and not the <hi>Body of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that had rais'd againſt them thoſe Severe Proſecutions, under which they had ſmarted ſo much; Yet ſome Merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Men were gain'd among them, and,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:51909:78"/>to the no ſmall ſurpriſe of the World, the old Monthly Obſervator, that had ſtuck ſo cloſe to Prerogative, as to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get almoſt the Intereſts of his Church, was now laid aſide: And the late Mr. <hi>Henry Carr,</hi> that had formerly Written the Packet from <hi>Rome;</hi> and had, in the moſt invidious and provoking manner imaginable, expoſed all the Intrigues of the Popiſh Agents; and all the Actions, and whole Conduct of that King, when Duke of <hi>York;</hi> and had ſerv'd, as a Trumpet, to the whole Party of the Excluſioners; was now Courted, and Brib'd, to Blazon forth the Graciouſneſs of the New Declaration for Liberty, and to Write, in Exchange, for their Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator.</p>
               <p>The like Proceedings were acted in <hi>Scotland,</hi> where <hi>Deſpotick Power,</hi> and <hi>Abſolute Authority</hi> was Aſſum'd, with a more Imperious Air; and then were our <hi>Gazettes</hi> ſtuff'd, with thoſe many <hi>Fulſome Addreſſes,</hi> that Nauſeated all Men of Senſe of both Parties; The hands to which, were moſt of them Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born'd, and hired; and the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds and Thouſands, that were not
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:51909:78"/>Named, ſet down with a Bold Stroke, indefinitely, <hi>Cum,</hi> &amp;c. Though no where yet Exiſting, but <hi>in Nubibus;</hi> and which indeed, though they pretended to have devoted their Lives and Fortunes to the ſervice of their New Benefactor, for the Gracious Liberty he had Granted them, yet proved but Troops of Air in his time of Need; the Main Body of the Diſſenting Party Wiſely Concurring with that of the Church, to wiſh well to the Arms of the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> and, in <hi>Scotland,</hi> doing indeed themſelves the whole Work for him.</p>
               <p>And though the Church-Party would not give their Conſent, to the taking off the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws;</hi> Yet he had ſome hopes, they, and eſpecially the Major part of the <hi>Clergy</hi> among them, would at leaſt have gone ſuch Lengths in Paſſive Obedience, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance to Prerogative, as to have been tamely ſubmiſſive with the diſpenſing with them; and not to have withſtood the Declaration for Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: But when he found by that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute <hi>Letter to a Diſſenter,</hi> and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Writings,</hi> Publiſht on that occaſion,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:51909:79"/>that they Diſavowed all Complaiſance with him, <hi>in thoſe Points;</hi> that no Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes of Thanks, excepting one or two, came from any of the <hi>Church of England Party,</hi> upon the ſubject of that Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and that notwithſtanding the many ſham <hi>Addreſſes,</hi> wherewith he ſought to Delude himſelf, and the World; the Beſt and Wiſeſt part of the Diſſenters Rejected his <hi>Declaration;</hi> as harbouring a <hi>Secret Snake</hi> in the Graſs, and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand ſided with the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in Diſavowing any <hi>Liberty</hi> not Granted <hi>in Parliament:</hi> He was extreamly Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie, and many Projects were offer'd to him, by his <hi>Cabinet Councellours,</hi> to Ward the Miſchiefs theſe ill ſymptoms Threaten'd, and make himſelf obey'd.</p>
               <p>According to ſome of theſe Advices, to Revenge himſelf upon ſuch of our Clergy as ſtood Tight to the <hi>Proteſtant and Engliſh Intereſts,</hi> by the means of ſuch of them, as he thought would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, which ſtill he imagin'd would be the Major part; and to make them, as his Jeſuits phraſed it, <hi>To eat their own Dung, by forcing them to Excert an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, or elſe to feel the ſmart of their own
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:51909:79"/>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> the Principles of which he miſtakingly fanſied would have car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Main-Body of the Clergy; Juſt as great and extravagant lengths, as ſome Tantivy-Court-Doctors, among them at that time, had laid out for them; and, have perſwaded them, that the ſame Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and Unlimitted Obedience, was owing to the Bare Commands of the King; as to the Acts of the <hi>Three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates,</hi> viz. <hi>King, Lords and Commons,</hi> in which alone, is the fulneſs of <hi>Supream Legal Power, and Authority;</hi> and to which alone conſequently, the <hi>Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Chriſtian Duty of Abſolute Active, or Paſſive Obedience</hi> is due; And that they were to ſubmit, as blindly and tamely to the King, acting without, or againſt <hi>LAW,</hi> as by and with it; and that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, or Paſſive Obedience, was as much due to the King, out of, as in Parliament; and to a Word of his, an Order of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, or a Proclamation, as to an Act of Parliament; I ſay, erroneouſly thinking that the Major part of our Churchmen were as much ſeaſon'd, with thoſe Miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Notions of Paſſive Obedience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as ſome <hi>Court-Doctours,</hi> by aſs'd then by
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:51909:80"/>the Jeſuits, and ſome of their Unthink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Followers ſeem'd to be; He reſolves to Adminiſter to the whole Body of the Clergy, ſuch a <hi>Doſe,</hi> or <hi>Pill,</hi> as ſhould infallibly ſearch and try the Temper of them all; and therefore preſently gives Order to all Miniſters, Paſtours, and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, <hi>To Read Publickly in their Churches his Declaration,</hi> for liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>But finding that, Contrary to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, not onely Seven of our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal, and <hi>Right Reverend Biſhops,</hi> had the Zeal and Courage, to Addreſs him againſt that Declaration, as Illegal; and to Proteſt they could not Comply with his Commands in Reading it, <hi>becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Law, as well as their Conſciences;</hi> And that the Main-Body of the Clergy, throughout the Kingdom, influenc'd by their Noble Example, Refuſed likewiſe to Read it, and that <hi>in Nine thouſand, and ſome Hundreds of Pariſhes, there are in</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Wales, <hi>beſides Collegiate-Churches and Chappels,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>there were ſcarely</hi> 500 <hi>Clergy-Men in all</hi> that were weak and ſupple enough to Comply
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:51909:80"/>with his Orders in that Matter; He and his Cabal were much inraged, And yet at their Wits end, what Meaſures to take; How to Remedy ſo great an Evil, and how to proſecute a whole Body of Men, ſo conſiderable, as that of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy. They had not long before that ſet up, though contrary to an Expreſs Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> a <hi>New High Commiſſion;</hi> thinking thereby to have awed the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and have Diſciplin'd them ſo, as to have diſpoſed them for a Ready Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with the Declaration that was to follow; And which, had they Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Was to have been the <hi>Dead-doing-Stroke to the Churchof England:</hi> By which <hi>High-Commiſſion,</hi> they Cenſured and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived, <hi>the Right Worthy and Magnanimous Prelate, the preſent Lord Biſhop of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> Notwithſtanding his, and his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Families great Merits towards the Crown, and ſeveral other worthy Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy Men; Which Bold Attempts upon the Subjects Liberty, and <hi>Prerogative of Parliament,</hi> did not a little move all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Ranks of Men in the Kingdom, and rather made them far more ſtiff, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Compliance with the leaſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:51909:81"/>made towards taking away the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſt;</hi> and, with the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration</hi> for <hi>Liberty,</hi> than any ways frightned, or diſpoſed them to it.</p>
               <p>Which made the Popiſh Cabal, tho they reſolv'd to deal rigorouſly with the <hi>Addreſſing Biſhops,</hi> whom they commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Tower, not dare to employ the Authority of their pretended Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt them any more; But rather to Impeach them at Law, which, when they were baffled in, they ſignified ſuch indiſcreet Rage and Spite, at their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment, that they could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear letting the whole <hi>Body of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants throughout Great Britain,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſee,</hi> that from thenceforwards they were minded, without ſeeking any more Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella's, or Diſguiſes of Law and Juſtice, to proſecute their Revenge by Main Force; and by Military and Dragooning hands to effect, what they could not do by their <hi>High-Commiſſion,</hi> or any courſes at Law.</p>
               <p>I need not mention their Practices, in endeavouring to Poyſon the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains that were to feed our Poſterity, by Erecting Popiſh Schools and Seminaries
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:51909:81"/>in divers places; and by endeavouring to ſtuff our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> with Roman E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries; Nor the violences uſed towards thoſe who withſtood them: As to thoſe of <hi>Magdalen College,</hi> and others, becauſe all thoſe were but leſs matters, in compariſon of what they did afterwards to the <hi>Right Reverend the Biſhops;</hi> and were going to do to the reſt of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and therefore ſhall only proceed, to hint upon thoſe other Extremities they openly, in the face of the Sun, at laſt were driving us upon; And which even forc'd the whole Nation, moſt Juſtly, in its Neceſſary Defence; after they had, out of an Exceſs of Reſpect to the <hi>Late King,</hi> born, till a Remedy was within an Ace of being too late, the Inſolences of a few deſpicable, hot-headed Jeſuits and Monks, influenc'd by the <hi>French</hi> Father <hi>la Chaieſe;</hi> whoſe blind Unthinking Paſſive Tool, <hi>P. Peters</hi> was; to call for Aſſiſtance to the Next Preſumptive Heirs of the Crown.</p>
               <p>Theſe then were their further Deſigns upon the Clergy.</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:51909:82"/>
               <p n="1">I. To New-Rate all <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, and make them pay Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruits, Tenths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to their preſent yearly value, and not according to the old Rates.</p>
               <p n="2">II. To examine at their <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſion,</hi> the ways and means uſed by Clergy-Men poſſeſs'd of Benefices, to come into them; and if they could be charged with the leaſt appearance of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> to deprive them, and give their Livings to Popiſh-Prieſts, or formerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd Nonconformiſt Miniſters, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers devoted to their Intereſts, to hold by Diſpenſation, or otherwiſe.</p>
               <p n="3">III. To Noſe the Conformable Clergy, by allowing a Right to Papiſts and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, to keep publick Regiſters, and to pay but half-Dues to the Pariſh Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters for burying.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. To nominate no New <hi>Proteſtant Biſhops,</hi> or other Eccleſiaſtical Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in place of thoſe that ſhould die; and to foiſt in as many Popiſh Prieſts
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:51909:82"/>and Diſſenting Miniſters, as they could into all <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Benefices</hi> that ſhould be vacant from time to time, who were to hold them by Diſpenſation, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them by conforming Curates, till they ſhould be ſtrong enough to eſtabliſh Popery by open Force.</p>
               <p n="5">V. To have the Juriſdiction of vacant <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> adminiſtred by Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and their Revenues employed for maintenance of Popiſh <hi>Biſhops, Prieſts,</hi> or <hi>Seminaries,</hi> &amp;c. As likewiſe the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue of all vacant <hi>Deaneries, Prebend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips,</hi> &amp;c. And to obtrude as many Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh School-maſters as they could, into all vacant Free-Schools, with ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther projects.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. To remove all Cauſes from the <hi>Biſhops Courts,</hi> to their Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſion.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. After ſome time, to ſieze the Cathedral of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s when it ſhould be Built, and the Abby of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> for Popiſh uſe, allowing only the Dean and Prebends, in caſe they quietly abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:51909:83"/>the poſſeſſion of them, their full Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues during life.</p>
               <p>Theſe things were really intended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Clergy, over and above what was actually already done; but then to Curb the Laity of all Degrees, theſe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Meaſures were concerted to put in Execution, as faſt as they could.</p>
               <p n="1">I. A new Court like that of the Star-Chamber, though under a diſguiſed name was to be erected.</p>
               <p n="2">II. To Awe and Balance the Power and Intereſt of the Metropolitan City of <hi>London,</hi> without the rougher Methods of a <hi>Tower</hi> or <hi>Garriſon,</hi> &amp;c. It was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd, to erect the City of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> into a Corporation, like to that of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> to be govern'd by a Lord Mayor, Aldermen, common Council, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with as ample Privileges, Immunities and Freedoms, as the ancient City of <hi>London</hi> enjoys; in order to invite People of Wealth and Trade, as great Merchants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to ſettle there as well as in <hi>London,</hi> and thereby to cauſe an Emulation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, that might keep both
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:51909:83"/>Cities tight to the Crown, or at leaſt to keep that of <hi>London,</hi> from being potent enough alone to conteſt any more with their King, or make too ſtrong a party againſt him.</p>
               <p n="3">III. The Militia when they durſt, were to be all Diſarm'd, and the Money levied for the maintenance of them, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed for that of a ſtanding Army.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. In caſe the <hi>Parliament</hi> to be call'd after the new model of Corporations and Counties, that then was endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was finiſhed, anſwered not expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Then a Parliament was to be packt, after the method of thoſe of <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s, compoſed moſt of Army Officers, Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, and ſuch others as they knew were diſpoſed, vigorouſly to concurr with all projects to the ruining of the publick Liberty.</p>
               <p n="5">V. After things were come to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> was to be declared unneceſſary and pernicious; and all <hi>Legiſlative Authority,</hi> to reſide in the King, and a ſelect Council of Lords and Gentry.</p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:51909:84"/>
               <p n="6">VI. In order to this, the Army was by degrees to be new Modell'd, and ſtuft with <hi>Engliſh, French, Scotch</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, or Perſons indifferent in Religion, or of none at all, with ſome Diſſenters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And all Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Men by little and little put out of the Council, and out of all places of Truſt both Civil and Military.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. That moſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces, ſhould be on ſome ſuddain pretence, ſhipt over into <hi>French</hi> Service, and reimplac'd by as many <hi>French,</hi> who with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing a greater number of <hi>Engliſh, Scotch, Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, and Popiſh <hi>Swiſſers,</hi> were to conſtitute the King's Guards, and the ſtanding Forces of <hi>England.</hi> And <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> were to be guarded by natural <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and ſuch others of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> or <hi>Scotch</hi> extraction that were Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. A new Court of Wards was to be Eſtabliſh'd, by virtue of which, all Minors and Infants being brought under the King's <hi>Tutelage,</hi> ſhould be brought up in the Romiſh Religion; as was
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:51909:84"/>already begun to be practiſed in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But notwithſtanding all theſe At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts upon the Rights and Liberties of the Subject, contrary to poſitive Law, his own Solemn Promiſes, and his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation Oath, ſo extreamly affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, were the beſt part of the Nation to the perſon of their Prince, and ſo wholly averſe to the contributing any thing, to the embroiling theſe Nations, a ſecond time in Civil Wars, as being ſo very ſenſible of the miſeries of the laſt, whoſe deep Scars ſcarcely well healed, yet remain'd in view, not without hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour before their Eyes, and reluctancy on their Spirits.</p>
               <p>That they were very hardly and with much difficulty induced to believe any thing of their King, that ſavour'd of an ill deſign; and when they were convinc'd of it by infallible Proofs, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Teſtimony of their own Senſes, together with Church and State now ſmarting under the Burthen: Yet would they have thought it their moſt dutiful, ſafe and wiſeſt Courſe, tamely to ſuffer
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:51909:85"/>almoſt any Inconveniences and Inſults from him, rather than to involve the three Kingdoms in freſh dangers, by any active Reſiſtance; eſpecially conſidering that he was already well ſtricken in Years, and could not Reign long.</p>
               <p>Had not they ſeen thoſe very Princely Heirs, and <hi>Nurſing Parents to the Church,</hi> in whom they repoſed all hopes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, treated after the ſame Injurious manner, as the Subjects; and not only Menac'd, but plainly going to be both for ever excluded of their Succeſſion, by a <hi>Jeſuitical impoſture, or a ſuppoſititious Prince of</hi> Wales, and driven even from their preſent poſſeſſions, both in the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> as they had new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been already from thoſe in <hi>France,</hi> by a formidable Invaſion; and that they (namely the Subjects) were to be made Tools of both for their own Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that of thoſe pious famous and moſt gracious Princes, from whom on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under God, they hoped for Relief and Deliverance. And had not they had perfect Information, by means of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſadour, as aforeſaid, of all the Intrigues and Stratagems, laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:51909:85"/>the Rights of thoſe <hi>Dear and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-beloved Princes,</hi> the hope of the Proteſtant Church throughout Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as well as againſt their own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Civil and Religious Liberties; and eſpecially, receiving perfect intelligence of the whole proceſs of that Impoſture, of putting upon them now a Suppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Heir, and had not King <hi>James</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his too precipitate Councellors, taken very much pains to convince them, that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Intelligence was very true to a Tittle in all particulars; and had not the League with <hi>France</hi> to deſtroy <hi>Holland,</hi> and the manifeſt ſteps made then by our Court, towards its Execution, beyond all Contradiction, demonſtrated to them that ſuch Chains were (of a truth) prepared for them, as would not be of a few years conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but would be very laſting, and impoſſible to be ſhaken off, if once who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put on: And that they were juſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be thrown about their necks, if not prevented, without further dallying in that very Nick of time.</p>
               <p>For at the ſame time, a pretended Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> was ſtarted up, they
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:51909:86"/>found their Pillars of the Church, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Reverend Biſhops, and the main Body of their Clergy fiercely attack'd; <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Proteſtants there, put wholly under <hi>Deſpotick Power,</hi> Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Diſpoſitions,</hi> and the mercileſs <hi>Mercy</hi> of cruel implacable <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts; <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> wholly ſubjected allready, under an open faced <hi>Deſpotick Authority;</hi> the brave <hi>Engliſh Proteſtant Nobility,</hi> thoſe Ornaments of our Kingdom, for the moſt part ſlighted, and their Sage advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, not at all heeded in Council; but all ruled by a Popiſh <hi>French</hi> Cabal, headed by <hi>P. Petres</hi> and Mr. <hi>Barillon,</hi> and all Church of <hi>England</hi>-men already diſplaced, or going to be removed, not only from Civil Employments, but as we have ſhew'd from Military ones too, both in the Fleet and Army; and when the Army it ſelf, which was to have back'd all theſe proceedings, ſaw, that for only oppoſing the foiſting in of <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Papiſts among them, their moſt Eminent Captains and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, though highly deſerving in the late time of need, againſt the Duke of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> were treated no better than the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:51909:86"/>Biſhops: That the illuſtrious Princeſs <hi>Ann</hi> of <hi>Denmark</hi> her ſelf, was ſo imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and diſdainfully handled, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe, nor any Perſon from their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Highneſs's, the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> though ſo very highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, ſuffered to be preſent at the Birth of the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales.</hi> But that on the contrary, War was plainly preparing againſt the <hi>Hollander,</hi> in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence forſooth; but in reality and indeed, againſt the precious Perſons of the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> whom they lookt upon at leaſt, as their <hi>Sovereigns in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion;</hi> and that they were to be ſent over Seas they knew not where, to fight <hi>French</hi> and Popiſh Quarrels, never more to return, whilſt their places were to be ſupplyed here, by <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> and other Popiſh Forces; I ſay, when the <hi>Army</hi> ſaw themſelves thus treated, and were convinced there were further deſigns, laid as deeply and maliciouſly againſt them, as againſt any other body of men in the <hi>three Kingdoms,</hi> and ſaw an Image of their future fate, by what they beheld already done to the late ſtanding Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to ſome
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:51909:87"/>of the beſt of their own Officers; and when they ſaw they began already to be diſtruſted, and yet that the Court had gone ſo far, in the affairs of the Biſhops, and the body of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> both Clergy and Gentry, that in all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance the Lawyers having refuſed to do them the Juſtice, pretended in the Tryal of the <hi>Right Reverend Prelates;</hi> they would now have recourſe to a <hi>French</hi> Army, aſſoon as ever they had ſeen but a good part of the preſent one gone away, and the Poſt new Modell'd.</p>
               <p>They, (<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army) rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily concurr'd with the reſt of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that is to ſay, Thoſe of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, Nobility and Gentry, in ſending in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionally if not actually to the Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to come, and (im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately under the Lord of Hoſts) to undertake their Relief and Deliverance; and thus a good part even of the whole Nation, and of the Army and Fleet too, even by the very proceedings of their Enemies, though much contrary to their Intentions, diſpoſed to wiſh ſucceſs to the moſt generous undertaking of our modern <hi>CONSTANTINE;</hi> who in
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:51909:87"/>Compliance with their hearty deſires, and the powerful <hi>Call of Self-preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as well as the Defence of his own Rights, with the zealous Aſſiſtance of the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> and of the moſt Serene Prince, the Elector of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> and ſome other generous Allies, provided a brave Fleet, conſiſting of <hi>Sixty five Men of War, five hundred Fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boates, ten fire Ships, ſixty Pinks, and as many Scheling Boats,</hi> &amp;c. A good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to be before hand with the <hi>French,</hi> and their Creatures in <hi>England</hi> too, ſet ſail in the midſt of Winter from the <hi>Brill,</hi> and whilſt he was coming, and after his firſt Landing, was ſtill further favour'd, by the following Actions and Behaviour of his Enemies.</p>
               <p n="1">I. For upon the News of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs's intended coming, King <hi>James</hi> to augment his Army, ſending for conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Numbers of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, and ſome <hi>Scotch</hi> Highlanders, and viſibly ſhewing more confidence in them, than in his own Native <hi>Engliſh;</hi> made an end perfectly of alienating the hearts of his <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army from him, and gave them
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:51909:88"/>moſt juſt grounds to fix their affections on the expected and bleſſed Prince, the hope of <hi>England</hi>'s beſt People; nay cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thém now to believe entirely all that had been told them of the late King <hi>James,</hi> and his Jeſuits Deſigns, and <hi>Frenchified</hi> Prieſts Intrigues, againſt them.</p>
               <p n="2">II. When our mighty Prince had ſet ſail the firſt time, and was repuls'd by a grievous Tempeſt, the good Providence of the Lord turn'd even that to his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; for having had the Prudence to publiſh in the <hi>Harlaem</hi> and <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> Convent, that his loſſes and detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by that grievous Tempeſt, were greater much than they in reallity were. And making a face of things as if his grand Deſign was thereby quite balked; it was very eagerly and readily believed, eſpecially by the Court Cabal of Jeſuits and Prieſts; nay, they imagined them ſtill greater than was reported, and thereupon became ſo very ſecure in their own thoughts, that they concluded all danger paſt, and thereby ſtill more and more alarm'd the whole Nation, and
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:51909:88"/>kept their inclinations the more firm and cloſe, unto their Great and Heaven in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired Deliverer. For that hot headed party, now as openly bragg'd in every Coffee-houſe, that God had defeated the <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and that the Noiſe of that Expedition, had only given the King a fair opportunity to increaſe his Army, wherewith he would now make himſelf Abſolute; and by the help of them, and the <hi>French</hi> together, chaſtice the proud Biſhops (as they fooliſhly call'd them) and the whole Church of <hi>England,</hi> and their Abettors, the Lawyers too; rout out the daring Prince out of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> and exterminate the States of <hi>Holland</hi> as an unſufferable Preſident, of proſperous Rebellion, and of pernicious Conſequence to all Princes.</p>
               <p>And among other Troops, they juſt now raiſed a new Regiment of Horſe-Guards, all notorious Papiſts for the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the cuſtody of his Perſon to them only, and to the <hi>Iriſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. After the renown'd Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> and his Forces were happily land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:51909:89"/>at <hi>Tor-bay,</hi> and had given Directions for the ſpeedy landing the reſt, and the Canon to be unſhip'd for the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency at <hi>Topſham;</hi> the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Council, as influenc'd by the <hi>French,</hi> adviſed him to neglect ſending the body of <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Soldiers, in which he confided to attack the Princes Force, while they were ſo fati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued and diſabled, with the bitter Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age they had undergone, and were not as yet, re-inforc'd by any <hi>Refreſhments</hi> or <hi>Reſt,</hi> or join'd by any Male-contents (as they call'd them) out of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, or from the late King's own Army; and rather to ſtay till he could aſſemble his whole Army, and provide a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent train of Artillery, ſtore of Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and be ready to March a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them in Perſon to give them a formal Battel; which muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, gave our renown'd Prince a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient opportunity, to refreſh his Men and Horſe, and recruit what were wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; and likewiſe to ſuch as were well affected to him in the Countrey, and in the King's Army, to go over to him.</p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:51909:89"/>
               <p n="4">IV. King <hi>James</hi> by a ſtrange Fate, though ſo much <hi>Frenchified,</hi> yet being over perſwaded not to become too much dependant of the <hi>French</hi> King, refuſed till it was too late, to receive a <hi>French</hi> Army, though often preſs'd to it by <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillon;</hi> inſomuch that the <hi>French</hi> King finding he could not have his Will, to have a <hi>French</hi> Force admitted, ſtrong enough to Maſter both <hi>England</hi> and its King, and to have the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of his own, to fight his Quarrels on the other ſide, gave the aforeſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to the late King <hi>James,</hi> not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tach his <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> againſt the Princes wearied Forces, for fear his <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Army taking exceptions thereat might Rebel, and ſeize his Perſon in the mean time; but to march with his whole Army againſt them in Perſon, where one Nation might awe the other, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> might have leſs cauſe of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, ſeeing ſome confidence ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in them; and the Kings preſence might keep them all in due <hi>Decorum</hi> and <hi>Obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>French,</hi> though fearing ſome would deſert him, yet thought that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:51909:90"/>would ſtill ſtay with the King, to keep up a Civil War, which would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and <hi>Confederates</hi> at leaſt of the Forces they had lent for that Expedition; and which was more, of the Conduct of ſo great a General, as the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and force King <hi>James</hi> the next Summer, to admit what num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>French</hi> to help him, he ſhould pleaſe to offer; and which he thought, he could eaſily ſend him by his own Fleet, with that part of King <hi>James</hi>'s that ſhould remain firm to him, and ſo he ſhould have his long deſired ends at laſt.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Becauſe King <hi>James</hi> had ſo ſtiffly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed a <hi>French</hi> Army for that preſent, and to part with his Engliſh, the <hi>French</hi> King in hopes that the late King would how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever find Friends enough, to keep the valiant Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and his Forces employed for ſome years, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to aſſiſt the Confederates, and make both <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Prey to him at laſt; though he were in actual War with <hi>Holland,</hi> and had a numerous Army near their Frontiers,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:51909:90"/>yet forbore to make any Attempt upon them, for fear it ſhould hinder the Prince and his Forces from going for <hi>England;</hi> and ſo deprive him of the ſundry advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages he hoped to reap, by that Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>So true a Friend was he at the Bottom, to his poor deluded Ally's Intereſt, and ſo very much miſtaken in true Meaſures for promoting his own, by an over-ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling hand of Providence.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. And laſtly, the ſtrange unmanly fear, and unſteadineſs that appeared in the late King <hi>James,</hi> when he had the greateſt occaſion, to ſhew that Courage and Conduct, he had alwaies before pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to; in not appearing firm to ſtand by thoſe, that otherwiſe, in all probability would have ſtood to him; even among the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces, as well as among the Nobility, Clergy and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and his actual deſerting them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards gave the laſt finiſhing Motion to the mighty and memorable Revolution that followed.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee, all theſe ſeveral ſteps of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s very Enemies,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:51909:91"/>though directed as they thought by the beſt, ſafeſt and righteſt meaſures of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Policy againſt him, were all made by the Providence of Almighty God (who taketh the Wiſe in their own craftineſs, and will ſuffer no enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt <hi>Jacob</hi> nor divination againſt <hi>Iſrael</hi>) to contribute to the more aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſpeedy ſucceſs of our noble Prince Enterpriſe, ſo very juſtly and lawfully undertaken, by a loud Call and Commiſſion from Heaven in his own Defence, and likewiſe in the Defence and Safety of the People, Church and Cauſe of God.</p>
               <p>And by theſe ſtrange means, it came to paſs, that the magnanimous Prince, ſetting ſail a ſecond time from <hi>Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voet-ſluys,</hi> with a proſperous Gale, though he ſuffer'd much again with his people afterwards, by rough Weather, and the incommodities of Landing in ſuch a place, and his firſt uncouth Marches; yet Landing upon the 5th. of <hi>November,</hi> in the famous Year, 1688. juſt 100 years after the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Invaſion, and on the Anniverſary of the <hi>Gun-powder Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> as if deſign'd and ordain'd by <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:51909:91"/>to deliver us, both from the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Contrivances of a Faction within us, and the approaching inundation of the <hi>French</hi> without us, now much more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable than <hi>Spain</hi> was then, in leſs than ſix Weeks time, entred <hi>Triumph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly into the Palace of our Capital City,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by almoſt univerſal Conſent of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding joyful Nation, of all Orders, Ranks and Degrees, inveſted on the Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary of the Nativity of our Lord, with the Adminiſtration of the Government; as if by Divine appointment, preordain'd to be a temporal Saviour to theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to all his choſen People; <hi>and by the peculiar Deligation and Commiſſion, of that King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, that Rules over the Kingdoms of Men, and gives them to whomſoever he will:</hi> And then after he had by the general deſire, and humble importunity of the Subjects, called a <hi>Convention of Eſtates,</hi> was by them on the 13th. of <hi>February,</hi> 1688. conjointly with his Royal and virtuous Princeſs, declared the Rightful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted King and Queen of <hi>England, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſoon after of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:51909:92"/>
               <p>The late King <hi>James</hi> by ſending his Queen and pretended Son, into <hi>France</hi> into the hands of a known Enemy of theſe Nations, and who had been the cauſe of all their manifold grievances; and by retiring thither afterwards, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily of his own accord himſelf, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given infallible Evidence, to all the ſober part of the Nation, that the Birth of that pretended Prince, was too dark a Contrivance to endure the clear light of a publick Examination in <hi>Parliament,</hi> and made all other expedients of reſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the ſhaken Government, redreſſing the multiplied grievances of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and doing right to the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted <hi>Preſumptive Heirs of the Crown,</hi> altogether impracticable.</p>
               <p>I forbear to inſert here, all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of his advances, towards the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting ſo great and happy a <hi>Revolution;</hi> becauſe they are freſh in the memories of all, and are known even to ſuch as are but only mere ſtrangers to us in theſe daies. And becauſe I have already exactly enough, related them in my late <hi>Diary,</hi> of that <hi>Memorable Expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> 1689.
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:51909:92"/>To which for thoſe points, I refer my Readers: The concluſion of all was, that Their Majeſties were on the 11th. of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril</hi> following, moſt Solemnly Crown'd at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> by the <hi>Noble and moſt Reverend Father in God, the Biſhop of</hi> London, <hi>aſſiſted with other Biſhops, to the great and inexpreſſible Joy and Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> of all their People; the Terrour and Amazement of their Enemies, and the Wonder and Surpriſe of the whole World.</p>
               <p>A Revolution, which if it were mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous in the Concurrence of ſo many ſeeming contrary, precedent and conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant Cauſes, as we have ſhewed, was no leſs wonderful for the Laudable and Angel-like moderation of the chief in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of it; namely, of the People and of the Gracious and Heavenly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted Prince and Princeſs, to whom they humbly and earneſtly Addreſs'd. For the People had ſo much Affection and Reſpect to their late King, that they ſuffer'd ſo much, till they were almoſt reduced beyond Remedy, before they would ſeek one; and when they ſought and obtain'd one, ſought ſuch a one, as
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:51909:93"/>was the moſt Natural and Conſonant to the Duty and Reſpect they ow'd their King, that could be Imagined: For they ſought to the next preſumptive Heirs of his own Fleſh and Royal Blood, againſt the falſe Game put upon them and the people, and even upon King <hi>James</hi> himſelf, by the Intrigues of a Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Prince, and a Subtil Popiſh Deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Step-mother, and Second Wife, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Help of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Prieſts:</hi> And that was done, not Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuouſly, or by a Faction; but by the <hi>Main Body of the Nation,</hi> in the perſons of their Chiefeſt Men of all Orders, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and Intereſts, and by as Legal Repreſentatives as the Juncture of Time and Affairs would permit (nay, I may aſſert, that that Moſt Honourable and Auguſt <hi>Convention,</hi> were as Lawful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives, and as Able Men, as the whole Kingdom could afford) And by their, Now, Moſt Excellent Majeſties, with ſo much Softneſs, Care and Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to the Perſon of the Late King, as infallibly declared to all Mankind, that they (yet) had preſerv'd no ſmall ſhare of Affection, and Reſpect for him. So
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:51909:93"/>much, as it plainly appeared ſince, he would not have reſerv'd for them, had he but prevail'd, or got them within the Verge of his Power. For, as our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Gracious Queen, then Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> had earneſtly intreated Her dear Lord and Husband, the Prince, to be very careful in all the Courſe of His Expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of the Perſon of Her Father; which was back'd with the Inſtances of the Confederate Roman Catholick Princes. Thoſe Counſels, and Intreaties were, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, ſo very conſentaneous to His own Sentiments, and Innate Inclinations, that he moſt readily and punctually ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and performed them. For, when the Late King was ſeized and inſulted by the Mobb at <hi>Feverſham,</hi> as he attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in Diſguiſe, to have made his Eſcape, and paſs the Seas; He was very ſenſibly Concern'd, at the Affronts and Indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties done him, and took ſpecial care he ſhould be ſafely Re-conveyed out of the dangers of the then Exaſperated People, by his own Guards to <hi>Whitehall.</hi> And when he ſaw him ſo fully bent to Retire for <hi>France,</hi> Though it were, in many Reſpects, againſt his Own, and the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:51909:94"/>Intereſt; yet he would not croſs him in it. And ſince he was ſo eagre upon it, had him Safe Conducted, by his own <hi>Dutch Guards</hi> to <hi>Rocheſter;</hi> and from thence to a Veſſel he had himſelf under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand provided, to Waft him ſafe where he would be; with private Command, He ſhould not be Moleſted, or Inſulted in his Paſſage, either by Sea or Land: Thus the Late King ABDICATED the Throne, and Retired to <hi>France;</hi> and ſo laudably and gloriouſly concluded this moſt Happy and Wonderful Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:51909:94"/>
            <head>An Appendix; <hi>Containing the Remarkable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences that have continued to Bleſs and Protect their Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majeſties, King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>ſince their firſt Happy Exaltation to the Imperial Throne of</hi> GREAT BRITAIN.</head>
            <p>THE Divine and Unſearchable Wiſdom and Juſtice, having through Two Mighty and Unparallell'd Revolutions, ſafely Conducted His pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſty to the Sovereign Throne of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> And made even the Oppoſitions and Stratagems of His Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Enemies of the <hi>Roman</hi> Faction, as he had formerly made thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:51909:95"/>of the Great <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries and Competitours, the moſt O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perative and Inſtrumental of any other Cauſes, to the Exaltation of him to be a <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that he might be the better able to Combate and Subdue the Enemies of his Church: Has ſince, by ſo many Stupendious Proofs, ſhewed it ſelf ſo particularly careful, as well of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fety and Protection of Both their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Sacred Perſons, as of the Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their Deſigns; which, as they are, without Contradiction, Juſt in their Cauſes, have been all along no leſs Juſt and Glorious in their Ends: As being (without Controverſie) in their whole Aim, directed purely to the Glory of God, <hi>and the Common good of Mankind.</hi> So that we may from thence, without any great Preſumption hope; That the Supream Soveraign of the World, whoſe hand is not ſhorten'd, will not ſtop here; But has intruſted ſo much Clemency, Power and Prudence, in the hands of a Prince of ſuch Matchleſs Moderation, Vertue and Integrity; that it might ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually be made uſe of, to the utter Defeating and Suppreſſing of that Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:51909:95"/>Tyrant, againſt whom He hath begun to give us ſuch a Signal, and Remarkable Deliverance. And we truſt and pray, <hi>That this All-wiſe and inſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Being,</hi> will never lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e preſiding in His Royal Councils, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> going forth with His Fleets and Armies, till he hath by him, as another <hi>Cyrus</hi> or <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> perfected our Deliverance, both from the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Tyranny; and placed the ſtate of theſe <hi>Three Nations,</hi> and of all <hi>Europe,</hi> upon ſo firm and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a Balance, That no One Power on the whole Earth may ever be able to ſhake, or diſturb its Tranquility, in a long Series of years. And till, like His Renown'd Predeceſſor in theſe Iſlands, the Matchleſs <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> He has to the full deſerved the Title of <hi>Reſtitutor Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani Generis,</hi> or Reſtorer of Mankind. To proceed then.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing His preſent Majeſty did, after His Happy Acceſſion to the Throne, was, by the Unanimous and Deliberate Advice, and Deſire of His People, to Proclaim War againſt the <hi>French</hi> King; and enter into a ſtrict En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement with <hi>Holland,</hi> and the reſt of
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:51909:96"/>the <hi>Confederates,</hi> for the <hi>Common Defence</hi> of the <hi>Liberties of Europe.</hi> And though His Majeſty was forced a while to ſtay on this ſide the Seas, till Matters in the Two Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> were ſo compoſed, that it might not be unſafe to leave them; And ſo could not appear for ſome time in Action againſt the Common Enemy. Yet he defeated the <hi>Gallick</hi> Tyrant of his Two great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations, <hi>viz.</hi> (1.) Of ſeeing the Force of <hi>England</hi> once more turn'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Holland;</hi> And, (2dly,) Of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Civil War enſue in <hi>England,</hi> which might give him a fair opportunity, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of Aſſiſting King <hi>James;</hi> of throwing in ſuch a Force, that might, in the ſequel, Enſlave us all. Which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment made the Monſieur to fret in his Greaſe; to think, that by his neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting, when time was, to Alarm the <hi>Dutch</hi> Frontiers with his Army, he had thereby given ſcope to his moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Enemy, to take free and full poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, without hardly any Reſiſtance, on the Kingdoms of his moſt Devoted and Powerful Ally; and now, at beſt, he could no way poſſible divert him, from
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:51909:96"/>turning his Force directly againſt <hi>France;</hi> but by Fomenting a War in <hi>Ireland,</hi> which would be more difficult and expenſive to him, to maintain at that Diſtance, than to King <hi>William.</hi> Yet ſtill he had Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant-like hope, to keep him in play at leaſt ſome years, till the Confederates ſhould be wearied out on the other ſide, and he might, by that means, retrieve all again in <hi>England,</hi> and Re-eſtabliſh his Ally King <hi>James</hi> with the higher hand. But even here too Providence deceiv'd him, and did that Work, as it had done the others before. For our <hi>Victorious King William,</hi> much Quicklier, and by more effectual and ſucceſsful Means, than our Great Heroe himſelf, or any of us all did, or could in Humane Reaſon, or Prudence expect. But though the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Creator</hi> was pleaſed generally to give a moſt ſurprizing Succeſs, to all that our truly Pious and Valiant King enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized in Perſon: Yet, leaſt thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperities ſhould lift up our hearts too high, and make us Attribute too much to our own Strength, they were allay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſome Rubs, in ſome other Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters, where His Majeſty was not,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:51909:97"/>nor could be preſent; As were ſufficient to convince us, That though God did indeed favour the Juſt Cauſe, and Well-intended Deſigns of our Gracious Prince, whom His own Arm had placed over us: Yet, he was ſtill Angry both with us, and our Allies; ſince neither their nor our Arms were ever obſerv'd to proſper ſo well under any other Chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, as that Great Prince, whoſe Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Vertues we might as ſafely Imitate, as His Civil and Warlike Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>England,</hi> 'tis true, had now by this time, excepting a very inconſiderable and diſarm'd Party, unanimouſly Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it ſelf under the Willing Obedience of Their preſent Majeſties happy Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But <hi>Scotland</hi> was ſtill diſturb'd, by the Influence of the late Viſcount <hi>Dundee;</hi> And poor <hi>Irelrnd</hi> was in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner totally under the Enemies Power; and provided with ſuch an Army of Diſciplin'd Natives, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſo well-furniſh'd with Warlike Neceſſaries, and Officers from <hi>France,</hi> that it perhaps could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver boaſt the like, and they ſeem'd at leaſt irrecoverably to have Rent that Kingdom from the <hi>Engliſh Empire.</hi> When
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:51909:97"/>it pleaſed <hi>Allmighty God</hi> to animate a handful of Men, inconſiderable for all things but Undaunted Courage, and Zeal to their Religion and Ancient Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties; when all the reſt of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was already Subjected, to ſhut their Gates againſt a Power, which then ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led every where elſe about them: And even at a time, when they could have little or no hope of Relief from <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or elſewhere; vigorouſly to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend a Town, but meanly Fortified, and worſe Provided; with a kind of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural and Wonderful Valour, againſt a Numerous and Well-furniſht Army, headed by their King himſelf; and able General-Officers from <hi>France,</hi> Renown'd for their Conduct, and to hold it out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Diſadvantages, to the Amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Whole World,</hi> till Relief, though very ſtrangely by many cauſes delayed, much longer than 'twas thought poſſible they could ſtay for it, was brought them; and by that means a Way open'd to deliver that very King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from the Oppreſſours, when they thought themſelves moſt ſecure, and firmly Poſted.</p>
            <pb n="168" facs="tcp:51909:98"/>
            <p>And, indeed, whoſoever well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Vigorous Actions of the <hi>Men of Derry,</hi> and of thoſe of <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> who took Arms about the ſame time, cannot but think they were influenc'd by ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than <hi>Humane Courage:</hi> Whilſt their Enemies at the ſame time, were not only Infatuated in their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, but palled in their Valour, (though they had ſome very good Troops among them, both <hi>Engliſh, Scotch</hi> and <hi>French;</hi> by the unexpected daring Magnanimity of a few true Zealots for Religion and Liberty, whom, looking upon as <hi>Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rado</hi>'s, they durſt not fight with, and yet were as much afraid to let alone. They were Infatuated, I ſay, in their Counſels; For by the very beſt Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it appears, That, if they had Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged <hi>Derry</hi> with their whole Army, and employed their beſt Diſciplin'd, and moſt Warlike Troops to make the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacks, they might eaſily have taken it, before any ſuccour had come: Or, if they had altogether let it alone, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting themſelves only with keeping a Blockade before it, and had ſent a good part of their Army into <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:51909:98"/>Aſſiſtance of the late <hi>Viſcount Dundee,</hi> who was a Commander both of Courage and Conduct, and who had, by his Great Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the Highlands, and other parts, Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed no deſpicable Oppoſition againſt the Government: (I ſay) 'Twas the ſenſe of very Underſtanding Men, as well of our Own, as the Enemies ſide, That if they had, in ſtead of Amuſing themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Derry,</hi> ſent Timely Aſſiſtance to <hi>Dundee,</hi> as he often and earneſtly preſs'd the Lord <hi>Melfort,</hi> they had at leaſt remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Seat of the War out of their own Countrey; and found ſo much Work for King <hi>William</hi> nearer home, that it had been impracticable for Him to ſend any Succours at leaſt that year to the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> any where in <hi>Ireland;</hi> So that <hi>Derry,</hi> and the <hi>Iniskillingers</hi> too, muſt needs have been Reduced at laſt of Courſe, and by Neceſſity, with little or no Fighting. But ſome of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, forſooth, muſt needs, in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Wiſdom, Adviſe the late King <hi>James</hi> to a Medium, by making a ſlow and regular Siege with his worſt Troops, under pretence of teaching theſe Men to be better Soldiers thereby, till by it
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:51909:99"/>he quite balkt and ſpoiled his poor Teagues at firſt daſh, and loſt his Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of Aſſiſting ſo brave a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant as <hi>Dundee</hi> was, and carrying the War into <hi>Scotland,</hi> if not into <hi>England</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Which muſt be confeſs'd by all ſober Chriſtians, was another Inſtance how the <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> as it had begun, ſo continued ſtill to Over-rule the Actions and Councils of the Enemies of our Bleſſed <hi>Joſhua</hi> and Mighty Deliverer, and to make them all Contribute to the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of that Great and Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Work it deſign'd by him, in ſuch a Manner, that the Finger of God might appear in it, of more clear efficacy than the Power and Policy of Man. For, our Good <hi>Theodoſius</hi> was always preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent with God in Prayer; And, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Deus ardenter invocatur, victoria ſtat a Bona cauſa.</hi> Therefore, as <hi>Marcellinus</hi> and <hi>Claudianus</hi> Spake, or Sang of this Battel, we may of this <hi>Iriſh</hi> War, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:51909:99"/>
               <q>
                  <l>O nimium dilecte Deo cui militat aether.</l>
                  <l>Et conjurati veniunt ad Claſſica venti.</l>
               </q> At laſt, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> had ſtrongly Fortified, and Barricado'd the River leading to it; But notwithſtanding all, that Diſtreſs'd Town was Reliev'd by <hi>Major General Kirk,</hi> after the <hi>Dartmouth</hi> Frigat had forced her way to it, over all thoſe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments, and the Siege was effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rais'd. The day before which, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Strange Accident, inconſiderable in it ſelf; But, by the <hi>Guidance</hi> of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, made Inſtrumental to the further Mortification of our Enemies; A choice Body of about 6000 <hi>Iriſh,</hi> Commanded by one of their beſt Officers, Major <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Mackarty</hi> were defeated by about 2000 <hi>Inniskillingers;</hi> by occaſion of a miſtake of the Word of Command a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Iriſh:</hi> For it ſeems <hi>Mackarty</hi> perceiving the Courageous <hi>Inniskilling</hi>-Men Charge the Right Wing of his <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> very deſperately, ordered ſome of his Choice Men to <hi>Face to the Right,</hi> and March to the Relief of their Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; but the Officer who carried the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:51909:100"/>Orders, miſtook, and Commanded the Men, in ſtead of Facing to the Right, <hi>To Face to the Right-about,</hi> and ſo March; upon which, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in the Rear, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Front look with their Faces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, and move, thought they had been running, and ſo immediately in a Terror, threw down their Arms, and run away; which the reſt ſeeing, run af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them for Company, and ſo were moſt of them cut off, or Drown'd in <hi>Lough's</hi> and <hi>Bogs;</hi> and <hi>Mackarty</hi> himſelf taken Priſoner.</p>
            <p>Afterwards, when Duke <hi>Schomberg</hi> went over but with a ſmall Army of new raiſed Men, though, as it uſually hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to <hi>Engliſh</hi> Armies new-raiſed, when they firſt came into a ſtrange Countrey, many of our Men died, and the whole Army was brought into a low condition by bad Weather, Lodging and Diet; nay, and by their own Lazineſs in great part, in not Hutting themſelves like Men more uſed to War. Yet the Enemies had not the Policy or Courage to make uſe of the many advantages they had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us, in that long time that our Army was thus languiſhing. But trifled away
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:51909:100"/>their opportunity, in hopes of the effect of a Plot, laid by ſome <hi>French Traitors</hi> among us, which God ſeem'd to have permitted, in order to encourage them for to flatter themſelves with vain hopes, and to make them paſs over, or ſlip thoſe other ſeaſonable and likely oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities they had to have deſtroyed us. Would they have been contented to uſe fair Force, rather than Treachery, odious to God and Man.</p>
            <p>But to paſs by all thoſe leſſer events, and haſten to the main Action, in which <hi>His Gracious Majeſty</hi> was preſent; And which gave the Great Turn of the Scale towards the Reducing of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>The next year being 1690, His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty King William,</hi> being fully reſolv'd to puſh the <hi>Iriſh</hi> War to an end, or fall in the Attempt; that ſo he might have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, ſolely and wholly, next year, againſt his Capital Enemy the <hi>French</hi> Tyrant, who had brought ſo many Miſeries up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all <hi>Europe,</hi> and had occaſion'd all the Misfortunes of his Deluded Ally King <hi>James,</hi> and having by, the Death of <hi>Dundee,</hi> ſuppreſt, in great meaſure, the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:51909:101"/>Inſurrection, or Stirs in <hi>Scotland,</hi> left <hi>Kenſington</hi> the 4th of <hi>June,</hi> 1690, and Embarking at <hi>Highlake</hi> on the 12th, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd on the 14th ſafely at <hi>Carrickfergus;</hi> And on the 27th of <hi>June</hi> following, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled a Royal Army of about 36000 as Brave Men, as <hi>Europe,</hi> or the World could ſhew; of <hi>Engliſh, Dutch, Danes, Germans</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> provided as well with all Neceſſaries, both for the Mouth and War; as could be deſired. So much of Life and Circumſpection had his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty's Preſence given to all Needful Orders for that purpoſe. When he was arrived at his Army, he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in action, and obſerving the Goodneſs of the Countrey, as he rid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long; he admired the Fertility of its foil, and pleaſing Aſpect of its Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skips; and ſaid, it was well worth fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for. And now, underſtanding that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army was retired over the <hi>Boyn,</hi> He Marched with all ſpeed and diligence after them; And being advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced near the River, hard by a Paſs, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Old-Bridge,</hi> he was ſo Adventurous, as to ſtand on the ſide of a Bank, within Muſquet-ſhot of the Ford, to obſerve the
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:51909:101"/>poſture of His Enemies. Which, though he ſaw well-fenced, and a River not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſable, and that was well-fortified with Canon, and other ſtrong Defences againſt him: Yet, knowing that the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fety of <hi>Europe,</hi> in great Meaſure, at that Juncture, depended upon ſome bold <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Stroke,</hi> in that Countrey; without which, all that he had hitherto done, and ventured for our Reſcue and Security, would be but loſt: He reſolv'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to venture through all Difficulties whatſoever, obeying the Great <hi>Call of Providence,</hi> rather than that ſo Noble and Happy a Revolution ſhould fail for want of Courage in him; Who is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by his Enemies to be a Prince of no ſmall Spirit and Valour, and had made it appear to the World, in all the Courſe of His Life. After he had, with thoſe Intentions, viewed them a while, he was pleaſed to ſit down on the Ground, to Refreſh himſelf; which ſome Principal Perſons of the Enemies ſide having obſerved, they cauſed a ſmall Party of Horſe to advance flowly upon a Plowed Field, over againſt where His Majeſty was, and ſlily to drop two
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:51909:102"/>Field-pieces, undiſcover'd, by a Hedge in the ſame Field, and ſo retired; leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only ſome Gunners to Manage them, who lay ſculking, ſtill and quiet, till His Majeſty was Re-mounted; and, Dreaming of no Danger at all, was Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſoftly back again; But then the Rogues Fired furiouſly, and, at the firſt ſhot, killed two Horſes and a Man, about 100 yards from the King; and, at the ſecond, had like to have given a very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Stroke, both to theſe Kingdoms and the whole Confederacy; by Quenching the Light, Joy and Hope of our <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the Bullet Graſing upon the Bank of the River, and thence Riſing towards the King, with a ſlanting Motion, glanced over His Right Shoulder, taking off a Piece of His Coat; Tore part of the King's Anointed Body; But, being turn'd off ſhort by the hand of ſome Guardian-Angel, Commiſſion'd by the Lord <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> touched not His Precious Life; nor ſo much as gave him any wound grievous enough to hinder Him from continuing with His Army, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the Remarkable Action that ſoon followed. For as ſoon as he had changed
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:51909:102"/>His Coat, and had His Wound dreſſed, He ſpent the moſt part of the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of that Day in Diſpoſing His whole Army for the next day's Work; and then on the Morrow, being <hi>Tueſday,</hi> the firſt of <hi>July</hi> following, early in the Morning, with full Truſt in the Protection of the Lord of Hoſts Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which He had found ſo ſignally at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended His Royal and Sacred Perſon, He very Courageouſly forces His Paſſage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Boyn,</hi> and gives ſuch a ſudden Defeat to the Enemy, though Poſted with all manner of Advantages on the other ſide; That while <hi>Hiſtory</hi> ſhall at all Subſiſt, will never be forgotten, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Friends nor Foes.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not here Deſcribe that Famous Battel, which is ſo well Related by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pens, whoſe Writings are now in every ones hand; but ſhall onely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark the <hi>Chain of Providences,</hi> that ſeem'd ſtill continuedly to run through that whole Tranſaction, as well as the precedent ones.</p>
            <pb n="178" facs="tcp:51909:103"/>
            <p>It is enough to ſay, that in it, <hi>the King behaved himſelf,</hi> as always on the like occaſions, both as a valiant Soldier, and a wiſe General.</p>
            <p>And though ſome out of pure Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to his Royal Perſon, have preſum'd to accuſe him of Raſhneſs, in expoſing himſelf both to the Accident of the common Shot, and venturing upon ſo deſperate an attempt, as the paſſing ſuch a ſcurvy River as the <hi>Boyn,</hi> at ſuch vaſt diſadvantages; yet when it ſhall be well weighed, that the <hi>French</hi> at that time, had given a very ſmart blow to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, at <hi>Flerus</hi> in the Netherlands; that by Treachery or Cowardice, or both among our ſelves, they had in ſome ſence beaten the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleets, ſo that they hover'd daily about our Coaſts.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Scotland</hi> was not quite appeaſed, and <hi>England</hi> at that time big, as was ſtrongly preſumed of a horrible Plot, ready to break out upon the landing of any number of the Enemy, who were now (as 'twere) Maſters of the Seas, and were thought in a poſture after <hi>Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> Battel, to have been able to ſpare
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:51909:103"/>Men enough for ſuch an Exploit; and when all <hi>Holland</hi> was in an Uproar, at the ſuppoſed foul Play they believed they had received from the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in the late Sea Fight; and the all of the whole Confederacy, ſeem'd to depend of ſome fortunate ſtroke from him. Inſtead of taxing our Valiant and Politick Prince with Raſhneſs, we ought rather to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire and adore God's goodneſs, in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring him with ſo much Courage, fit for ſuch an extraordinary Occaſion at that critical time. And impute the ſtrength and laudable warmth of his Faith in God, and Zeal for his glory and ſervants good, in his victorious Majeſty, in taking a Reſolution to fight at all Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards on that preſſing occaſion, to be a call of Providence; which for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intereſt, he moſt willingly obeyed, relying confidently upon the Protection of the Almighty alone, to go through with his undertaking.</p>
            <p>Moſt certain it is, that he thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd both us, and the whole Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy, from another very low ebb of Fortune, the publick Enemy would elſe once more have reduced us to, and put
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:51909:104"/>himſelf and them in a condition the next year, to carry back Terrour to the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing Foe. But there was ſtill as I find by very credible Evidence, another main reaſon, that urged a neceſſity for this Battel.</p>
            <p>For that upon the News that Sir <hi>Cloudſly Shouel</hi> after he had landed his Majeſty, was order'd to ſail immediately with his Squadron, to join the Grand <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet, and that all our Ships with Proviſions, and other neceſſaries for the War, were left in <hi>Carrick-Fergus Bay,</hi> with little or no Convoy.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> were ſending ten ſmall Frigats, and ten Privateers into the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel to burn them; which if it had been done, then all our Communication from <hi>England,</hi> had been cut in a manner off, and our Army forced to ſubſiſt upon the ſmall pittance they could find in a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted Countrey, or elſe ſtarve; or at leaſt we had been debarr'd of thoſe neceſſaries, without which we could not have made any Defence, nor Offence in War. And this deſign of the <hi>French,</hi> being made known to His Majeſty, who wanted not good intelligence, and that the <hi>French</hi> and
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:51909:104"/>
               <hi>Iriſh</hi> Officers, as truſting in the Succeſs of that Stratagem, unanimouſly agreed to retreat towards <hi>Athlone</hi> and <hi>Limerick,</hi> in hopes that they ſhould have King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> and his Army a much cheaper Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni-worth, when they were half ſtarv'd, than at that time; and though King <hi>James</hi> was againſt that motion, yet for fear they ſhould over-rule him and be gone, and the <hi>French</hi> ſhould in the mean while, execute their Exploit. His Heroical Majeſty is ſuppoſed upon that as well as other Conſiderations, to have haſten'd the Battel; in which theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing things ſeem further very much reſembling peculiar effects of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; the one was, That in the Fight out of an imprudent complaiſance to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who would have the Poſt of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> foot were ſet to guard the chief Paſſes; whereas, had the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Scotch,</hi> or <hi>French</hi> been put in their places, 'tis generally thought the attempt would have been much more doubtful.</p>
            <p>And the ſecond was, that the late King without ſtaying to rallie his Forces, who were many of them ſtill entire, made haſt to <hi>Waterford,</hi> where meeting
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:51909:105"/>with ſome of the <hi>French</hi> Ships, deſign'd to burn our Proviſion and Ammunition Veſſels; he told them 'twas too late, for all was loſt, and ſo put them quite off the deſign; whereas had he let them have proceeded, they might ſtill have done us that miſchief. That together with the news of the defeat at <hi>Flerus,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> being maſters at Sea, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after arriv'd among the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> too, after he and thoſe Ships were gone, might have ſtruck fair to have put them in a Condition to recover their Loſſes, and repay themſelves doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>In fine, the ſudden and unexpected arrival of King <hi>James</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> after the <hi>French</hi> King had juſt before raiſed his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd peoples Expectations ſo high, as to make them believe King <hi>William</hi> was dead; quite ſlurr'd the mighty Monſieur, and made him appear very ſneakingly, and little to his own people, and moſt ridiculous to Foreigners, and every way much broke his meaſures.</p>
            <p>After which laſt puſillanimous and ſhamefull fight, the late King fell into as great Diſreputation among the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> as
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:51909:105"/>he had before gain'd upon his firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion among the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army. <hi>Sars<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> not long after ſpeaking of the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at the <hi>Boyn,</hi> ſaid thus much to the Honour of King <hi>William,</hi> and contempt of King <hi>James, That if we would change Kings, they would fight it over again and beat us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, at the firſt ſeige of <hi>Limerick,</hi> as his gracious Majeſty was riding ſoftly towards <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s Fort, had not his uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al good Angel, by God's Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment preſerv'd him, he had been like to have been taken off by another fatal ſtroke. The aforeſaid ſudden arrival of the late King <hi>James</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and the ill Character he gave of the poſture of affairs there, and of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> as Men that would not fight, was the cauſe that the <hi>French</hi> King, even after King <hi>William</hi> had raiſed his Siege before <hi>Limerick,</hi> and was departed for <hi>England,</hi> ſent po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Orders to Count <hi>Lauzun,</hi> with all his <hi>French</hi> to quit <hi>Ireland</hi> and return home, whilſt there appeared freſh hopes of recovering in part their former loſs, and of protracting the War, at leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſively in <hi>Connaught;</hi> though after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:51909:106"/>upon better Information, he ſent counter Orders, when it was too late.</p>
            <p>I ſhall mention but two more Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, and then follow His Majeſty to another Scene.</p>
            <p>Another great Blunder the <hi>French</hi> committed, was, That following the <hi>Iriſh</hi> more than their own Intereſt, which muſt be acknowledged a fault not very uſual with them; they neglected to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie <hi>Kingſale,</hi> one of the moſt commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Havens, for the convenience of their Fleets in the World, and whereby they might have extreamly annoyed our <hi>We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern</hi> Trade, and ſecured their own Ships of War upon all Accidents; and amuſed themſelves with fortifying <hi>Limerick,</hi> which could be of very little or no uſe to them in that Juncture. And ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, after ſo much coſt and pains beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon <hi>Limerick,</hi> they neglected to ſend the neceſſary ſupplies to it, till 'twas too late, and thereby left King <hi>William</hi> at full Liberty to turn all his whole Force towards themſelves in <hi>Flanders,</hi> as he has done ſince. Theſe I conceive, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering all circumſtances, <hi>are moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Marks, of an Almighty and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:51909:106"/>Power,</hi> that directed the Counſels of the moſt Politick Court in the whole world, upon thoſe occaſions to our mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous Prince's advantage, and even made them contribute very much to the ſpeedy Reduction of a Kingdom, they had the greateſt inclination and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the World, to preſerve ſure foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in.</p>
            <p>The next year being 1691. His moſt Excellent Majeſty, met and faced them in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and though he was not ſo Fortunate, as to hinder them from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Mons,</hi> yet he acted ſo Wiſely and Valiantly, as to let the whole World ſee, 'twas none of his fault that as brave and bold a ſtroke, was not ſtruck there in Defence of that, as at the <hi>Boyn,</hi> and he kept the formidable Enemy all that Campagne, in ſuch Awe and Terrour, that their old Fox <hi>Lnxemburg,</hi> as able a General as he is accounted, durſt not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Battel, ſo long as he continued with the Army, though it were ſeveral times offer'd him with advantage; but only to ſave his Credit, indeed when King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> was gone, at the cloſe of the Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne, he fell briskly upon the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:51909:107"/>Rear, though he got nothing at all by it. That his haughty Maſter, might have at leaſt, ſome ſhadow of a Pretence, to keep up his deſponding Peoples ſinking Spirits, with the Noiſe and empty Sound of a pretended Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But to paſs by that unactive year, when they would not let His Majeſty come at them, neither by Sea nor Land, and come we to this laſt Campagne of, 1692. which was remarkable for the Enterpriſes of <hi>three Kings,</hi> all ſtiling themſelves Kings of <hi>France,</hi> viz. <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> King of <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> at the head of the Confederate Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King before <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur,</hi> with an Army of about 130000 <hi>French, Iriſh,</hi> and <hi>Swiſs,</hi> and the late King <hi>James</hi> at the head of 15 or 16000 <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> on the Coaſt of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy,</hi> with a Popiſh Plot in <hi>England</hi> to favour them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Flanders</hi> was now filled with above 300000 armed warlike Soldiers and 100000 Horſe, and the Sea covered with two of the moſt Numerous and Glorious Fleets, that ever beſpread the Ocean, conſiſting of above 150 great Men of
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:51909:107"/>War, the moſt Beautiful and Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent that ever were; eſpecially, the <hi>French</hi> Royal Sun: The great Sea-won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Age, admired by all for the Beauty of her Shape and Proportion; the curioſity of her Painting and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, the Number, Size, and Quality of her Guns, and the incomparable rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of her Gilding; which made her of very great value, and emboldened her preſumptuous Maſter to inſcribe on her this proud Motto; <hi>Je ſuis L'unique ſur L' Onde Comme mon maitre eſt dans le monde.</hi> i. e. I only on the Sea command, as my Maſter doth on Land. And both the <hi>French</hi> King, and the late King <hi>James</hi> truſting to ſuch vaſt Forces by Sea and Land, but more to their dark Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, thought they had taken ſuch ſure and infallible Meaſures, not only to reduce <hi>England</hi> to King <hi>James,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the <hi>French</hi> Power, but even to have blown up the whole Confederacy, with one Summers Effort, that they bragg'd of it publickly before all the World as of a thing done, and declared by their Miniſters, in the <hi>Northern Courts,</hi> that their deſigns were ſo ſurely laid,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:51909:108"/>that nothing but God could defeat them. Which Arrogancy, the King of Kings and Lord of Lords, not ſuffering, by the ſequel ſhewed them and us too, that his own omnipotent Arm defeated them of the main and moſt wicked aims they le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd at, leaving to men, only to do the remainder of the Work that had been inſignificant without thoſe happy inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening Providences.</p>
            <p>For whereas the <hi>French</hi> King truſted indeed, ſomething upon the intrigues of ſome Traytors in <hi>Namur,</hi> and among the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and very much upon his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſant Force by Sea and Land. Yet he repoſed much more conſidence, in the Execution of theſe four following Projects, for which he thought he had taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible meaſures, if any of which, and much more, if all had taken effect, he had moſt certainly compaſs'd his moſt pernicious ends, either in whole or in great part.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The firſt was, to get out his Fleet before the Confederates Fleets were join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if it were poſſible; and land an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of 15 or 20000 Men in <hi>England</hi> to join with the Jacobites here.</p>
            <pb n="189" facs="tcp:51909:108"/>
            <p n="2">II. If they could not do that time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, at leaſt to debauch a part of our Fleet, to deſert and come over to them, and then to beat the reſt, and land their Army, and at leaſt to raiſe a Civil War here, that ſhould detain King <hi>William,</hi> till they ſhould ſubdue the reſt of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Netherlands.</p>
            <p n="3">III. To ſeize our moſt gracious Queen <hi>Mary</hi> by the help of the Party, form'd by them here, in order to that end, and tranſport her into <hi>France,</hi> to be made a Sacrifice to that Tyrant's Intereſt, or if they could not otherwiſe ſecure her, moſt Barbarouſly to aſſainate her.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. And laſtly, moſt barbarouſly to kill our gracious Deliverer, King <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> any manner of way. The firſt of theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Their getting out their Fleet, and landing an Army before ours could get to Sea, was only (all men know) hindred by God himſelf; who ſent not only contrary Winds in the Chanel, which hindred the Fleet they had in the Ocean, from approaching us, but even ſhattered their other Fleet, in the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:51909:109"/>with ſuch an horrible Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, That two of their biggeſt Ships, were miſerably wreckt, and the others kept back, that they could not come in any time to join the reſt in the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, to prevent the diſmal overthrow they afterwards received.</p>
            <p>The ſecond was diſappointed by their failure in the firſt, and ſtedfaſt fidelity of our Officers and Seamen; but the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comſiting or overthrow of our Enemies at Sea, though the Courage and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of our brave Admirals and Seamen, had, it muſt be own'd, no ſmall ſhare in the Execution of it; was in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure cauſed by a lying Spirit, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Mouths of the <hi>Jacobite</hi> Correſpondents, of thoſe two <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Kings; and by telling them what Sea-officers they had gain'd, and how generally the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sea-men were alienated from their Majeſties King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> for want of Pay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which perſwaded them to ſend Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Orders to their Fleet, though ſcarce 50 Sail of Capital Ships, without ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their <hi>Tholoun</hi> Squadron, to fall upon ours, which was much ſuperiour
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:51909:109"/>in Number and much more in Quality, of Experienc'd and Courageous Officers and Seamen, which proved an almoſt incurable Blow, to their power at Sea, and daſht all their Projects upon <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> into pieces, loſing them 25 of their biggeſt Ships, ſome thouſands of their beſt Sea-men, and particularly their gawdy Sea Idol, the <hi>Golden Sun,</hi> that had been the work of twenty years, and had coſt more than the Revenues of ſome Kingdoms, which was Sacrified to the Flames in a few Minutes, as an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt perhaps of the Future Fate, of that preſumptuous <hi>Phaaeton,</hi> its Maſter; who ſo injuriouſly to the Bright Sun in the Firmament, and its moſt glorious maker, has ſo long uſurp'd the Title, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Sun, though like the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter he imitates, he has been Famous for nothing, but ſetting the World in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming Blaze, and laying ſtately Palaces and Cities, into ruinous heaps.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, as for the Plots againſt both Their <hi>Sacred Majeſties Royal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> which, had they ſucceeded, had proved more fatal to theſe Kingdoms; nay, to the Common Intereſt of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi>
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:51909:110"/>than all the reſt: Can we pretend to have detected them by any foreſight of ours? If any of us do; it is more than I am confident <hi>Their Majeſties</hi> themſelves will; who thankfully own, that even when they thought of no ſuch matter, the Execrable Deſign, and Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical Plot againſt <hi>His Majeſties Royal Perſon,</hi> was very Providentially Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by one of the Accomplices: I pray, Who detected it, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the All-ſeeing-Eye, and Searcher of the Heart, when 'twas ſo very nigh its Execution? That it ſtrikes a Great Horrour in good and honeſt Men, and makes my hands to ſhake, and joynts to tremble but to think of it.</p>
            <p>So that the <hi>French Nero</hi> had ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to brag, his Meaſures were ſo ſurely laid, that none but <hi>Almighty God</hi> could defeat them. For I conceive 'tis plain, and without Controverſie, That none but the Almighty Being could Mollifie one of thoſe Obdurate Sons of Violence, and bring him to ſo much Remorſe, or Compunction, as generouſly to detect his Comrade in Iniquity: Who, to the ſhame, and eternal Ignominy of
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:51909:110"/>that Grand Engine of Satan, the <hi>French Tyrant;</hi> ſufficiently proved by his Chief Miniſter of State's own Hand, who ſet them on Work. And had not this Diſcovery (ſo cloſely laid as 'twas) been timely made, Alas! What would our Fleets or Armies have ſignified? but to Contribute the more to our Swift De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, by the Mutual Jealouſies and Diviſions, attended with Confuſion, that would have enſued among them, upon ſo very Diſmal an Accident? The ſame <hi>Providence</hi> is no leſs Remarkable, in the Detection of the other Plot, againſt our Vertuous and Pious Queen, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment here: Yet ſo very Gracious and Merciful have their Majeſties been, even to a kind of Crime, That none but their Princely Hearts would Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That none but <hi>Granvale</hi> himſelf, that Hell-hound, who was to have Aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our Sovereign King <hi>William,</hi> was Executed, for all theſe Horrid Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances. And therefore, as we are in Duty bound to Pray; So we may, with Aſſurance hope from thence, That thoſe Darlings of Heaven, who are ſo
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:51909:111"/>very averſe to all Cruelty, will never fall by it; But that the Angel of the Lord will ſtill Encamp round about their Sacred Perſons, to Protect them from all Dangers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus all theſe <hi>(Four)</hi> Fine Projects, to the Great Grief of that Falſe Court, were rendred Abortive, by the <hi>Care of Heaven.</hi> However the <hi>French</hi> King, what by the help of his Golden Lewiſſes, and Inteſtine Treachery; And the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonableneſs of the Weather, hindring our Great Prince from approaching to Attack him, took <hi>Namur;</hi> God not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing perhaps to deſtroy this Grand Enemy of His Truth and Peace at once, for Reaſons known to himſelf; but to let this Proud <hi>Pharaoh</hi> have ſome encouragement, ſtill to venture upon ſome other Enterpriſe; till the Harveſt of his Abominations is full ripe for the Sickle, and to make his final Ruine and Deſtruction ſo much the more Remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as it is longer deferr'd. However, that very ſame year, at the enſuing Battel of <hi>Steenkirk,</hi> Our Heroical King ſhewed <hi>Monſieur Lewis</hi>'s General <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> That neither Hedges, nor Ditches, or
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:51909:111"/>any other Fences, were always ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Obſtacles againſt True Valour, once Reſolv'd, and fully Provoked; and made the <hi>French</hi> feel that day, that He was Born on Purpoſe, to be a Scourge to their Inſolence; and beat down their Pride. Since, with but a part of His Army, he had put them ſo much in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a Total Defeat; that had not ſome Accidents, or Miſtakes, hindred the coming up of the reſt of the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Forces, the Date of the <hi>Greatneſs</hi> of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth, had, in all probability, Expired, with the end of that fierce and Bloody Battel. Which, by the loſs of ſo many Officers, Nobility and Gentry as were there ſlain; made the Drapers of <hi>Paris</hi> regain no inconſiderable part of the loſs of Trade they had ſuffered by the War, and ſecretly Sing Jubilate to the Courageous <hi>King William of Great Britain,</hi> their Benefactor; whilſt their Lordly Cuſtomers Sung a Melancholick <hi>De profundis.</hi> Neither was Providence, in this hot Action, one of the Bloodieſt, and Fierceſt ſince the War, leſs mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of His Majeſties Royal Perſon, ſo dear to a Multitude of Nations, than it
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:51909:112"/>had been, upon all other Occaſions, tho he was expoſed to the continual Fire, both of the Great and Small Shot of the Enemies; and was as deeply as any Engaged in the Warmeſt part of the Medley, from the Beginning to the end.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> with a Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Navy, and more Powerful Army than ever yet, already <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uſht in <hi>French</hi> Blood, and Fired with Indignation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were laſt time ſo unluckily Robb'd of their Victory that was before them, had not ſome of the Confederates made a Falſe Step; is Prepared once more to March againſt the ſame Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and to Attack them briskly in their moſt ſenſible part, even in their own Countrey; of whoſe Heroical pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, if any Prognoſticks may be made, without offending the <hi>Moſt High God,</hi> I think, in Humane probability, we may promiſe our ſelves all proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Succeſs (if the National Crying Sins do not hinder it) ſince Providence has already been pleaſed to give us ſome Earneſts and Pledges of the Continuance
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:51909:112"/>of her uſual Favours; that ſeem to me to Promiſe Greater Proſperity than ever to our <hi>Mighty Monarch's</hi> Vigorous En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours for the Common Good. Since, the Monſieurs have been terribly baf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled at <hi>Rhineberg,</hi> by the Exceſſive Rains, that gave time for Succours to advance, and the Troops of <hi>Heſſe</hi> to come up. And the reſt of their Winter-Work in <hi>Flanders</hi> has been utterly ſpoiled, by the ſudden and Prodigious fall of the late Snows; And their Deteſtable Plots, the one upon <hi>Piedmont,</hi> and the other upon the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet, in the Poſt of <hi>Naples,</hi> moſt ſtrangely diſcover'd, juſt in the Nick of Time; The one, by falſe ſteps of ſome of the <hi>Plotters;</hi> and the other, as we hear, and are inform'd, by Advice from the <hi>Pope</hi> Himſelf; as much <hi>Frenchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> as ſome report him to be; but ſix bare hours before the <hi>French</hi> Squadron appeared there. And their <hi>Mediterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean</hi> Fleet, almoſt as roughly handled, and as much Damag'd, by another late Dreadful Tempeſt, as 'twas the laſt year by our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Navy, being now driven back again, in a very ill Plight to <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon:</hi> Where it muſt Refit, before it can
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:51909:113"/>Rejoyn their Fleet in the Ocean; to the Great Retarding, and I Hope, and Pray, to the Total Defeating of their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Deſigns at Sea this year. And their Land-Forces are in ſuch ill-plight, by the Foreſaid Diſappointments; that (through God's Mercy to theſe Nations) they never were ſo backward in the Field as now: And therefore having loſt the Sole Advantage almoſt, they had always over us, of taking Places, as well as the Field before us; We may juſtly hope, that the <hi>French Pharaoh</hi> and his Armies are near an Overthrow; and their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperities not far from a <hi>Period:</hi> And that the Eternal God, whoſe Eyes run too and fro, throughout the whole Earth, will ſtill be pleaſed to ſhew Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Strong in the Behalf of our Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King (whoſe Heart no doubt is perfect towards Him) and make all His Noble Enterprizes to Succeed, till He hath once more added the Ancient Crown of <hi>France</hi> to the Three <hi>Britiſh</hi> Ones, which He already has Given Him: Or, at leaſt, that God of His Great Goodneſs will lower it, ſo that it may pay Due Homage to <hi>England</hi> again; And be out
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:51909:113"/>of a Condition any more, to Diſturb the Tranquility of God's Church, and the Civil State of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>GOD Save KING <hi>WILLIAM</hi> And QUEEN <hi>MARY.</hi> AMEN.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
